Accounting

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Accounting

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours (unless pursuing CPA or MPA) for the degree; 21 hours for the major

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–for CBA students only

DESCRIPTION

Accounting and Business Law

Director: Paul Shoemaker

Professors: Brown, Shoemaker, Smith

Associate Professors: Allen, Crabtree, Lawrence, Ruchala

Assistant Professors: Seavey, Tanyi, Wan

Associate Professor of Practice: Cosgrove

The School of Accountancy is separately accredited by the Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business (AACSB). The School’s mission is to create an academic environment that enables student and faculty development into effective and ethical accounting professionals. In accomplishing its mission, the faculty fosters integrity and ethical behavior to protect the public interest. More specifically, the School of Accountancy community accomplishes its mission in advancing accounting education through:

Fostering intellectual curiosity, academic excellence, business insights, and accounting expertise;
Creating high-impact, relevant research; and
Engaging and collaborating with professional communities.

The courses in accounting are designed to give business students a basic proficiency in accounting as an analytical tool for understanding business and public affairs and to develop essential theory and application for those specializing in the field. Students who complete the College of Business Administration program with a major in accounting and/or the master of professional accountancy degree (MPA), are well prepared to accept positions in industry, commerce, government service, or public accounting.

Students interested in the accounting discipline are strongly encouraged to work closely with faculty members in the School to understand requirements and options available for those interested in careers as certified public accountants and options to pursue the five-year, Master of Professional Accountancy program. Requirements and processes vary with each of these options.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

Other Admission Requirements

Enrollment in the Masters of Professional Accountancy program will require admission to the graduate program after obtaining senior standing and having completed the accounting courses normally required in the junior year (ACCT 308, ACCT 309, ACCT 313, ACCT 314, and BLAW 372). See the online Graduate Bulletin for admission requirements specific to the Business Interdepartmental Area.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 21 hours of course work for the major.

All students will complete ACCT 201 and ACCT 202 Introductory Accounting I & II, 3 credit hours each as part of the Business Core Foundation (BCF).
ACCT 306 Survey of Accounting, for 4 credit hours may be an alternative option for actuarial science majors and for non-accounting majors transferring in with junior standing and excellent academic performance (by permission only).
All students interested in the bachelor of science degree with a major in accounting will take BLAW 372 Business Law I as part of the Business Core Intermediate requirements (instead of BLAW 371).
Enrollment in many of the accounting courses requires certain grades in prerequisite courses as well as enrollment in a sequenced order. Refer to course descriptions for prerequisite requirements.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
Accounting majors are exempt from taking the International Business Course requirement as part of their degree requirements.

Specific Major Requirements

Bachelor of Science in Business Administration–Major: Accounting

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in accounting will complete 21 hours of course work for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M).

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting II

ACCT 410 Auditing

ACCT 412 Federal Tax Accounting

ACCT Elective (selected from):

ACCT 404 Advanced Accounting

ACCT 408 Advanced Managerial Accounting

Master of Professional Accountancy

As part of the College Requirements and Major Core Requirements, students interested in pursuing the master of professional accountancy degree will complete 150 hours consisting of College Degree Requirements (including enrollment in BLAW 372 in place of BLAW 371) plus the following courses:

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting II

Courses listed under the senior year

Courses listed under the masters’ year

Enrollment in the Masters of Professional Accountancy program will require admission to the graduate program. The application should be completed the semester before graduation with the bachelor of science degree.

Students should work closely with the Graduate College, the Business Interdepartmental Area Graduate Committee (CBA 125) and the MPA director for admission and enrollment requirements. Application is required through the Graduate Admissions Management and Evaluation System (GAMES) which will include online submission of:

Graduate College Application
Graduate Management Admissions Test (GMAT)
Three letters of recommendation
Two copies of official transcripts of all college course work completed
And completion of ACCT 308, ACCT 309, ACCT 313, ACCT 314 and BLAW 372

During the senior year for the MPA program, students will take the following 9 hours of course work:

*ACCT 410/810 Auditing

*ACCT 412/812 Federal Tax Accounting

*ACCT Elective (selected from):

ACCT 404/804 Advanced Accounting

ACCT 408/804 Advanced Managerial Accounting

Students planning to do the MPA program should plan a maximum of two senior-level accounting courses to be held for Graduate Credit. They need to take these courses at the graduate level. To do this, they must complete the form at http://research.unl.edu/gradstudies/credit/.

During the master’s year of the MPA program, students are required to complete 30 hours of the following:

ACCT 803 Seminar in Financial Accounting

ACCT 831 Seminar in Auditing

ACCT 857 Controllership or ACCT 858 Seminar in Managerial Accounting

Accounting 900 level (or 800 level with no 400-level counterparts) - 6 hours

Additional graduate-level course work to meet minimum 150 hours - 15 hours

Additional requirements such as submission of a memorandum of courses form, should be completed during the fifth year of the program. The memorandum must be completed prior to completion of half of the MPA program.

Students should contact the MPA adviser for additional information.
Students’ registration forms must be signed by the MPA adviser each semester.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Certified Public Accountant (CPA)

The CPA Exam is a national exam but licensing requirements are set by jurisdiction (the 50 states, District of Columbia, and U.S. territories) of residence. Nebraska requires 150 hours of education, successful completion of the CPA Exam and two years of qualifying work experience for licensure. Nebraska specifically requires 30 hours of accounting courses (beyond principles of accounting) be included in the 150 hour requirement. Candidates with a masters of professional accountancy (MPA) degree from UNL automatically meet the educational requirements. Otherwise, transcripts will be examined for compliance with educational requirements.

The Nebraska Board of Public Accountancy has a 60/90 provision for meeting the educational requirements to sit for the CPA Exam. Candidates who will complete their educational requirements (150 hours) within 60 days after taking the CPA Exam are eligible to take the exam, but they will not receive credit for the exam unless evidence satisfactory to the Board showing the completion of the educational requirements is received by the Board within 90 days following when the candidate took the exam.

Visit the Nebraska Board of Public Accountancy website for additional information (www.nbpa.ne.gov/).

(30 Semester Hours of Accounting Beyond Principles)

University of Nebraska–Lincoln courses that will satisfy the accounting requirements. Thirty semester hours beyond Accounting Principles are required. A minimum of 3 hours must be taken in each of the areas below (except Other Accounting Courses).

Hours

Financial Accounting, Theory and Problems 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 404/804 Advanced Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 803 Seminar in Financial Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 805 Financial Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 888 Financial Statement Analysis (3 cr)

Cost and Managerial Accounting 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 408/808 Advanced Managerial Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 858 Seminar in Managerial Accounting (3 cr)

Tax Preparation and Planning 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ACCT 412/812 Federal Tax Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 813 Corporate Tax Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 815 Tax Research & Planning (3 cr)

ACCT 816 Special Topics in Federal Taxation (3 cr)

ACCT 817 The Income Tax & Management Decisions (3 cr)

ACCT 819 Partnership Tax Accounting (3 cr)

Auditing 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ACCT 410/810 Auditing (3 cr)

ACCT 831 Seminar in Auditing (3 cr)

Information Systems 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems (3 cr)

Governmental and Not-for-Profit 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ACCT 404/804 Advanced Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 814 Governmental & Not-for-Profit Accounting (3 cr)

Other Accounting Courses

Select from:

ACCT 399 Independent Study (3 cr)

ACCT 399H Honors Independent Study (1-3 cr)

ACCT 499H Honors Thesis (3 cr)

ACCT 802 Accounting Standards (3 cr)

ACCT 807 Professional Responsibility & Ethics in Accounting (3 cr)

ACCT 840 Fraud Examination (3 cr)

ACCT 857 Controllership (3 cr)

ACCT 920 History & Philosophy of Accounting Thought (3 cr)

ACCT 990 Accountancy Internship (1-3 cr)

NOTE: Most graduate-only courses—800 level with no 400 counterpart and 900-level courses—cannot be taken by undergraduate students. Some graduate courses are open to MPA students only. Consult with your faculty adviser or the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

(36 Semester Hours in General Business)

University of Nebraska–Lincoln courses that will satisfy the General Business Requirements. At least 6 hours of Principles of Accounting are required and at least 3 hours from each of the other areas are required (except for Other Business Courses).

Hours

Macroeconomics 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ECON 211 Principles of Macroeconomics (3 cr)

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics (3 cr)

Microeconomics 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ECON 210 Intro to Economics (5 cr)

ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics (3 cr)

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics (3 cr)

Business Law 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

BLAW 371 Legal Environment (3 cr)

BLAW 372 Business Law I (3 cr)

Marketing 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

MRKT 341 Marketing (3 cr)

MRKT 341H Honors: Marketing (3 cr)

Management 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

MNGT 350 Intro to Management Information Systems (3 cr)

MNGT 360 Managing Behavior in Organizations or MNGT 360H Honors: Managing Behavior in Organizations (3 cr)

Finance 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

FINA 361 Finance (3 cr)

FINA 361H Honors: Finance (3 cr)

Business Communications 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

JGEN 220 Business Communication Strategies (3 cr)

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication (3 cr)

Business Ethics 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

ACCT 807 Professional Responsibility & Ethics in Accounting (3 cr)

BLAW 371 Legal Environment (3 cr)

BLAW 372 Business Law I (3 cr)

Quantitative Applications in Business 3

Select a minimum of 3 hrs from:

MNGT 245 Elementary Quantitative Methods (3 cr)

MNGT 331 Operations & Supply Chain Management (3 cr)

Principles of Accounting 6

Select a minimum of 6 hrs from:

ACCT 201 Introductory Accounting I or ACCT 201H Honors: Introductory Accounting I (3 cr)

ACCT 202 Introductory Accounting II or ACCT 202H Honors: Introductory Accounting II (3 cr)

ACCT 306 Survey of Accounting (3 cr)

Other Business Courses

MNGT 475 Business Policies & Strategies (3 cr)

Electives

As noted with the MPA and/or CPA, students may choose to take elective course work required for the degree in course options suggested.

See College Degree Requirements–Electives for additional options/restrictions regarding elective credit for the degree.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in many of the accounting courses requires certain grades in prerequisite courses as well as enrollment in a sequenced order. Refer to course descriptions for prerequisite requirements.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Grades of C or better are required in accounting courses which serve as prerequisites for upper-level accounting courses unless special permission is given by the director of the School of Accountancy.

Pass/No Pass Limits

No accounting courses can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis with the exception of ACCT 399.

Course Level Requirement

Upper-level accounting course work (300/400-level) must be taken at UNL (i.e. may not transfer in 300/400-level accounting courses from another institution without prior permission).

All 800- and 900-level courses are open to graduate students; some 800-level courses may be taken by undergraduate students with permission.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

The accounting minor is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college expects that 75% of the course work will be completed at UNL.

Accounting course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation, intermediate or advanced-major degree requirements, for another major (except as noted for finance majors, nor any other business minor requirements.

To fulfill the requirements for an accounting minor, students must complete 12 graded hours of accounting course work beyond accounting principles to include the following (to be taken for a grade [no Pass/No Pass]):

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting II or ACCT 412 Federal Tax Accounting

Finance majors may want to consider an accounting minor as course work for the finance major in the general finance option and CFA® – investments option allows for a double counting of ACCT 308, ACCT 313, and ACCT 314. Double counting availability depends on the option selected.

Actuarial Science (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Actuarial Science

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Art or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Warren Luckner

DESCRIPTION

Director and Professor of Practice: Warren Luckner, 210 CBA

Professor: Ramsay

Associate Professor: Mashayekhi

Assistant Professor of Practice: Vagts

http://cba.unl.edu/academics/actuarial/

An actuary is a mathematically-oriented business person who will most likely be a manager or supervisor at some point in his/her career. Thus, a course of study culminating in a bachelor of science degree in business administration with a major in actuarial science is an excellent educational background for prospective actuaries. Additional information is available at www.BeAnActuary.org.

The actuarial science program is designed to prepare students for the current industry demands. Because the demands change on a regular basis, often times, the number of hours, the sequencing of courses, and the specific requirements change for this major. Students should continue to consult with the department for the appropriate selection and listing of course requirements.

All actuarial science students are encouraged to visit the actuarial science program’s website (http://cba.unl.edu/academics/actuarial/) and an actuarial science program faculty adviser for more information about the program, including the Actuarial Science Club, sequencing of courses, scholarship opportunities, and the requirements for achieving professional actuarial designations.

See the College of Business Administration section of this bulletin for a description of the major in that college.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The major must include a complete calculus sequence (MATH 106/MATH 107/MATH 208, or MATH 108H/MATH 109H, or the equivalent); and the following statistics and probability sequence: STAT 380, STAT 462, STAT 463 and 22 semester hours of actuarial science. (See actuarial science adviser for specified courses in actuarial science.)

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Students must complete STAT 462 before taking any 400-level actuarial science course except ACTS 440; STAT 463 may be taken concurrently with ACTS 470.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits (related to the major)

No course may be taken Pass/No Pass.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A. Requires 15 hrs of actuarial science plus prerequisite mathematics and statistics courses.

Plan B. Requires 12 hrs of actuarial science plus prerequisite mathematics and statistics courses.

Actuarial Science (CBA)

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Actuarial Science (CBA)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (28 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Warren Luckner, Sue Vagts

DESCRIPTION

Professor: Ramsay

Professor of Practice: Warren Luckner

Assistant Professor: Shi

Associate Professor: Mashayekhi

Associate Professor of Practice: Vagts

An actuary is a mathematically-oriented business person who will most likely be a manager or supervisor at some point in his/her career. Thus, a course of study culminating in a bachelor of science degree in business administration with a major in actuarial science is an excellent educational background for prospective actuaries. Additional information is available at www.BeAnActuary.org.

The actuarial science program is designed to prepare students for the current industry demands. Because the demands change on a regular basis, often times, the number of hours, the sequencing of courses, and the specific requirements change for this major. Students should continue to consult with the department for the appropriate selection and listing of course requirements.

The actuarial science program is proud to have been named one of the first Centers of Actuarial Excellence by the Society of Actuaries.

All actuarial science students are encouraged to visit the actuarial science program’s website (http://cba.unl.edu/academics/actuarial/) and an actuarial science program faculty adviser for more information about the program, including the Actuarial Science Club, sequencing of courses, scholarship opportunities, and the requirements for achieving professional actuarial designations.

In addition, because of the mathematical orientation for this program, actuarial science majors are required to make some modifications to the degree program requirements. These requirements (with a reminder that all required course work must be taken for a grade) are noted below.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 28 hours of course work for the major.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade. Actuarial science majors must take MATH 106, MATH 107, and MATH 208, as well as CSCE 101 & CSCE 101L.
These hours have been built into the College Degree Requirements as part of the Non-Business Requirements (NBR).
ACTS 399/499 may not count toward the major or minor in actuarial science.
Other College Degree Requirement changes for actuarial science majors includes:
ACTS majors must take STAT 380 in place of ECON 215 for the Business Core Foundation (BCF) requirements.
ACTS majors will also take STAT 462 & STAT 463 Introduction to Mathematical Statistics I & II for the Business Core Foundation (BCF) requirements.
ACTS majors will take FINA 461 Advanced Finance in place of FINA 361 for the Business Core Intermediate (BCI) requirements; the prerequisite of FINA 361 (for FINA 363 and FINA 461) is satisfied with completion of ACTS 440.
12 hours of 300/400-level elective course work is NOT required for actuarial science majors.
As part of the college elective requirements, all students complete ONE business elective course for the program. ACTS majors are WAIVED from this specific requirement; however, all ACTS majors must take an IBCR course and thus, this can be done to meet the business elective requirement. The department suggests FINA 450 International Financial Management be taken to meet the requirement. An alternative option is to take ECON 321 or MNGT 428 as part of NBR 6–ACE 9 which then double counts for both the NBR 6 and IBCR requirement.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in actuarial science will complete 28 hours of actuarial science course work for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M):

ACTS 430 Actuarial Applications of Applied Statistics

ACTS 440 Financial Mathematics

ACTS 470 Life Contingencies I

ACTS 471 Life Contingencies II

ACTS 473 Intro to Risk Theory

ACTS 475 Actuarial Applications in Practice

FINA 307 Principles of Individual Risk Management & Insurance or FINA 338 Principles of Corporate Risk Management

FINA 363 Investment Principles

Choose one of the following:

ACTS 410 Intro to Credibility, Smoothing of Data & Simulation

ACTS 425 Survival Models

ACTS 450 Stochastic Processes for Actuaries

FINA 467 Options, Futures & Derivative Securities

In addition to the 28 hours for the major, ACTS majors are also encouraged to take:

Actuarial science problem labs as appropriate
MATH 314 Applied Linear Algebra, MATH 221 Differential Equations
At least one of FINA 412, FINA 420, FINA 438, or ECON 413

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, actuarial science majors may double major in finance. The finance department allows double counting of courses for students choosing to obtain a double major in actuarial science and finance.

Actuarial Science and Finance Double Majors

1. Take the Core Finance Requirements.

2. Choose ONE of the four options available. Students may select only ONE option to complete.

a. If choosing the General Finance Option, double majors must take FINA 375 Financial Statement Analysis, and cannot take FINA 307 as a finance elective

i. Also, consider choosing FINA 450 as one of the 400-level options to meet the requirement for the major as well as a requirement for the IBCR.

b. For all other options within the finance major, the required and elective finance courses are the same as those of a student obtaining just the finance major.

Finance Minor

Actuarial students may double count their finance courses towards a finance minor. They will follow the regular minor found in the finance section of the Bulletin. The courses used might include:

FINA 307 or FINA 338

FINA 363

FINA 365/ECON 365

FINA 450 or FINA 467 or FINA 412 or FINA 420 or FINA 438

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Actuarial Science Minor

To fulfill the requirements for an actuarial science minor, students must complete:

Twelve (12) graded hours of actuarial science course work; ACTS 440, ACTS 470, ACTS 471, and ACTS 473 are recommended.
(no Pass/No Pass)
ACTS 399 may not be used toward the minor (or major).
The college requires that 75% of the minor be earned on campus.

OTHER

Actuarial Science Major

All course work for the major must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).

Substitutions When Changing Majors

If ACTS students change to a different major in the College of Business Administration, the following substitutions may be made.

ACTS 440 for FINA 361

STAT 380 for ECON 215

Advertising & Public Relations

COLLEGE: Journalism & Mass Communications

MAJOR: Advertising & Public Relations

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Journalism

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Michael Goff

DESCRIPTION

Professors: N. Mitchell, Shipley

Associate Professors: Brown, Hachtmann, Struthers,

Assistant Professors: Kiambi, Lauerman, Peon-Casanova, Wang

Senior Lecturers: Goff, James, Larsen

Lecturers: R. B. Mitchell, Tidball

The advertising and public relations major prepares students for careers in a wide variety of communication-related areas. Recent graduates have been placed in more than 20 states and several other countries in diverse advertising careers such as retail and corporate advertising and marketing, media sales, brand management, media planning, account management, research, public relations, media relations, special event planning, Internet communications, copywriting and layout and design.

The advertising faculty believes that a successful career must be built upon a solid foundation, an education that combines theory and practice. To achieve that end, the major offers courses in copywriting, layout, media planning, graphics, campaign development, research, management, and strategic communications. The curriculum is designed to emphasize strategy, planning and implementation in creative problem solving.

Much emphasis is placed on individual relationships between faculty and students, an interaction vital to a student’s creative development. An adviser also helps each student tailor an academic plan to meet his or her interests and needs.

In advertising and strategic communications classes, students often work with actual clients who present real-life problems. This experience gives students a professional perspective on problem solving in many sectors including nonprofit, retail, small business and community organizations as well as large corporations. Students are encouraged to augment their academic experience with internships.

The faculty, with many professional contacts both locally and nationwide, actively help place students in jobs within the state and throughout the country. Students interested in majoring in advertising and public relations should contact the college office in 147 Andersen Hall, 402-472-3041.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The major is 39 hours in advertising and public relations.

The courses required for a major in advertising and public relations are as follows:

ADPR 251, ADPR 283, JOMC 101, and one of the following two sets:

Either both JOMC 162 and JOMC 163, or only JOMC 160

Either both JOMC 164 and JOMC 165, on only JOMC 161

Additionally, all ADPR majors take one of the following three: ADPR 429, ADPR 439, or ADPR 489. And they take 18 hours from approved electives for the major.

The 18 elective hours below comprise four optional tracks. Students may complete a track leading to account services or to creative/interactive or to public relations or to sports communication. Students also may select the elective courses from multiple tracks to provide a broad background. Among the 18 elective hours, students may select courses from JOUR, JOMC or BRDC; however, at least 9 of the 18 elective hours must be chosen from ADPR elective options numbered 300 or higher.

The account services track includes the following: ADPR 329, ADPR 339, ADPR 360, ADPR 434, ADPR 481, and ADPR 484.

The creative/interactive track options include the following: ADPR 323, ADPR 329, ADPR 333, ADPR 339, ADPR 433, ADPR 447, ADPR 458, ADPR 459, ADPR 483, and ADPR 484.

The public relations track options include the following: ADPR 207, ADPR 329, ADPR 339, ADPR 417, ADPR 450, ADPR 451; JOUR 201 and JOUR 202.

The sports communication track options include the following: JOMC 101; JOUR 202; ADPR 450 and ADPR 451.

If approved by the Advertising and Public Relations sequence head, all tracks may further include the following: ADPR 491 or JOUR 491; ADPR 495 and ADPR 499H.

Students may complete two majors in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications by completing all requirements for each major; however, the second major in the college will not take the place of a concentration or any of the 72 hours required outside the college.

Agricultural Education

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Agricultural Education

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Agricultural Education

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation, 2.5 for graduation with teaching option

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–Environmental Communication, Leadership & Communication

CHIEF ADVISERS: Lloyd Bell (teaching), Gina Matkin (agricultural leadership)

DESCRIPTION

Head: Mark Balschweid, Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication; 300 Agriculture Hall

Professors: Bell, Husmann

Assistant Professors: Matkin, Kang

Assistant Professor of Practice: Kreifels

A degree in agricultural education is designed to prepare students with the necessary communication and interpersonal skills, leadership training, and knowledge of technical agriculture to be a teacher of agricultural education at the secondary or postsecondary level, or accept employment in agribusiness leading to positions in training and/or development. The degree provides good preparation for work in agricultural extension, positions in foreign service, and agricultural educators in business and industry. Many students graduate with a dual degree in agricultural education and another degree in the College. Agricultural education students may elect to follow the teaching options or the leadership option.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Students desiring to be admitted to the Teacher Education program in the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication should apply as early as possible after the completion of at least 42 credit hours (at least one year before they plan to student teach). Student teaching is conducted off campus through university-approved agreements with cooperating secondary schools. Plans for student teaching must be made early.

To be admitted into the student teaching program candidates must have: 1) a minimum scholastic grade point average of 2.50 including no grades lower than “C”: within the endorsement area, and no grades lower than “C+” within professional education courses, 2) passing scores within the Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST), 3) 1,000 hours of verified work experience within the agriculture, food, natural resources (AFNR) career cluster, or 300 hours of supervised employment in the AFNR career cluster under the direction of a UNL academic unit, 4) three written letters of recommendation; one of which must be a character reference. Student Teaching (ALEC 431) is available as Pass/No Pass only. Meet with your adviser to plan for your student teaching experience.

Other Admission Requirements

Teaching Certificate

Successful completion of the teaching endorsement requirements, along with a recommendation by the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication, warrants recommendation for a Nebraska Secondary Teaching Certificate by the Nebraska Department of Education, with an endorsement to teach secondary agricultural education (7-12). The choice is available to students to complete course work qualifying for subject endorsement in biology.

Students in other agricultural degree programs may qualify based upon meeting the teaching certificate requirements.

Criminal History/Background Check

Effective August 2012, individuals enrolled in any UNL teacher education course requiring a practicum experience in schools or other institutions must have successfully completed a background review prior to any practicum visitations. Two successful reviews will be required during your teacher preparation program; one prior to your initial practicum experience, and a second prior to your student teaching field experience. Background reviews must be completed through One Source, The Background Check Company. See your adviser or practicum course instructor for necessary details to request and complete a background review.

Nebraska State Department of Education Policy Pertaining to Students with Felony or Misdemeanor Convictions

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with felony convictions or misdemeanor convictions involving abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval by the Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the Department of Agricultural Education will require each student to affirm under oath that he/she does not have any convictions in the above-named areas prior to each field placement. If a student does have any felony or misdemeanor convictions, he/she is required to meet with Dr. Tom Wandzilak, Certification Officer, Student Services Center, 104 Henzlik Hall, 402-472-8626, as soon as possible. Students with questions pertaining to convictions should contact Dr. Wandzilak.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Teaching Option

Hours

College Integrative Courses 15

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

ALEC 431 Student Teaching (ACE 10) (Capstone Course) (P/NP only) 12

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) 5-6

Select from:

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I (5 cr)

MATH 102 Trigonometry (2 cr) or MATH 104 Calculus for Mathematics & Social Sciences (3 cr) or MATH 203 Contemporary Mathematics (3 cr) and STAT 218 Intro to Statistics (ACE 3) or EDPS 459 Statistical Methods (3 cr)

Communications 9

Written Communication (ACE 1) 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 200, JGEN 300

Oral Communication 3

Select from: COMM 209 or COMM 286

Communication/Interpersonal Skills: ALEC 102 (ACE 2) 3

Natural Sciences (ACE 4) 12

HORT 131 & HORT 133 4

CHEM 105* Chemistry in Context I 4

PHYS 141 or MSYM 109 4

*Students pursuing combined agriculture-biology endorsement must complete CHEM 109.

Economics 3

AECN 141 Intro to the Economics of Agriculture (ACE 6) 3

Humanities and Social Sciences 15

EDPS 457 Learning & Motivation Principles for Secondary Teaching 3

SOCI 217 Nationality & Race Relations or TEAC 330 Multicultural
Education (ACE 9) 3

Humanities and Social Sciences electives 9

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, and 8.

Agricultural and Natural Resource Sciences 36

A minimum of 15 hours completed at the 200 level or above, and a minimum of 9 hours completed at the 300 level or above. Students must have a course in four CASNR departments or program areas. A course may be used to fulfill more than one category; however, the hours will only count once toward the 36-hour agricultural science requirement.

Research and Applied Technology 3

Select from: AGRI 115; AGRO 315, AGRO 431; FDST 131

Policy 3

Select from: AECN 265, AECN 276, AECN 346, AECN 376; NRES 323; POLS 235, POLS 236

Management 9

Select from: AECN 201, AECN 325; ASCI 250, ASCI 320, ASCI 330, ASCI 450, ASCI 451, ASCI 452, ASCI 453, ASCI 454, ASCI 455, ASCI 457; AGRO 204, AGRO 240, AGRO 405; HORT 325

Production 3

Select from: ASCI 100 or ASCI 150 or HORT 133, HORT 159, HORT 221, HORT 325, HORT 327, HORT 350

Natural Resources 6

Select from: AECN 265; AGRO 153, AGRO 366; BIOS 232; ENTO 109; NRES 211, NRES 220, NRES 311

Mechanized Systems 9

Select from: MSYM 232, MSYM 245, MSYM 312; ALEC 104, ALEC 203, ALEC 205, ALEC 242

Food System 3

Select from: AECN 225; ASCI 210; or FDST 101, FDST 131

Leadership and Education 20

ALEC 134 Agricultural Education, Journalism, & Leadership Careers 2

ALEC 135 Early Field Experience in Agricultural Education, Leadership & Communication 1

ALEC 234 Planning Leadership & Experience Programs 3

ALEC 308 Lab Instruction & Management 3

ALEC 405 Methods of Instruction for Secondary Agriscience Education 3

ALEC 405L Methods of Instruction Laboratory Education 1

ALEC 413 Program Development 3

ALEC 494 Undergraduate Seminar in Agricultural Education 1

SPED 401B Accommodating Exceptional Learners in the Secondary School Classroom or SPED 434 Intro to Special Vocational Needs 3

Free Electives 4-5

Minimum Credit Hours Required for Graduation 120

Biology Endorsement Requirements

If the student desires to qualify for both an endorsement in agricultural education and a subject endorsement in biology, the following course work should be integrated into the teaching option.

Supporting Laboratory Based Courses (12 hours)

Hours

Chemistry: CHEM 109 4

Physics: PHYS 141, PHYS 151, or MSYM 109 4

Earth Science: AGRO 153 Soil Resources 4

Biology Courses (24 hours)

Select at least one of the suggested courses from each of the following categories. A course may be used more than once toward fulfilling the content requirement, however a minimum of 24 different hours is required. At least 12 hours must be taken at the 200 level or higher. Other course work may be negotiated with your academic adviser.

Hours

Botany

BIOS 109 General Botany 4

AGRO 131 & AGRO 132 Plant Science & Agronomic Lab 4

AGRO 204 Resource-Efficient Crop Management 3

AGRO 240 Forage Crop & Range Management 4

HORT 131 & HORT 133 Plant Science & Intro to Horticultural Sciences Lab 4

Cell Biology/Biochemistry

BIOS 102 Cell Structure & Function or BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab 4

Ecology

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resources Systems 3

NRES 211 Intro to Conservation Biology 3

NRES 311 Wildlife Ecology & Management 3

Evolution

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

Genetics

AGRO 315 Genetics 4

Human Biology

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab 4

Microbiology

FDST 372 Food Safety & Sanitation 3

Zoology

ASCI 240 Anatomy & Physiology of Domestic Animals 4

*To be eligible for the biology endorsement, a student must maintain a minimum grade point average of 2.5 in the above course work or its equivalency.

Integrated Laboratory Management

ALEC 308 Laboratory Instruction & Management 3

Science Methods Instruction

TEAC 451V Secondary Science 3

TEAC 397 Professional Practicum Experience III parallel with TEAC 451V 1

Student Teaching

Students seeking a dual endorsement will be required to complete their student teaching experience in a school where they will spend teaching time in both biology and agriculture.

Horticulture Education Endorsement Requirements

If the student desires to add a subject endorsement in horticulture education to their teaching certification, the following course work should be completed.

Hours

Horticulture Education (Grades 7-12) 33

ALEC 400 Overview to Program Planning or ALEC 413 Program Development 3

HORT 131 Plant Science 3

HORT 133 Intro to Horticultural Sciences Lab 1

HORT 153 Soil Resources 4

HORT 212 Landscape Plants I or HORT 213 Landscape Plants II 3

HORT 221 Plant Propagation 3

HORT 227 Introductory Turfgrass Management 3

HORT 228 Intro to Landscape Management 3

HORT 261 Floral Design I 3

HORT 325 Greenhouse Practices & Management 4

HORT 395 Career Experience 3

Skilled and Technical Sciences 2+2 Teaching Option

The following is a 2+2 program for students interested in obtaining certification in Skilled and Technical Sciences (STS). This certification will allow an individual to teach Skilled and Technical Sciences in a Nebraska secondary school (grades 7-12). Completion of the 60 credit hour requirement in the Skilled and Technical Sciences 2 + 2 Teaching Option at UNL, along with the completion of an associate of applied science within a post-secondary institution with a 2 + 2 agreement, will allow a student to complete a BS degree in agricultural education from UNL.

The program is an agreement between the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources (CASNR) and community college systems in Nebraska. The 2+2 program requires a student to complete the first two years at a community college and earn an associate of applied science degree before transferring to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln (UNL).

The transfer policy in CASNR will be in effect for all students interested in the STS 2+2 program. This 2+2 program is for the STS teaching program and will be the only program available for students to become certified at UNL. Students transferring into other UNL programs other than the STS program must follow the requirements set forth through the departments within the specific colleges.

The prerequisite for entry into the STS certification program at UNL is the completion of the Skilled and Technical Sciences Program at a community college with a 2 + 2 Skilled and Technical Sciences Agreement. Students who transfer into UNL from other programs within the community college system will not be eligible for entry into the 2+2 program in STS at UNL.

To be admitted into the student teaching program candidates must have: 1) a minimum scholastic grade point average of 2.50 including no grades lower than “C” within the endorsement area, and no grades lower than “C+” within professional education courses; 2) passing scores within the Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST); 3) 1,000 hours of verified work experience within the Skilled and Technical Sciences (STS) career cluster, or 300 hours of supervised employment in the STS career cluster under the direction of a UNL academic unit; and 4) three written letters of recommendation; one of which must be a character reference. Student Teaching (ALEC 431) is available as Pass/No Pass only. Meet with your adviser to plan for your student teaching experience.

Teaching Certificate. Successful completion of the teaching endorsement requirements, along with a recommendation by the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication, warrants recommendation for a Nebraska Secondary Teaching Certificate by the Department of Education, with an endorsement to teach skilled and technical sciences (7-12).

STS Teaching Option

Students who meet entry requirements in the STS Teaching Option will have completed a variety of course work from their community college. Many of the courses within the community college system have direct equivalencies with our ACE program at UNL. Following a comprehensive transfer analysis, students will be provided an accurate degree audit of the remaining ACE courses needed at UNL along with the professional program in Agricultural Education. The minimum requirements of CASNR reflect the common core of courses that apply to students pursuing degrees in the college. Students should work with an adviser to satisfy ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 10 requirements. ACE requirements 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, and 9 will be completed through their academic programs within the community college system since it is a requirement for an associate of applied science degree at their institutions.

Hours

ACE Requirements 9

Students should work with an adviser to select one course each in ACE outcomes 5, 7, and 8.

Leadership and Education 42

ALEC 135 Early Field Experience in Agricultural Education, Leadership & Communication 1

ALEC 308 Lab Instruction & Management 3

ALEC 405 Methods of Instruction for Secondary Agriscience Education 3

ALEC 405L Methods of Instruction Lab Education 1

ALEC 413 Program Development 3

ALEC 424 Foundations of Career & Technical Education 3

ALEC 431 Student Teaching (ACE 10) 12

ALEC 494 Undergraduate Seminar in Agricultural Education 1

ALEC 496 Independent Study in Leadership Education (SkillsUSA/PDP) 3

EDPS 209 Strategies for Academic Success 3

EDPS 457 Learning and Motivation Principles for Secondary Teaching 3

SPED 401B Accommodating Exceptional Learners in the Secondary Classroom or SPED 434 Intro to Special Vocational Needs 3

TEAC 259 Instructional Technology 3

Free Electives 9

Program Credit Requirements 51

STS Credit Requirements for BS Degree in Agricultural Education 60

Maximum Credits for Transfer into UNL 60

Minimum Credit Hours Required for Graduation 120

Agricultural Leadership Option

The Agricultural Leadership Option is recommended for those interested in pursuing a career in the agricultural industry in the areas of leadership development, commodity board advocacy, executive development, youth and leadership development, extension, consulting/training, organizational development, human resources, public policy, rural and community development.

Hours

College Integrative Courses 8

AGRI 103/NRES 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

ALEC 495A Internship in Leadership Development (ACE 10) (Capstone Course) 5

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) 5-6

Select from:

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I (5 cr)

MATH 102 Trigonometry (2 cr) or MATH 104 Calculus for Mathematics & Social Sciences (3 cr) or MATH 203 Contemporary Mathematics (3 cr) and STAT 218 Intro to Statistics (ACE 3) or EDPS 459 Statistical Methods (3 cr)

Communications 9

Written Communication 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 200, JGEN 300 (ACE 1)

Oral Communication 3

Select from: COMM 209 or COMM 286

Communication/Interpersonal Skills: ALEC 102 (ACE 2) 3

Natural Sciences 8-9

Select 2 of 3 Natural Sciences courses (ACE 4)

CASNR Approved Life Sciences (4 cr)

CHEM 105 Chemistry in Context I (ACE 4) (4 cr) or CHEM 109 General Chemistry (4 cr)

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151 or MSYM 109 (4-5 cr)

Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences 15

ECON 211 or ECON 212 or AECN 141 (ACE 6) 3

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

Minor 12-20

NOTE: An approved minor in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources other than leadership and communication minor is required.

Major Requirements 33

ALEC 134 Agricultural Education, Journalism, & Leadership Careers 2

ALEC 202 Leadership Development in Small Groups & Teams 3

ALEC 302 Dynamics of Effective Leadership in Organizations 3

ALEC 305 Presentation Strategies for Agricultural Audiences 3

ALEC 388 Ethics in Agriculture & Natural Resources 3

ALEC 407 Supervisory Leadership 3

ALEC 410 Environmental Leadership 3

ALEC 414 Classic Figures in Leadership 3

ALEC 466 Leadership & Diversity in Organizations & Communities 3

ALEC 477 Leadership & Motivation 3

ALEC 488 Leadership, Power & Influence 3

ALEC 494 Undergraduate Seminar in Agricultural Education 1

Free Electives 20-30

Must include one 3-credit 200-level or higher course from a department other than ALEC or the minor department.

Minimum Credit Hours Required for Graduation 120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Students in the teaching option of Agricultural Education need to be aware that CASNR has a 24-credit hour limitation established by the Faculty Senate. Please plan accordingly and review your status with your academic adviser every academic term.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Environmental Communications Minor

A minor program in environmental communications is available through the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication in cooperation with the School of Natural Resources. The minor is designed to provide students with interests in environmental studies and natural resources, additional expertise that can be used in a variety of career paths and settings. It is also designed to provide the student with a general understanding and working knowledge of the interactions that do–and can–exist between the agricultural sciences, natural resources, and the environment. The ability to communicate effectively with the public about these relevant issues, in articulate, analytical and substantive ways, is becoming an increasingly valued and necessary skill, self-evident to many groups including policy makers, legislators, regulators, advocates, business, and the general public. The 12-hour minor is comprised of the following courses:

Hours

ALEC 305 Presentation Strategies for Agricultural Audiences 3

Select one from: 3

ALEC 388 Ethics in Agriculture & Natural Resources (3 cr)

AECN 357 Natural Resource & Environmental Law (3 cr)

NRES 323 Natural Resources Policy (3 cr)

ALEC 410/810 (NRES 413/813) Environmental Leadership 3

NRES 423/823 Integrated Resources Management 3

Students who wish to minor in environmental communications must first be assigned an adviser with copies of the approved program sent to the University Registrar and the dean of the student’s college.

Leadership and Communication Minor

An 18-hour minor in leadership and communication is available through the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication. Combining a leadership and communication minor with any CASNR degree strengthens students’ “employability” base by making them competent technical professionals who are also strong leaders and effective communicators. The 18-hour minor is comprised of upper and lower division courses as follows:

Hours

Complete at least three courses from the following list 9

ALEC 102 Interpersonal Skills for Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 202 Leadership Development in Small Groups & Teams (3 cr)

ALEC 302 Dynamics of Effective Leadership in Organizations (3 cr)

ALEC 305 Presentation Strategies for Agricultural Audiences (3 cr)

The remaining courses are selected from the following list 9

ALEC 337 *Instructional Internship in Leadership Development (3 cr)

ALEC 388 Ethics in Agriculture & Natural Resources (3 cr)

ALEC 407 Supervisory Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 410 Environmental Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 414 Classical Figures in Leadership (3 cr)

ALEC 466 Leadership & Diversity in Organizations & Communities (3 cr)

ALEC 477 Leadership & Motivation (3 cr)

ALEC 480 **Dynamics of Agricultural Environmental Journalism (3 cr)

ALEC 488 Leadership, Power & Influence (3 cr)

AERO 331 ***Air Force Leadership Studies I (3 cr)

AERO 332 ***Air Force Leadership Studies II (3 cr)

NOTE: Animal Science Leadership Academy students see Dr. Linda Moody for course requirements.

* For students having completed ALEC 102 and who have been selected as Teaching Assistants.

** Open only to students enrolled in the Agricultural Journalism major.

*** May be substituted for Air Force ROTC students only.

Students who wish to minor in leadership and communication must first meet with a Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication faculty member from the leadership program. A completed Declaration of Minor form, filled out with the assistance of the ALEC faculty, should be signed by the student’s academic adviser and turned into the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources Dean’s office.

Architecture

COLLEGE: Architecture

MAJOR: Architecture

DEGREES OFFERED: The professional program in architecture consists of two components: the two-year Bachelor of Science in Design (BSD-Architecture) and the subsequent two-year Master of Architecture (MArch).

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 for BSD; 54 additional for the MArch

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISERS: Leslie Brehm & Stephanie Kuenning (pre-architecture); assigned faculty (architecture)

DESCRIPTION

Program Director: Jeffrey Day, 232 Architecture Hall

Professors: Day, Drummond, Handa, Hoistad, Kuska, Laging, Scholz

Associate Professors: Ford, Hardy, Hemsath, Hind, Krug

Assistant Professors: Karle, Kelly, Olshavsky

Professors Emeritus: Borner, Corkill, Duncan, Ertl, Gibbs, Moore, Potter, Puderbaugh, Sawyers, Steward

Chief Advisers: Pre-Architecture: Leslie Brehm (lbrehm2@unl.edu) and Stephanie Kuenning (skuenning2@unl.edu); Architecture: Assigned faculty

The primary responsibility of the architectural profession is the design of meaningful, productive environments for human occupation and use. Architects, therefore, must be able to understand the needs and desires of the people who will inhabit and use their creations and then effectively synthesize the complex structural, mechanical, constructional components, and cultural references that go into the design of a building. As designers, they must possess both creative and aesthetic skills as well as technical knowledge.

The architecture program seeks to increase students’ desire to learn and to develop a capacity for design-thinking and sound, critical judgment while simultaneously developing their creative potential. Specifically, the curriculum provides the background and means for the student to:

1. Analyze and understand society’s needs and desires,

2. Translate these needs and desires into a physical form and spatial organization,

3. Contribute creatively to the building construction industry,

4. Search out new problems and contribute to environmental knowledge through research,

5. Initiate and review changes in technology and society, and

6. Participate in the community that makes decisions affecting the physical environment.

Architecture is a six-year course of study divided into a pre-professional year and a professional program of study. Students choosing to study architecture first enter the College as majors in pre-architecture. After completing a one year introductory design curriculum common to all undergraduates in the College of Architecture, students apply for admission into the architecture program’s professional program. The professional program in architecture consists of two components: the three-year bachelor of science in design (BSD-Architecture) and the subsequent two-year master of architecture (MArch).

Students in good standing at the completion of the BSD-Architecture are admitted to the MArch program without application.

In the United States, most state registration boards require a degree from an accredited professional degree program as a prerequisite for licensure. The National Architectural Accreditation Board (NAAB), which is the sole agency authorized to accredit U.S. professional degree programs in architecture, recognizes three types of degrees: the bachelor of architecture, the master of architecture and the doctor of architecture. A program may be granted a 6-year, 3-year, or 2-year term of accreditation, depending on the extent of its conformance with established educational standards.

Masters degree programs may consist of an undergraduate degree and a professional graduate degree, that, when earned sequentially, constitute an accredited professional education. However, the undergraduate degree is not, by itself, recognized as an accredited degree.

The bachelor of science in design is a para-professional degree and a necessary component of the professional program which culminates with the master of architecture degree. The master of architecture degree is the first professional degree. The professional master of architecture degree is fully accredited by the National Architectural Accreditation Board (NAAB).

In addition to the normal two-year professional program, applicants with degrees from other fields may be eligible to enter the three year master of architecture program with deficiencies. These deficiencies are evaluated by the program director on an individual basis after admission resulting from a review of the applicant’s transcripts and other pertinent professionally-related materials by the Student Affairs Committee. Students in this three year program are required to complete 27 to 50 hours of selected undergraduate courses (a minimum of one additional year) prior to pursuing the professional program. Applicants with deficiencies exceeding 50 credit hours are not admitted.

For those who would like to pursue scholarship in architecture, the architecture program also offers a 36 credit hour, scholarly-nonprofessional master of science in architecture degree for students with a bachelors degree in architecture or a related discipline.

The Master of Architecture Professional Program

General

The professional program in architecture is a six-year course of study that includes a one-year pre-professional segment, a three-year core segment culminating in the award of the bachelor of science in design (BSD) and culminates in the final two-year exploratory segment which results in the receipt of the professional master of architecture degree (MArch).

Although the bachelor of science in design degree is an integral part of the five-year professional program in architecture, it should be clearly understood that the undergraduate BSD is not a professional degree and is not accredited by the National Architectural Accrediting Board. Most state registration boards will not acknowledge any degree unless accompanied by an accredited professional degree.

The accredited, first professional degree awarded by the College of Architecture is the master of architecture degree which is awarded at the successful conclusion of the professional program in architecture. This is the only accredited professional architecture program in the state of Nebraska.

Upon successful completion of the one-year pre-architecture program, students who have been admitted to the second year may enroll in the curriculum that leads to the BSD degree and the MArch degree.

The professional program in architecture is structured to develop highly competent professional architects.

Common First Year

The Common First Year engages and prepares students for exciting futures in all design fields within the College of Architecture.

The Common First Year curriculum offered by the College of Architecture, introduces students to design through courses in three areas: Technique (drawing and computer applications), Design Discipline (an introduction to the related design disciplines and design history), and Design Practice (design Thinking and design Making). In addition, students take University courses in math, English, communications, and a general education elective. dThink and dMake are sequential hands-on courses where students learn to work in teams to address problems and promote innovation. At the same time, they learn the foundational skills in composition, craft, presentation, and idea generation necessary for all design fields.

At the end of the Common First Year, students have gained an understanding of the broad range of design and are eligible to apply to any of the design programs in the College—Architecture, Landscape Architecture, Interior Design, and Industrial Design (pending program approval).

ADMISSION

Admission to the Architecture Program

After completion of the first year of pre-architecture studies, either within the College of Architecture or at another institution, students may apply for admission to the architecture program.

Pre-architecture students should apply for admission to the professional program in architecture. Successful applicants will have their major changed from pre-architecture to BSD-Architecture option.

Available teaching resources and space capacities limit enrollment to the second year of architectural studies; therefore enrollment limits are established each semester.

Required courses must be completed before advancing to the next year of study.

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the architecture program, applicants must:

Be enrolled in the College of Architecture
Be in good scholastic standing
Have completed the one year pre-architecture program of study.

Second Year Admission Process

1. An application for admission may be completed by filling out the online application. The program receives applications once a year on March 1.

2. Applicants must submit a portfolio conforming to the defined criteria for the program applied for by the date posted at the completion of the spring semester.

3. Any applicant who has previously applied for admission and has not been accepted or who fails to enroll in the professional program in architecture after an acceptance must reapply in the regular manner. Students may apply for admission to the architecture program only three times.

Evaluation

The Student Affairs Committee of the program will carefully evaluate the applications for admission. The committee considers three elements in their evaluation; cumulative grade point average, a weighted grade point average, and the portfolio of student work. The weighted grade point average gives additional value to the applicant’s achievement in the required DSGN prefix course or transfer equivalents in the pre-professional curriculum.

Selection

Admission to the architecture program will be awarded to applicants who show the greatest professional potential and have demonstrated scholastic achievement. The Student Affairs Committee reserves the right to not fill all available spaces in the professional program in architecture if it determines that the remaining applicants have not performed at an acceptable level.

Admission to the 2-Year Master of Architecture Program

Students having completed the BSD-Architecture may continue their studies culminating in the MArch without re-application provided they exhibit a cumulative grade point average of B (3.0) and a studio GPA of B (3.0). Students must submit an intent form with a brief statement of purpose. A portfolio is not required. Students wishing to be eligible for fellowship and assistantships must submit the form by February 1.

Students from outside the program must apply to gain admission to the 2-year MArch degree program. Applications are available in October from the department office and are reviewed once a year in February. The Graduate Record Examination (GRE) is not required.

All applications for admission are subject to approval of the Student Affairs Committee. Fifth and sixth year enrollment shall be limited by the teaching resources and space capacities of the department. An enrollment quota is established prior to each admissions cycle.

Students in the professional program are governed by the rules, procedures and policies established in the architecture program. These are published in the Student Guide or by official notification by the faculty.

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the 5th and 6th year of the professional program in architecture, applicants must:

Have a 4-year degree from an accreditation-leading architecture program
Present a portfolio of design work
Be in good scholastic standing
Have a B average or its equivalent in past academic programs

The Student Affairs Committee of the architecture program requires a minimum TOEFL score of 550 or 213 computer-based or Internet-based score of 79-80 for all international student applicants whose first language is not English.

Evaluation

A portfolio of an applicant’s recent design work will be evaluated by the Student Affairs Committee of the architecture program and is considered to be a very important part of the application review process, along with the applicant’s educational profile, letters of recommendation, transcripts, and application form.

Selection

The limited number of spaces available each semester will be awarded to applicants who have displayed the highest abilities in a combination of scholastic achievement, design capability, and professional potential.

The Admissions Committee reserves the right to reject applicants who, in its opinion, have not reached an acceptable level of design proficiency.

Admission to the 3-Year Master of Architecture Program

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the 3-year MArch program, applicants must:

Have a four-year bachelor degree in any field
Have a B (3.0) cumulative grade point average in past academic programs

The Student Affairs Committee requires a minimum TOEFL score of 550 or 213 computer-based or Internet-based score of 79-80 for all international student applicants whose first language is not English.

Evaluation

The Student Affairs Committee evaluates the candidate’s past academic record, three letters of recommendation, a statement of educational goals and the information requested on the application form. A portfolio is not required for candidates applying for the three year masters degree program, however, providing evidence of past achievements and/or creative activity is helpful to the committee in its evaluation.

Selection

The limited number of spaces available each semester will be awarded to applicants who have displayed the highest abilities in a combination of scholastic achievement and professional potential.

Deficiencies

The Student Affairs Committee and/or the Program Chair reserve the right to require additional course work be done to correct perceived deficiencies in the candidates educational background.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Pre-Architecture Curriculum

The pre-architecture curriculum begins with a basic design first year common to all undergraduate majors in the College of Architecture. This common first year introduces students to the fundamentals of design thinking and design making. The pre-architecture program is followed by three years of architectural instruction leading to a bachelor of science in design. After receipt of the bachelors degree, students may declare intentions to continue for an additional two years of study, leading to a professional master of architecture degree. The professional master of architecture degree is accredited by the National Architectural Accreditation Board (NAAB).

The College of Architecture, and all six years of the architecture program, are located in Lincoln. However, we do offer the option to do the first year of the program at UNO. After successfully completing the prescribed pre-architecture program at UNO, students may transfer to UNL and apply for admission to the second year of study in the Architecture Program.

For more information about courses at UNO, or transferring from UNO to UNL, please contact us.

PRE-ARCHITECTURE: Common First Year, First Semester

DSGN 101 Introduction to Design 2

DSGN 110 Design Thinking (ACE 7) 3

DSGN 120 Design Drawing 3

ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 Composition Elective (ACE 1) 3

ACE 6 Elective 3

Total 14

PRE-ARCHITECTURE: Common First Year, Second Semester

DSGN 111 Design Making 4

DSGN 123 Computer Applications in Design 3

DSGN 140 History of Design (ACE 5) 3

MATH 104 Calculus for Managerial & Social Sciences 3

Communication Elective: COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication or COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication (ACE 2) 3

Total 16

See your adviser for the BSD course requirements.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Minimum Grades

Students must earn at least a C (2.0) in all courses with an ARCH, DSGN, IDES, or LARC prefix to earn credit toward their degree. Students will be required to retake all core required courses with a grade of C- or below, but will not be required to repeat courses that were taken as electives.

Pass/No Pass Limits

None of the required classes offered in the professional program are offered Pass/No Pass, but a maximum of 12 Pass/No Pass credit hours of humanities, social sciences, or open electives may be taken from departments outside the College of Architecture.

Courses taken outside the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs to fulfill the upper level outside elective requirement at the 800 level or 900 level, with or without a 400-level counterpart, in a minor, collateral, or supporting area of work, can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis.

GPA Requirements

Pre-Professional Program, Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Interior Design

Students in the first year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average at or above 2.0. The College places students who fail to meet these standards on academic probation.

Second, Third and Fourth Year, Architecture

Students in the second year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average of 2.6. Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to meet two parallel academic standards. First the student must maintain a semester grade point average of 2.6 to remain in good academic standing. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation. Further, students whose GPA for the academic year is between 2.6 and 3.0 are required to submit their studio work for review by the Student Affairs Committee for determination of continuance in the program or repetition of the year’s studio sequence.

Fifth and Sixth Year, Architecture

Students in the MArch program are required to maintain a semester grade point average of 3.0 to remain in good academic standing. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

Art

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Art

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts, Bachelor of Fine Arts

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Christy Aggens

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Peter Pinnell, 120 Richards Hall

Professors: Forde, Fritz, Kunc, Pinnell

Associate Professors: Cal, Dominguez, Holz, Ingraham, Neal, Souto, Williams

Assistant Professors: Asher, Bohls, Sontheimer, Sutherlen

Assistant Professors of Practice: Cole, Syron

The program in the Department of Art and Art History enables students to attain proficiency in the practice of art and knowledge of the history of art in addition to a general college education. The department is keenly interested in both students who choose art as their profession and who want to devote themselves to a period of intensive education, and those who recognize the cultural advantages or who find in artistic endeavor a high degree of personal enjoyment and satisfaction.

The department offers facilities for instruction and exhibition in a variety of studios, shops, and laboratories. The Sheldon Museum of Art, adjacent to the department, is the setting for traveling exhibitions as well as the display of works of art selected from the Sheldon’s extensive permanent collection. The department also presents exhibitions in its own Eisentrager-Howard Gallery and the student-run MEDICI Gallery. These serve as extensions of the studio and classroom learning experience.

Two undergraduate degrees are available to art majors. The student’s career goals will determine the appropriate option. The bachelor of arts degree (BA) is a liberal arts degree with about forty percent of the course work in the Art and Art History Department, providing a wider exposure to various academic disciplines. The bachelor of fine arts degree (BFA) is a professional degree, the usual preparation for professional careers or graduate study in studio art, including about seventy percent of the course work from the Art and Art History Department.

Bachelor of Arts Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30

Languages: Classical & Modern 0-6

Select from the list of “Approved Courses” found under “College Degree Requirements.”

Library 110 1

Art Major Requirements 50

Minors 18-24

Electives 9-21

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

Bachelor of Fine Arts Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30

Library 110 1

Art Major Requirements 83

Electives 6

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Any student who meets college admission requirements may declare a major in art.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Bachelor of Arts Requirements

Hours

BA Requirements 50

Visual Literacy (ARTP 140A, ARTP 140B, ARTP 141A, ARTP 141B) 8

ARTP 400 Capstone Art Experience 3

Studio Electives (including a minimum of 3 credits above 299) 21

AHIS 101 & AHIS 102 Intro to Art History & Criticism I & II 6

Art History electives (including a minimum of 3 credits in courses numbered above 299) 12

Minor Requirements

BA students are required to complete one Plan A or two or more Plan B minors. Art history may only be used as a Plan B in conjunction with another minor outside of the department.

Bachelor of Fine Arts Requirements

Hours

BFA Requirements 83

Visual Literacy (ARTP 140A, ARTP 140B, ARTP 141A, ARTP 141B) 8

Required Distribution 18

DRAW 201 intermediate Drawing 3

CERM 231 Beginning Ceramics 3

PANT 251 Beginning Painting I 3

PHOT 261 Beginning Photography-Digital 3

PRNT 241 Beginning Printmaking I 3

SCLP 211 Beginning Sculpture I 3

Studio Electives (emphasis, if desired) 39

ARTP 400 Capstone Art Experience 3

AHIS 101 & AHIS 102 Intro to Art History & Criticism I & II 6

Art History electives (including a minimum of 3 credits in courses numbered above 299) 9

Emphasis Requirements

BFA students may opt to focus their studio electives in one area for an unofficial emphasis. Available areas of emphasis include ceramics, drawing, graphic design, painting, photography, printmaking, and sculpture. Course recommendations are available from the department.

Minor Requirements

BFA students are not allowed to declare a minor.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

BA Degree

Grade Rules

All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.
Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.

Course Level Requirement

A minimum of 3 credits of studio art and 3 credits of art history must be taken in courses numbered above 299.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit Rules

No more than 6 hours of independent study courses (ARTP 395, ARTP 495, ARTP 496, ARTP 499H; AHIS 390, AHIS 392, AHIS 395, AHIS 490, AHIS 492, AHIS 495, AHIS 499H) may count toward the major in the BA degree.
At least 12 credit hours in studio art and 9 credit hours in art history of the required BA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

Time and Credit Guidelines

The Department of Art and Art History adheres to the following time and credit guidelines established by the National Association of Schools of Art and Design (NASAD):

In studio courses, one hour of credit represents three hours of work each week of the 16-week semester. Two of the hours are spent in class with the instructor, and one hour of additional work is expected outside of regularly scheduled class time.
In lecture/discussion courses, one hour of credit represents one hour each week in class, and two hours each week of work outside of class for the duration of the 16-week semester.

BFA Degree

Grade Rules

All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.
Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.

Course Level Requirement

A minimum of 3 credits of art history must be taken in courses numbered above 299.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules, Transfer Credit Rules

No more than 9 hours of independent study courses (ARTP 395, ARTP 495, ARTP 496, ARTP 499H; AHIS 390, AHIS 392, AHIS 395, AHIS 490, AHIS 492, AHIS 495, AHIS 499H) may count toward the major in the BFA degree.
At least 36 credit hours in studio art and 9 credit hours in art history of the required BFA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A minor in Art – 18 credits

AHIS 101 Intro to Art History & Criticism I 3

AHIS 102 Intro to Art History & Criticism II 3

Studio Electives 12

Select from:

ARTP 101 Fundamentals of Art (3 cr)

CERM 131 Ceramics for Non-Majors (3 cr)

DRAW 101 Beginning Drawing (3 cr)

PHOT 161 Photography for Non-Majors (3 cr)

PRNT 141 Printmaking for Non-Majors (3 cr)

SCLP 111 Sculpture for Non-Majors (3 cr)

Plan B minor in Art – 12 credits

Studio Electives 12

Select from:

ARTP 101 Fundamentals of Art (3 cr)

CERM 131 Ceramics for Non-Majors (3 cr)

DRAW 101 Beginning Drawing (3 cr)

PHOT 161 Photography for Non-Majors (3 cr)

PRNT 141 Printmaking for Non-Majors (3 cr)

SCLP 111 Sculpture for Non-Majors (3 cr)

Up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass may be taken in the minor.

Athletic Training

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Nutrition & Health Sciences

PROGRAM: Athletic Training

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Vicki Fisher

DESCRIPTION

Athletic training is the art and science of treating athletic injuries. The Commission on Accreditation of Athletic Training Education (CAATE) develops and maintains guidelines for colleges and universities to provide an education for athletic training and verifies that those standards have been met. The University of Nebraska–Lincoln athletic training program is currently granted accreditation status by the CAATE. The underlying philosophy of this program is the same as with all other components of the University of Nebraska athletic medicine program.

The athletic training education program is dedicated to providing students with educational programming that is recognized as excellent. It is dedicated to providing students with opportunities to have clinical experiences with teams noted for excellence, in facilities noted for excellence. It is also expected that students will display excellence in academic and clinical settings, and will adhere to the highest standards as put forth in the National Athletic Trainers Association Code of Professional Ethics. The University of Nebraska athletic training education program is dedicated to the continual assessment of our program and our students in order to maintain our standards.

The athletic training education program is housed in the Department of Nutrition and Health Sciences. Completion of the entire program constitutes a major field of study. Students completing the course of study are eligible to sit for the National Athletic Trainers Association Board of Certification Examination.

Students are required to earn a B- or higher in ATHT 145 in order to continue in the program. All other ATHT courses must be a C+ or higher and must average at least 3.0 to remain in good standing in the program and graduate. The minimum grade requirements for other courses vary. Students are strongly encouraged to contact the advising center for a complete program description.

Admission to the athletic training education program is competitive. Included in athletic training education are six semesters of required clinical internship.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 32

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. EDPS 330 or EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. 3

ACE 10. ATHT 445 (Professional Requirement) 3

Professional Requirements 45

ATHT 145, ATHT 146, ATHT 245, ATHT 246, ATHT 249, ATHT 446 (3 hrs ea) 18

ATHT 345 and ATHT 346 (4 hrs ea) 8

ATHT 247, ATHT 248, ATHT 347, ATHT 348, ATHT 447, ATHT 448 (1 hr ea) 6

NUTR 100, NUTR 250, NUTR 384, NUTR 484 (3 hrs ea) 12

NUTR 150 1

Supporting Courses 30-34

ATHC 279 3

MATH 102 or MATH 103 or MATH 106 2-5

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L 4

BIOS 214 5

CHEM 110 4

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151 4-5

Electives 9-13

Total Hours 120

ADMISSION

Before a student is admitted to the athletic training education program, they must undergo a period of observation in the training rooms at the University of Nebraska. This period serves two purposes. First, it allows the student to make an informed decision about whether they wish to pursue athletic training as a career. Second, it allows the staff athletic trainers to observe the students work habits and social skills. The ability to work long and sometimes tedious hours and the ability to work well with people is absolutely necessary to be a successful athletic trainer.

Observation lasts for one year, and is tied to the completion of ATHT 145 and ATHT 146. During the first few weeks of the fall semester, the student will be assigned to a rotation between the various sports and training rooms at the University of Nebraska. The student will be asked to observe approximately five hours per week with the various athletic trainers at UNL. During these rotations, the student is expected to finish weekly assignments, which reflect the knowledge and abilities that are expected of an introductory student in athletic training. If a student does not complete the course of study or does not complete ATHT 145 and ATHT 146 with a grade of B- or better, they will be asked to repeat the observational period.

During the spring semester, the students interested in continuing the athletic training curriculum will apply to the director of athletic training for admittance to ATHT 247. Applications will be considered based on the following criteria:

Completion of ATHT 145 and ATHT 146 with a grade of B- or better.
A cumulative grade point average of 2.75 or better.
Evaluations provided by the staff athletic trainers supervising the students during their observational experiences.
Completion of an application provided by the director of athletic training education, along with an interview with the admissions committee.

There are a maximum number of students that may be admitted to the curriculum. Therefore, this application process is competitive. Candidates will be evaluated by the entire athletic training staff, and will be selected based on the work and academic criteria outlined above.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Professional Requirements

Athletic Training

A grade of C+ or higher and an overall GPA of 3.0 is required in all ATHT courses unless otherwise indicated.

ATHT 145 Intro to Athletic Training (grade of B- or higher is required)

ATHT 146 First Aid, Treatment, & Management of Athletic Injuries (grade of B- or higher is required)

ATHT 245 Organization & Administration of Athletic Training

ATHT 246 Prevention & Care of Athletic Injuries

ATHT 249 Therapeutic Modalities

ATHT 345 Evaluation of Athletic Injuries

ATHT 346 Rehabilitation & Reconditioning

ATHT 445 Advanced Studies in Athletic Training

ATHT 446 Medical Aspects of Athletic Training

ATHT 247 Clinical Education I

ATHT 248 Clinical Education II

ATHT 347 Clinical Education III

ATHT 348 Clinical Education IV

ATHT 447 Clinical Education V

ATHT 448 Clinical Education VI

Nutrition and Health Sciences

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health (grade of C+ or higher is required)

NUTR 150 Foundations in Nutrition & Health Promotion

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism (grade of C+ or higher is required)

NUTR 384 Biomechanics of Human Movement (grade of C+ or higher is required)

NUTR 484 Physiology of Exercise (grade of C+ or higher is required)

Supporting Courses

ATHC 279 Coaching Effectiveness & Psychological Components of Sports Performance (grade of C+ or higher is required)

EDPS 330 Measurement & Evaluation in Nutrition, Fitness & Health Promotion or EDPS 459 Statistical Methods or STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics (grade of C or higher is required)

PSYC 181 Intro to Psychology (grade of C+ or higher is required)

MATH 102 Trigonometry or MATH 103 College Algebra & Trigonometry or MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I (grade of C or higher is required)

Supporting Sciences

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab (grade of C or higher is required)

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab (grade of C or higher is required)

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab (grade of C+ or higher is required)

BIOS 214 Human Anatomy (grade of C+ or higher is required)

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

PHYS 141 Elementary General Physics I or PHYS 151 Elements of Physics

Electives

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grades of D-, D, D+, C- satisfy requirements of the programs in human sciences unless specified otherwise under the Programs and Departments section of the bulletin. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, or C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course, particularly if it is in the major area.

Grades Earned Outside UN System

Up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

OTHER

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Business Administration

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Business Administration

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (24 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–for non business students only

CHIEF ADVISER: D’vee Buss

DESCRIPTION

The business administration major is designed for students who wish to obtain a broad education in business administration rather than specializing in a specific area within the College. For the student who has an educational goal that bridges two or more areas of business, the general business administration major permits the design of a tailor-made program to fit that goal.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 24 hours of course work for the major.

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.

No departmental 399/499 courses may count toward the business administration major.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in business administration are to complete 24 hours of 300/400-level business course work for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M) to be selected from course work offered by:

Accounting
Economics
Finance
Management or Supply Chain
Marketing

As part of the 24 hour requirement:

Course work must be from the 300/400-level with the course work selected from the following approved list.
A MINIMUM of 3 hours from each of five departments must be represented.
A MINIMUM of 6 hours from each of three departments must be represented.
A MINIMUM of 12 hours must be taken at the 400 level.
Departmental 499s (unless an honors thesis) may NOT be used toward the major.

Accounting:

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

ACCT 309 Accounting Systems

ACCT 313 Intermediate Accounting I

ACCT 314 Intermediate Accounting II

Any 400-level accounting course work

Economics:

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics

ECON 321 Intro to International Economics

Any 400-level economics course work

Finance:

FINA 338 Principles of Corporate Risk Management

FINA 363 Investment Principles

FINA 365 Financial Institutions & Markets

Any 400-level finance or actuarial science course work

Management:

MNGT/ENTR 321 Entrepreneurship & Innovation in Organizations

MNGT 361 Human Resource Management

MNGT 311 Leadership, Communications, & Teams

SCMS 335 Supply Chain Decision Making Models

Any 400-level management or supply chain management course work

Marketing:

MRKT 346 Marketing Channels Management

MRKT 347 Marketing Communication Strategy

MRKT 345 Market Research

MRKT 350 Marketing Information Systems

MRKT 355 Marketing Metrics

Any 400-level marketing course work

Additional Restrictions:

Students who earn BSAD 491 (6 hrs) from the Senshu (Japan) study abroad program may substitute 6 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in two of the three required departments.

Students who earn BSAD 491 (3 hrs) from the CBA China study abroad program may substitute 3 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in one of the three required departments.

Students who earn BSAD 491 (3 hrs) from the CBA CIMBA (Italy) study abroad program may substitute 3 hours of BSAD 491 toward the second course in one of the three required departments.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in any upper-level course work offered by the departments requires completion of appropriate prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions for specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

General Business Minor—Plan A Only

The minor consists of the following 18 hours:

ACCT 200 Accounting for Business Decisions (3 hrs)

ECON 200 Economic Essentials & Issues (3 hrs)

BLAW 300 Business Government & Society (3 hrs)

FINA 300 Financial Decision Making (3 hrs)

MNGT 300 Management Essentials for Contemporary Organizations (3 hrs)

MRKT 300 Contemporary Marketing (3 hrs)

Please note the following information.

This minor is available to all other colleges at UNL.
Only nonbusiness students can complete this minor.
Courses in the minor can’t be used towards a degree in business
Prerequisites are enforced.
No more than one course may be transferred into the minor. The number of courses is calculated on the course replaced. If ACCT 201 and ACCT 202 are used to replace ACCT 200, it is one course
Students with previous credit in business should see their college adviser for further information.

OTHER

All students enrolling in CBA courses are required to meet the prerequisites listed for each course, including any specific grade or GPA requirement, to include junior standing, as well as expected completion of the BCF and BCI for enrollment in most 300 or 400-level business courses. This includes the required course work in information systems, communications, mathematics and statistics, accounting, and economics as well as marketing, finance, production, MIS, human resources, and business law prior to enrolling in course work for their major.

Business Administration majors are not eligible to add an International Business minor.

Business Minor for Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science & Management (ENGR)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Business Minor for Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 29

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

DESCRIPTION

This minor is applicable ONLY to students participating in the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management.

The College of Engineering enables its students to participate in this approved minor subject to the following conditions:

1. A minor will not reduce or alter the existing course or degree requirements for students electing to pursue a minor.

2. A student’s minor program must be organized and approved by an adviser prior to the submission of the senior check to the department chair or head.

3. The minor must be approved by the adviser, the department chair or head, the Dean and the cognizant program offering the minor.

4. The College of Engineering will follow the “Plan A/B” format of the Arts and Sciences College in which a student pursuing a single minor must complete the “Plan A” requirements. A student pursuing a double (or greater) minor must fulfill either the “Plan A” or “Plan B” requirements for both minors depending on which plan is offered by the cognizant department.

5. Minors on the Lincoln or Omaha campuses may be added by approval of the College of Engineering Curriculum Committee and faculty.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Hours

Required Foundation Courses 16-17

MATH 106, MATH 107, or MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I, II or III 4-5

STAT 218 Intro to Statistics or STAT 380 Statistics & Applications or
IMSE 321 Engineering Statistics & Data Analysis 3

RAIK 181H Honors: Foundations of Business I 3

RAIK 182H Honors: Foundations of Business II 3

RAIK 281H Honors: Business Systems & Operations I 3

Required Business Core Courses 12

MRKT 341 Marketing 3

RAIK 282H Honors: Business Systems & Operations II 3

RAIK 381H Honors: Advanced Topics in Business I 3

RAIK 382H Honors: Advanced Topics in Business II 3

Total hours for the RAIK/BSAD minor 28-29

Civil Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Civil Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 130

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Andrzej S. Nowak

DESCRIPTION

Interim Chair: Bruce I. Dvorak

Associate Chair: Stansbury

Professors: Dahab, Dvorak, Nowak, Rilett, Sicking, Tuan, Zhang

Associate Professors: Admiraal, Bartelt-Hunt, Guo, Jones, Khattak, Kim, Krause, Moussavi, Rohde, Stansbury, Szerszen

Assistant Professors: Irmak, X. Li, Y. Li, Sharma

The Department of Civil Engineering offers a complete undergraduate program to students on the Lincoln and Omaha campuses of the University of Nebraska. Curriculum requirements are nearly identical on both campuses. The goal is to prepare students for entry into the civil engineering profession immediately after graduation or to pursue graduate-level work.

The general educational objectives of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln civil engineering undergraduate program are to prepare our graduates to:

APPLY their solid foundation in civil engineering toward the practice and to obtain an advanced-degree education toward a broad range of career choices;
PERFORM technical analysis or design of a complex system, component or process as acting representatives of governmental agencies, private consulting engineering firms, research organizations or industry;
EXPLAIN engineering concepts accurately and effectively to inform technical and non-technical audiences using appropriate verbal, written, virtual and graphical means;
APPLY basic project management and business concepts and processes;
ENGAGE in lifelong learning to foster technical growth, ethical conduct, and the practice of professional communication, teamwork and leadership skills; and
OBTAIN licensure in a profession, such as civil engineering, after the requisite number of years of practice.

As a professional discipline, civil engineering is closely related to the total human environment. In all professional endeavors, the civil engineer must consider ecological effects as well as the social, economic, and political needs of people. The civil engineer designs systems to control and manage our water resources to provide electric power, agricultural irrigation, flood control, recreation, water supplies and wastewater treatment systems for our urban and industrial needs.

The civil engineer plans, designs, and constructs our transportation systems including highways, railroads, waterways, and airports to connect rural, urban, and industrial areas. The civil engineer also designs and constructs housing and facilities for recreational, industrial, and commercial complexes, which comprise the urban environment. It is the responsibility of civil engineering to minimize air, water, and land pollution and protect the environment.

Instructional emphasis is placed on fundamental engineering principles derived from mathematics, chemistry, physics, and engineering science. These subjects provide a sound background for the subsequent introductory courses in environmental, geotechnical, structural, transportation, and water resources engineering. Students are introduced to design concepts in the freshman year. Design is incorporated throughout the curriculum that culminates in two senior-level courses, CIVE 385 Professional Practice and Management in Civil Engineering and CIVE 489 Senior Design Project.

Instructional laboratories in environmental engineering, hydraulics, geotechnical engineering, structures, and surveying provide each student with an opportunity to learn, through individual participation, the operation of the testing equipment used to establish engineering design criteria and to monitor and model engineering facilities such as water and wastewater treatment plants, river control systems, and structural systems.

Some students may desire to obtain a degree in construction management in addition to the degree in civil engineering. Because some civil engineering courses require prerequisites beyond those required for similar construction management courses, students should obtain the civil engineering degree first. Advising will be done by a civil engineering faculty member familiar with the construction management curriculum. After completing the civil engineering degree, the student will move to the construction management department to complete requirements for the second undergraduate degree in construction management.

The Departments of Civil Engineering and Architecture have a joint program awarding licensing degrees in both fields of study. A bachelors degree in civil engineering and masters degree in architecture are awarded, after approximately seven years of study. The departments work with individual students in tailoring a joint degree program. More information can be obtained from either department office.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree of Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering (Lincoln and Omaha campuses)

Students must have completed the equivalent of the third semester before admission to the civil engineering program. Transfer students must have all transfer hours accepted before being considered for the degree program.

First Semester Hours

CIVE 112 Intro to Civil Engineering 1

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

CSCE 155N Computer Science I: Engineering & Science Focus 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Chemistry Elective 4

Chemistry elective must be CHEM 111, CHEM 113, or both CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 (8 hrs).

Total 16

Second Semester Hours

CIVE 130 Computer-aided Design 2

MECH 130 is an acceptable substitute.

CIVE 221 Geometric Control Systems 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 5

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 17

Third Semester Hours

ENGM 223 Engineering Statics 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Either CHEM 114 & CHEM 116, or CHEM 221 are acceptable substitutes.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 17

Fourth Semester Hours

CIVE 361 Highway Engineering 3

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication 3

ENGM 325 Mechanics of Elastic Bodies 3

ENGM 373 Engineering Dynamics 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations for Engineers 3

Total 15

Fifth Semester Hours

CIVE 310 Fluid Mechanics 3

CIVE 319 Hydraulics Lab 1

CIVE 326 Intro to Environmental Engineering 3

CIVE 327 Environmental Engineering Lab 1

CIVE 341 Intro to Structural Engineering 4

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications or IMSE 321 Engineering Statistics &
Data Analysis 3

Total 15

Sixth Semester Hours

CIVE 334 Intro to Geotechnical Engineering 4

CIVE 352 Intro to Water Resources Engineering 3

CIVE 378 Materials of Construction 3

CIVE 385 Professional Practice & Management 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 16

Seventh Semester Hours

Technical Elective 3

A description of allowable technical elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Design Electives 6

A full list of approved elective courses is available from the department.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Science Elective 4

Approved science elective courses include BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L, CHEM 251 & CHEM 253, and GEOL 101.

Total 16

Eighth Semester Hours

CIVE 489 Senior Design Project 3

Technical Electives 9

A description of allowable technical elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Design Elective 3

A full list of approved elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Professional Development Elective 3

A full list of approved professional development elective courses is available from the civil engineering department.

Total 18

Total Credit Hours Required 130

Design Electives

CIVE 419 Flow Systems Design (3 cr)

CIVE 425 Process Design in Water Supply & Wastewater Treatment (3 cr)

CIVE 426 Design of Water Treatment Facilities (3 cr)

CIVE 427 Design of Wastewater Treatment & Disposal Facilities (3 cr)

CIVE 436 Foundation Engineering (3 cr)

CIVE 440 Reinforced Concrete Design I (3 cr)

CIVE 441 Steel Design I (3 cr)

CIVE 452 Water Resources Development (3 cr)

CIVE 462 Highway Design (3 cr)

CIVE 463 Traffic Control System Design (3 cr)

Classics & Religious Studies

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Classics & Religious Studies

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–Classics; Religious Studies

CHIEF ADVISERS: Yaroslav Komarovski (Religious Studies); Thomas Rinkevich (Classics)

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Stephen G. Burnett, 237 Andrews Hall

Professors: S. Crawford, Turner

Associate Professors: Athanassopoulos (anthropology), Burnett, Duncan, Gorman, Lahey, Rinkevich, Wood

Assistant Professor: Komarvoski

Senior Lecturer: D. Crawford

The courses and majors in the Department of Classics and Religious Studies have been designed to meet the needs of three categories of students:

1 Those who wish to pursue the subjects for general educational purposes;

2 Those who plan to major and do graduate work in classics or religious studies;

3 Those who want to become high school Latin teachers.

Any student who studies classics and religious studies will acquire the basic elements of a liberal education and a beneficial background for study in professional schools.

The Major in Classics and Religious Studies

The classics and religious studies major offers a wide range of courses in the civilization, religions and culture of the ancient Mediterranean world, as well as ancient and modern religions broadly conceived. It is an interdisciplinary major with two areas of emphasis, one in Classics and one in Religious Studies. Depending on your chosen emphasis, this major is designed to provide you with an excellent background to pursue graduate work in classical languages and literature, classical archaeology, ancient history, religious studies, literary scholarship, and other humane disciplines. In addition, the broad and humane education offered by the major serves as excellent preparation for careers in law, medicine, journalism, religion, business and education.

The Major in Classical Languages

This major is intended primarily for those interested in graduate study of the Greco-Roman world. As competency in both Greek and Latin is requisite for graduate study, students must take courses in both languages to complete the major. This major is also appropriate for students who wish to undertake advanced study in related fields such as linguistics, or to teach high school Latin.

Education Abroad. Advanced undergraduates are encouraged to further their education abroad. Students may choose from among several established programs that cover a full academic year, semester, or summer. Most ancient studies programs offer a variety of courses in classics, ancient and modern languages, and history. In addition, students are introduced to the archaeology and art of the culture by frequent trips to sites and museums. These programs include, but are not limited to the American School of Classical Studies at Athens, College Year in Athens, the Intercollegiate Center for Classical Studies in Rome, and The Hebrew University in Jerusalem.

Also, UNL faculty frequently offer archaeological study tours to Greece, Italy, Turkey and Egypt during the summers. The department administers the Clarence A. Forbes Fellowship for education abroad. Further information on education abroad scholarships and programs may be found at http://educationabroad.unl.edu.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

Core Courses

CLAS 180 Classical Mythology (3 cr)

CLAS 283 Epic Tales: The World’s Heros & Gods (3 cr)

CLAS 286 Literature of the Ancient Near East (3 cr)

CLAS 305 Ancient Greek Religions (RELG 305) (3 cr)

CLAS 307 Early Christianity (HIST 307/RELG 307) (3 cr)

CLAS 312 Pagans & Christians in the Roman Empire (RELG 312) (3 cr)

CLAS 331 Ancient Israel (HIST 331/JUDS 331/RELG 331) (3 cr)

RELG 181 Judaism, Christianity, & Islam (3 cr)

Specific Major Requirements

The major requires 30 hours of courses. Students will choose 9 hours from the Core Course list above. In addition, each student will choose an emphasis in either Classics or Religious Studies (described below). Twelve hours must be taken at the 300 level or above. The student may count up to 6 hours above the 100 level in Greek, Latin, Hebrew, or Arabic toward the major. No more than 6 hours of independent study may count toward the major. A minor is required and may be any Plan A minor approved by the College.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required:

1. To assemble and maintain a portfolio to include the syllabus and a copy of all written exams and assignments for each course applied toward the major.

2. In their senior year, to complete a written exit survey.

The undergraduate adviser will inform students of the scheduling and format of assessment activities.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Requirements for the Emphasis in Classics

Students may divide their courses among the following areas, provided 6 hours are taken in each area. Core courses may also count toward the area requirements.

Area A. Arts and Archaeology

AHIS 211 Classical Art & Archaeology

AHIS 311 Greek Art & Archaeology

AHIS 313 Roman Art & Archaeology

AHIS 411 Classical Architecture

AHIS 413 Roman Painting

CLAS 252 Archaeology of World Civilizations (ANTH 252)

CLAS 320 The Classical World: Archaeology & Texts

CLAS 438/838 Topics in Old World Prehistory (ANTH 438)

Area B. Language, Thought, and Literature

CLAS 180 Classical Mythology

CLAS 183 Heros, Harlots & Helots

CLAS 281 The World of Classical Greece (ENGL 240A)

CLAS 282 The World of Classical Rome (ENGL 240B)

CLAS 283 Epic Tales: The World’s Heros & Gods

CLAS 286 Literature of the Ancient Near East

CLAS 381 Ancient Novel (ENGL 381)

CLAS 409 Religion of Late Western Antiquity (HIST 409/RELG 409)

CLAS 483 Classical Drama (ENGL 440)

ENGL 340 Classical Roots of English Literature

PHIL 231 History of Philosophy (Ancient)

PHIL 336 Ethics: Ancient & Medieval

PHIL 337 Knowledge: Ancient & Medieval

PHIL 338 Metaphysics: Ancient & Medieval

PHIL 450 Ancient Philosophy

Area C. Historical Studies

CLAS 141 Spectacle & Entertainment in the Roman World

CLAS 233 Science in the Classical World

CLAS 245 War in the Classical World

CLAS 305 Ancient Greek Religions (RELG 305)

CLAS 307 Early Christianity (HIST 307/RELG 307)

CLAS 312 Pagans & Christians in the Roman Empire (RELG 312)

CLAS 315 Medieval World: Byzantium (HIST 315)

CLAS 331 Ancient Israel (HIST 331/JUDS 331/RELG 331)

CLAS 440 Gender & Sexuality in the Ancient World (WMNS 440)

HIST 210 Ancient Rome

HIST 311 Homer & the Trojan War

HIST 317 The Roman Empire

HIST 412 Democracy & Tyranny in Classical Athens

HIST 417 The Roman Revolution, 133 BCE-68 CE

Requirements for the Emphasis in Religious Studies

Students may divide their courses among the following areas, provided 6 hours are taken in each area. Core courses may also count toward the area requirements.

Area D. The Nature of Religion

RELG 125W Religion, Peace & Social Justice

RELG 150 Explaining Religion

RELG 206 Ways of Western Religion

RELG 220 Reason & Religion

RELG 225 Science & Religion

RELG 310 Great Ideas in Religious Thought: From God to Nothingness

RELG 350 Issues in the Theory & Study of Religion

RELG 418 Fundamentalism, Religion, & Politics

PHIL 265 Philosophy of Religion

PHIL 338 Metaphysics: Ancient & Medieval

SOCI 452 Sociology of Religion

Area E. Scriptural Studies

RELG 205 Intro to the Hebrew Bible/Old Testament (JUDS 205)

RELG 212W Life & Letters of Paul

RELG 217 Israel: The Holy Land (HIST 217/JUDS 217)

RELG 307 Early Christianity (CLAS 307/HIST 307)

RELG 308 Dead Sea Scrolls (JUDS 308)

RELG 331 Ancient Israel (CLAS 331/HIST 331/JUDS 331)

RELG 340 Women in the Biblical World (JUDS 340/WMNS 340)

RELG 406 Second Temple Judaism (JUDS 406)

ENGL 341 The Bible as Literature

Area F. The Study of Religious Traditions

RELG 108 World Religions

RELG 118 Intro to Asian Religions

RELG 130W Women & Religion

RELG 134W Religious Diversity in the United States

RELG 181 Judaism, Christianity & Islam

RELG 208 Intro to Islam

RELG 209 Judaism & Christianity in Conflict & Coexistence (JUDS 209)

RELG 218 Intro to Buddhism

RELG 230 Tibetan Buddhism

RELG 305 Ancient Greek Religions (CLAS 305)

RELG 318 Islam in the Modern World

RELG 332 Jews in the Middle Ages (HIST 332/JUDS 332)

RELG 334 Jews, Christians & the Bible (JUDS 334)

RELG 351 Death, Immortality & Transcendence in Asian Religions

RELG 370 Religion & Reform: Utopian & Communal Societies in America (ANTH 370)

RELG 409 Religion of Late Western Antiquity (CLAS 409/HIST 409)

RELG 410 Gnosticism (CLAS 410)

RELG 489 Medieval Literature & Theology (ENGL 489)

CLAS 286 Literature of the Ancient Near East

CLAS 312 Pagans & Christians in the Roman Empire (RELG 312)

HIST 214 History of Islam (RELG 214)

HIST 216 History of Christianity (RELG 216)

HIST 219 Intro to Jewish History (JUDS 219/RELG 219)

HIST 421 The German Reformation

JUDS 350 Literature of Judaism

MUSC 451 Music & the Church

MUSC 452 Hymnology

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Departmental permission to take major or minor courses for Pass/No Pass credit must be obtained. Request forms are available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Requirements for the Minor in Classics

A minimum of 18 hours in the courses listed in A, B, and C. At least 3 hours must be taken from each area, and at least 9 of those hours must be CLAS. At least 6 hours must be above 299.

Requirements for the Minor in Religious Studies

A minimum of 18 hours in the courses listed in D, E, and F. At least 3 hours must be taken from each area, and at least 9 of those hours must be RELG. At least 6 hours must be above 299.

Computational Biology & Bioinformatics Minor

COLLEGE: Engineering, Arts & Sciences, Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Computational Biology & Bioinformatics (Minor only)

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Computer Science and Engineering Department, 256 Avery Hall, Phone: (402) 472-2401, Email: cbb@unl.edu.

Steering Committee: Etsuko Moriyama (SBS), Stephen E. Reichenbach (CSE), Stephen D. Kachman (Statistics), Jeyamkondan Subbiah (BSE)

This interdisciplinary minor prepares students to understand, use, and develop advanced computational methods and tools for processing, visualizing, and analyzing biological data and for modeling biological processes. Studies in computational biology and bioinformatics involve biosciences, computer science, engineering, mathematics, and statistics. Students will be prepared for careers in biomedical, biotechnology, agricultural, pharmaceutical, and engineering fields and for related graduate studies.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

18 hours: Includes 13 hours for the core courses and at minimum 5 hours from elective courses are required.

Foundation courses

The following courses are required for the CBB minor students to have the necessary foundations towards the minor. These courses are also the prerequisites to the core courses listed below:

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I (4 cr) or equivalent

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab (4 cr)

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I (5 cr) or equivalent

Core courses (13 hours)*

CSCE 155T Computer Science I (3 cr)

CSCE 311 Data Structures & Algorithms for Informatics (3 cr) (starts Spring 2012)

BIOS 237 Basic Application of Bioinformatics (4 cr)

STAT 218 Intro to Statistics or STAT 380 Statistics & Applications (3 cr) (special section of STAT 218 for CBB minor may be offered in Fall 2011)**

*These requirements can be replaced with equivalent courses upon approval except for BIOS 237, which cannot be replaced.

**Students are strongly encouraged to take STAT 218 or STAT 380. However, ELEC 305 (Probability Theory & Intro to Random Processes) can be used to satisfy this requirement subject to approval.

Elective courses: Two courses (5 hours minimum) at 400 levels

Take one each from Life Science electives and Computer Science/Mathematics/Statistics/Engineering (CMSE) electives in the following lists. These lists will be updated periodically. Similar courses can be used to fulfill elective requirements upon approval by the CBB Minor steering committee.
For life science major students, those courses listed as LS elective 2 cannot be used for CBB requirements. For students in computer science, mathematics, engineering, and related majors, those courses listed as CMSE elective 2 cannot be used for CBB requirements.

Life Science elective courses

LS elective 1: for students in life science majors

BIOS 427 Practical Bioinformatics Laboratory (3 cr)

BIOS 428 Perl Programming for Biological Applications (3 cr)

BIOS 456 Mathematical Models in Biology (3 cr)

BIOS 477 Bioinformatics & Molecular Evolution (3 cr)

STAT 442 Computational Biology (3 cr)

LS elective 2

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism (4 cr)

BIOC 432 Gene Expression & Replication (2 cr)

BIOC 434 Plant Biochemistry (3 cr)

BIOS 420 Molecular Genetics (3 cr)

BIOS 425 Plant Biotechnology (3 cr)

BIOS 429 Phylogenetic Biology (4 cr)

BIOS 472 Evolution (4 cr)

Computer Science/Mathematics/Statistics/Engineering Electives

CMSE elective 1: for students in computer science major

CSCE 471 Intro to Bioinformatics (3 cr)

CMSE elective 2

BSEN 414 Medical Imaging Systems (3 cr)

CHME 473 Biochemical Engineering (3 cr)

CHEM 474 Advanced Biochemical Engineering (3 cr)

CSCE 410 Information Retrieval Systems (3 cr)

CSCE 413 Database Systems (3 cr)

CSCE 421 Foundations of Constraint Processing

CSCE 423 Algorithms (3 cr)

CSCE 435 Cluster & Grid Computing (3 cr)

CSCE 456 Parallel Programming (3 cr)

CSCE 471 Digital Image Processing (3 cr)

CSCE 474 Intro to Data Mining (3 cr)

CSCE 476 Intro to Artificial Intelligence (3 cr)

CSCE 478 Intro to Machine Learning (3 cr)

CSCE 479 Intro to Neural Networks (3 cr)

MATH 439 Mathematical Models in Biology (3 cr)

MATH 452 Graph Theory (3 cr)

STAT 412 Intro to Experimental Design

STAT 450 Intro to Regression Analysis

Computer Engineering (Omaha)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Computer Engineering (Lincoln)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 133

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISER: Dr. Bing Chen

DESCRIPTION

Interim Chair: Roger Sash, PKI 201E

Professors: Chen, Sharif, Wysocki

Associate Professors: Ci, Jang, Nguyen, Peng, Sash

Assistant Professors: Qian, Yang

Senior Lecturers: Detloff, Gilmore

Phone: 402-554-2288

FAX: 402-554-2289

Website: http://ceen.unl.edu

Email: rsash1@unl.edu

The computer engineering program is administered by the Department of Computer and Electronics Engineering (CEEN) and the bachelor of science degree program is accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of ABET, http://www.abet.org.

Mission

The mission of the Department of Computer and Electronics Engineering (CEEN) at the University of Nebraska is to develop and maintain programs of excellence in teaching and research which meet the educational needs of its constituents, which will support the state of Nebraska in its development as a leading center for high-technology computer/electronics/ telecommunications industry and which will support national needs for well-educated computer and electronics engineering professionals.

Program Educational Objectives

The department’s Program Educational Objectives are a statement of what its graduates are doing or are capable of doing three to five years after graduation. The students in the computer engineering program receive a strong foundation in engineering science and design that will enable them to pursue productive careers in not only the computer engineering field, but can also be used as the foundation for careers in other areas such as business, management, and medicine. Typical industries in which the computer engineering graduate would be employed could include those microprocessor/embedded system design, digital design, hardware/software integration, and computer architecture and parallel processing

The Program Educational Objectives for the computer engineering program are that our graduates will:

Be employed in industries doing work utilizing the education and skills attained through their undergraduate engineering program
Be able to function on teams with multidisciplinary aspects
Participate in lifelong learning
Exhibit competency in communication skills
Have an ethical approach to engineering practice.

These Program Educational Objectives were developed with input from the program’s educational objectives constituency consisting of employers (including CEEN Industry Advisory Board), graduates of the program, and faculty of the department.

The individual holding this degree will have advanced knowledge in his or her field of engineering interest and in addition will have a university educational background involving mathematics, the physical sciences, and the humanities and social sciences. Completion of this curriculum will enable the graduate to enter employment in positions involving computer hardware design and applications, computer software design and development, microcomputer based applications, and computer networking. The program also leads to the preparation for graduate work in computer engineering, computer science or electrical engineering.

Concentrations

The department offers several areas of concentrations so students can attain an in-depth study of a topic in computer engineering or electronics engineering. The computer engineering concentrations are:

Advanced Digital Design

This area includes advanced digital design topics from both the circuit and system perspectives. Topics include the structure and analysis of digital integrated circuits, interface signal integrity, Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) design and synthesis, Very Large Scale Integration (VLSI) design, and advanced processor designs. Lab exercises provide hands-on experience with design tools and the design process.

Multimedia Systems

This area includes topics on 1) the temporal and spectral analysis of digital signals and systems, the design of digital filters and systems, and advanced systems including multi-rate digital signal processing techniques; 2) the spatial and spectral analysis of digital images, the design of multi-dimensional digital filters and systems, and advanced theories and technologies in multimedia processing systems; and 3) the software and hardware system designs for real-time and offline machine vision and multimedia understanding systems.

ADMISSION

General Requirements

Advisement

Upon entry into the curriculum, each student will be assigned a faculty academic adviser. It is required that the student meet with the adviser prior to each class registration period and that all courses to be applied toward the degree be selected with the advice and approval of the adviser. Students are expected to have their academic records reviewed and obtain approval from the department prior to application to the University registrar for award of the degree in order to insure that all curricular requirements will be satisfied by the time of intended graduation.

Curriculum

Because of the rapid developments in the fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering, the curricular requirements are continually reviewed and upgraded to reflect technological advances. Curricular sequence and course descriptions contained herein are intended to serve as general guidelines. Contact the department for information on any changes to the requirements that are currently in effect but not listed in this catalog. Currently enrolled students are expected to modify their programs to take advantage of such revisions. Students who do not maintain continuous progress toward the degree through enrollment in applicable course work will be considered as new students upon reentering the computer or electronics engineering curricular sequence and will be subject to the requirements of the curriculum current at the time of their reentry. Certain courses may not be valid as prerequisites or as credit toward the degree after two academic years; the student’s academic adviser should be consulted regarding applicability.

The department maintains a high standard of excellence in meeting its objective of providing the student with extensive experience in the fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. The development of both hardware and software and the knowledge of the interrelationship of these areas is enhanced through the extensive use of laboratory equipment. The applicable University bulletins and College academic policies must be followed to ensure that the student satisfies the campus general education requirements.

Senior Thesis

The capstone senior thesis requirement provides a unique and challenging opportunity for the undergraduate student to demonstrate his/her ability to apply the knowledge gained in the course work sequence to the planning, design, execution, testing and reporting of a significant project in the applications of engineering principles. The initiative and responsibility expected of the student executing the senior thesis parallel the expectations of the employer of the program graduate.

Electives

Computer engineering and electronic engineering courses which are described in the catalog but are not shown as requirements in the semester sequences are offered as the need arises to provide co-interest areas wherein the students may broaden their background in the applications of computer engineering or electronics engineering. In addition, appropriate specified technical electives will be selected to augment the student’s particular area of interest. The applicability of transfer course work with engineering content toward credit in the curriculum is determined on a case-by-case basis by the department.

Special Interest Areas

Opportunities are provided for the development of areas of special interest through enrollment in the Individual Study in Computer and Electronics Engineering courses which are offered at the freshman through senior level for the student who may wish to develop a topic under the guidance of a department faculty member. Enrollment is by permission after the department chair has approved a written proposal. Special Topics in Computer and Electronics Engineering classes also are offered by the department as the need arises to cover topics needing emphasis as a result of the rapidly developing fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. Academic advisers should be consulted regarding the particular topics to be covered and the necessary prerequisites for each offering of this course.

Students who expect to continue their education at the graduate level after the award of the baccalaureate degree should consult their adviser regarding course selections that would enhance that objective.

Students are encouraged to develop their professional and leadership potential through participation in student chapters of related professional organizations and in University extracurricular activities. Participation in the University Honors Program is encouraged for those who qualify.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Typical Schedule

First Semester Hours

CEEN 103 Computer & Electronics Engineering Fundamentals 4

CSCE 155A Computer Science I or CSCE 155E Computer Science I: Systems Engineering Focus 3

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument 3

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

Total 15

Second Semester Hours

CEEN 106 Microprocessor Applications 3

CEEN 225 Computer & Electronics Engineering Seminar 1

CSCE 156 Computer Science II 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

PHYS 221 General Physics Lab I 1

Total 16

Third Semester Hours

CEEN 213 Electrical Circuits I 4

CEEN 218 Electrical Circuits Lab 1

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication 3

Total 15

Fourth Semester Hours

CEEN 222 Electronic Circuits I 4

CEEN 313 Switching Circuit Theory 4

JGEN 300 Technical Writing 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication 3

Total 18

Fifth Semester Hours

CEEN 310 Digital Design & Interfacing 4

CEEN 332 Assembly Language Programming 1

CSCE 310 Data Structures & Algorithms 3

MATH 314 Applied Linear Algebra (Matrix Theory) 3

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications 3

ACE Elective SLO 5 3

Total 17

Sixth Semester Hours

CEEN 325 Communications Systems 4

CEEN 433 Microprocessor System Design 4

Conc/ENGR Electives 6

ACE Elective SLO 6 3

Total 17

Seventh Semester Hours

CEEN 436 Embedded Microcontroller Design 4

CEEN 496 Senior Thesis Proposal 1

ENGR 469 Tech, Science & Civ (UNO) 3

Conc/ENGR Electives 5

ACE Elective SLO 7 3

Total 16

Eighth Semester Hours

CEEN 499 Senior Thesis 3

Conc/ENGR Electives 6

ACE Electives SLO 8 & 9 6

Total 15

Students must complete one of the computer engineering concentrations.

Three of the engineering electives can be chosen from a list of approved non-CEEN courses.

Total Credit Hours Required 127

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

All course work must be of “C” grade level or higher to be credited toward graduation requirements or to be valid as a prerequisite for another course.

Computer Science

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Computer Science

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Charles Riedesel

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Steve Goddard, 256 Avery

Professors: Deogun, Dwyer, Elbaum, Goddard, Jiang, Ramamurthy, Reichenbach, Revesz, Rothermel, Samal, Seth (emeritus), Sincovec (emeritus), Surkan (emeritus)

Associate Professors: Choueiry, Cohen, Costello (emeritus), Lu, Scott, Soh, Srisa-an, Variyam, Vuran, Xu

Assistant Professors: Detweiler, Sarma, Yu, Zhong

Research Associate Professor: Swanson

Assistant Professor of Practice: Riedesel

Lecturers: Bourke, Suing

Phone: 402-472-2401

FAX: 402-472-7767

http://cse.unl.edu

email: info@cse.unl.edu

The UNL Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) offers Nebraska’s only comprehensive program of higher education, research, and service outreach in computer science and computer engineering.

The CSE department offers a challenging baccalaureate degree program in computer science that prepares graduates for professional practice as computer scientists, provides the basis for advanced studies in the field, and establishes a foundation for life-long learning and achievement. The BS degree in computer science is accredited by the Computing Accreditation Commission of ABET.

Consistent with these goals, the computer science baccalaureate program develops:

The ability to solve a wide range of computing-related problems. Studies include mathematical foundations, computer science theory, programming and software design, system components and design, application of theory, experimentation, design tools and techniques, and documentation and maintenance.
The ability to work with professionals in fields related to computing and/or having computing applications. Studies include natural sciences and the completion of at least one minor.
Skills to quickly adapt to new work environments, assimilate new information, and solve new problems. Studies include application of theory, experimentation, design tools and techniques, documentation and maintenance, and technical communications.
The background and perspective necessary to pursue post-graduate education. Studies include computer science theory, application of theory, experimentation, and life-long learning/professional development.
Abilities to work in conformance with societal needs and expectations. Studies include liberal arts and ethical/social issues.
Insight into the world of practicing professionals for collaborations, mutual support, and representing the profession to government and society. Studies include teamwork and life-long learning/professional development, plus students are provided multiple opportunities for involvement in organizations such as ACM and UPE; undergraduate research; and service to the department and community.

The CSE Department also offers a degree of bachelor of science in computer engineering through the College of Engineering. All students majoring in the CSE Department should see their advisers during their first semester to make sure they understand the differences in the requirements of the two programs. Majors must consult with their advisers each semester for registration advising.

Introductory Courses. Entering students may select from several introductory courses, according to their interests and as indicated by the CSE Placement Examination. The Computer Science I courses (CSCE 155A, CSCE 155H, CSCE 155E, CSCE 155N, and CSCE 155T) all provide a foundation in designing and programming computing solutions and prepare students for more advanced CSCE courses, including CSCE 156. These courses are designed to meet different interests. CSCE 155A is designed for students majoring in computer science or computer engineering. CSCE 155H is for honors students. CSCE 155E emphasizes computing for systems engineering, such as control systems, mobile computing, and embedded devices. CSCE 155N focuses on numerical and graphical computation in engineering and science, such as applied physics, working with time-sequence data, and matrix applications. CSCE 155T focuses on data and information processing, such as document or database applications, online commerce, or bioinformatics. CSCE 156 is for students with a background in designing and programming computing solutions, such as is provided by Computer Science I. CSCE 101 is for students seeking a broad introduction to computer science with brief instruction in computer programming.

Graduate Programs. The CSE department offers several graduate degree programs: master of science in computer science, master of science in computer science with computer engineering specialization, master of science in computer science with bioinformatics specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science, doctor of philosophy in engineering with computer engineering specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science with bioinformatics specialization, and joint doctor of philosophy in computer science and mathematics. See the Graduate Studies Bulletin for details.

ADMISSION

Other Admission Requirements

Computer Science Placement Policy. The required Computer Science and Engineering Placement Exam (CSEPE) is used to assess students’ background in problem solving, computer programming, and relevant mathematics. Students who have not taken a recognized UNL or transfer prerequisite course with a grade of C or better must take the CSEPE.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Computer Science (44 hours)

Computer Science Core (22-24 hrs)

CSCE 155A, CSCE 156, CSCE 230, CSCE 230L, CSCE 235, CSCE 251, CSCE 310, CSCE 322, and CSCE 361

Or for students in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management: RAIK 183H, RAIK 184H, RAIK 283H, RAIK 284H, RAIK 383H, CSCE 251, CSCE 322.

Depth Courses (6 hrs)

CSCE 351 or CSCE 451, and

CSCE 423 or CSCE 428

Technical Electives (9-11 hrs)

Any CSCE/RAIK 3xx or 4xx courses except CSCE 390, CSCE 490, and RAIK courses lacking CSCE equivalents (except that RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 384H, RAIK 401H, and RAIK 402H are acceptable as technical electives).

Up to 3 hours of CSCE 491 can be used for technical electives, and an additional 3 hours can be used toward the 125 hours required for the degree.

At most, one of MATH 428, MATH 432, MATH 433, MATH 439, MATH 450, MATH 452

Senior Design Experience (5 hrs)

CSCE 486 (or RAIK 381H or RAIK 382H), and CSCE 487 (or RAIK 302H or RAIK 402H). CSCE 486 and CSCE 487 are to be taken in consecutive semesters.

Students completing the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management automatically satisfy the technical electives and senior design experience requirements and need only CSCE 251, CSCE 322, and the 6 hours of depth courses to satisfy the computer science requirements.

Mathematics (16 hours)

MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 314, and STAT 380

Joint mathematics and computer science majors who take any two MATH 4xx courses listed under Technical Electives for Computer Science may apply one of those courses toward both majors.

Science (12 hours)

Must be in courses intended for science/engineering majors and must include at least two laboratories in a single science discipline. The CSE department has identified the following five disciplines with their acceptable courses:

Chemistry: CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 221 (or CHEM 113, CHEM 114, CHEM 116)
Physics and Astronomy: PHYS 211, PHYS 221, PHYS 212, PHYS 222, PHYS 213, PHYS 223, ASTR 204, ASTR 224
Biological Sciences: BIOS 102, BIOS 103 & BIOS 103L, BIOS 109, BIOS 111, BIOS 112, BIOS 112L, BIOS 205, BIOS 206, BIOS 207
Earth and Atmospheric Sciences: GEOL 101, GEOL 103H, GEOL 210, GEOL 410, METR 200, METR 205, METR 370
Anthropology: ANTH 242, ANTH 242L

NOTE: Bold face type indicates a lab course or that a lab is included with the course.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required in their senior year to complete a written exit survey.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Focus

A computer science major has the option of declaring a Focus in one of the areas listed below. Students who, in addition to meeting all computer science requirements listed above, receive a grade of C or better in each of three courses from one area below will receive a notice from the Department of Computer Science and Engineering stating that they received the degree bachelor of science in computer science with a Focus in their chosen area.

The Focus areas are as follows:

Informatics: CSCE 410, CSCE 413, CSCE 464, CSCE 470, CSCE 471, CSCE 472, CSCE 473, CSCE 474

Artificial Intelligence: CSCE 421, CSCE 475, CSCE 476, CSCE 478, CSCE 479

Computer and Networking Systems: CSCE 430, CSCE 432, CSCE 434, CSCE 435, CSCE 455, CSCE 456, CSCE 462

Foundations: CSCE 340, CSCE 421, CSCE 423, CSCE 424, CSCE 428, CSCE 477

In addition, up to 3 hours of CSCE 498 Computer Problems (undergraduate research) can be used in any focus area. Some offerings of CSCE 496 Special Topics may be substituted in an appropriate area. See your adviser for more details.

A Focus is in addition to all major requirements. Thus, no course used by a student to fulfill a major requirement can also be applied to a Focus.

Customized Focus Areas are possible. The department chair, in consultation with relevant faculty members and the undergraduate adviser, may approve a customized Focus Area proposed by a student. See your adviser for more information.

To declare a Focus, see your adviser.

Minor Requirements

The Plan A minor enables students to develop expertise in an additional academic area. Completing MATH 208 (in addition to the major requirements) meets the Plan A minor requirement for mathematics. See your adviser for more information.

Students who wish to take a cohesive block of courses that crosses departmental or even college lines should consider the Individualized Program of Studies minor offered by the College or a business minor offered by the College of Business Administration.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Departmental permission to take major or minor courses for Pass/No Pass credit must be obtained. Request forms are available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Course Level Requirement

13 hours of the CSCE courses must be at the 400 level for students not completing the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

For students not enrolled in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management: 18 hours of computer science courses, including CSCE 155 and CSCE 156 and at least 3 hours of CSCE courses at the 300 level or above, but excluding CSCE courses explicitly designated as not counting toward the minor.

For students enrolled in the J. S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management: 18 hours of computer science courses, including CSCE 183H/RAIK 183H, CSCE 184H/RAIK 184H, and CSCE 283H/RAIK 283H. For the remaining 7 hours, students may count any CSCE courses (or RAIK courses cross-listed as CSCE courses) numbered 200 or above (except CSCE 235 and courses designated as not counting toward the minor) and up to 3 hours for a RAIK Design Studio course (RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 401H, RAIK 402H).

Construction Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Construction Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Construction Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 128

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

DESCRIPTION

Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction

School Director: Eddy M. Rojas

Program Coordinator: George Morcous

Professors: Foster, Sires

Associate Professors: Bernstein, Bonsell, Goedert, Harmon, Jensen, Schwer

Assistant Professors: Lau, Norton, Pedersen

Construction engineering (CONE) is a program of the Charles W. Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction. The construction engineering major integrates engineering, construction, and management courses. This program is designed for persons fulfilling the construction industry’s need for licensed professional engineers. It resembles the construction management program but provides a greater emphasis on engineering, scientific, and technical courses so that requirements for licensure are met. The courses in construction engineering focus on the application of engineering principles to solve real world construction problems.

The educational objective of the construction engineering program is to produce graduates who possess lifelong knowledge acquisition skills enabling them to add value to society throughout their construction careers by applying engineering principles of analysis and design to the constructed environment and using appropriate construction practices including business organization, estimating, scheduling, project delivery, and ethics.

Under the stimulus of increasing demand for its services globally, the construction industry has expanded its technological capabilities pertaining to physical and informational systems. This demand gives the construction engineering graduate an unprecedented number of opportunities for employment and for pursuing an advanced degree.

Construction engineers participate in the preparation of engineering and architectural plans and specifications which they translate into finished projects, such as buildings, bridges, highways, power plants, or other constructed facilities. These projects involve thousands of details shared by a team of owners, architects, engineers, general constructors, specialty constructors, manufacturers, material suppliers, equipment distributors, regulatory bodies and agencies, labor resources, and numerous others. The constructor assumes responsibility for delivery of the completed project at a specified time and cost and also accepts associated legal, financial, and management obligations. Because of the broad scope of the construction engineer’s project responsibility, he/she must assure the project’s ability to be constructed as well as its ability to be operated and sustained.

The construction engineering student is required to enroll into a predetermined set of courses specifically designed for general construction education. Each student selects, with the approval of his/her adviser, a set of approved electives. The program outlined below leads to the bachelor of science degree in construction engineering.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Students are required to enroll in a predetermined set of courses specifically designed for general construction education. Each student selects, with the approval of his/her adviser, a set of approved electives.

First Semester Hours

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I 4

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication 3

CONE 103 Intro to Construction Engineering 1

CSCE 155E Computer Science I: Systems Engineering Focus 3

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

Total 16

Second Semester Hours

CIVE 130 Computer-aided Design 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

PHYS 221 General Physics Lab 1

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 15

Third Semester Hours

CIVE 221 Geometric Control Systems 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

MECH 223 Engineering Statics 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 17

Fourth Semester Hours

CONE 211 Construction Business Methods 3

BSEN 206 Engineering Economics 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

MECH 325 Mechanics of Elastic Bodies 3

MECH 373 Engineering Dynamics 3

Total 15

Fifth Semester Hours

CIVE 310 Fluid Mechanics 3

CIVE 341 Intro to Structural Engineering 4

CONE 319 Construction Methods & Equipment 3

CONE 378 Construction Estimating I 3

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications 3

Total 16

Sixth Semester Hours

CIVE 334 Intro to Geotechnical Engineering 4

CIVE 378 Materials of Construction 3

ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics 3

ELEC 211 Elements of Electrical Engineering 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 16

Seventh Semester Hours

CIVE 440 Reinforced Concrete Design I 3

CONE 414 Accident Prevention in Construction 3

CONE 476 Project Budgets & Controls 3

CONE 485 Construction Planning, Scheduling, & Controls 3

Technical Design Elective 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 18

Eighth Semester Hours

CIVE 441 Steel Design I 3

CONE 489 Construction Engineering Capstone Course 3

BLAW 371 Legal Environment 3

Technical Design Elective 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 15

Total Credit Hours Required 128

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

All course work must be of “C” grade level or higher to be credited toward graduation requirements or to be valid as a prerequisite for another course.

Electives–Technical and Design

Hours

CONE 416 Wood &/or Miscellaneoud Materials Design 3

CONE 417 Formwork Systems 3

CONE 466/866 Heavy &/or Civil Estimating 3

CONE 481/881 Highway & Bridge Construction 3

CONE 483/883 Support of Excavation 3

CONE 485/885 Temporary Construction 3

CONE 498 Special Topics 1-6

Course Substitutions and Suggestions

PHYS 222 is an acceptable substitute if taken with PHYS 212.
Suitable equivalent probability and statistics courses can be substituted with the approval of the student’s adviser.
Suitable technical electives selected with concurrence of adviser selected from the following: EMEC 4480, EMEC 4600, EMEC 4800; MENG 2000, MENG 4200 and their UNL equivalents. Other College of Engineering courses approved by the student’s adviser can satisfy this requirement.

Construction Management

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Construction Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Construction Management

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

DESCRIPTION

Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction

School Director: Eddy M. Rojas

Program Coordinator: Wayne Jensen

Associate Professors: Fischer, Grosskopf, Harmon, Jensen, Stentz, Wentz

Assistant Professor: Ahn, Shen

Construction is the largest and most diversified industry in the country, accounting for approximately 10 percent of the gross national product. The key professional in this vast enterprise is the “constructor”, a term given to the leaders and managers in the construction industry, having the responsibility for planning, scheduling, and building the projects designed by architects and engineers. These highly specialized efforts are indispensable in meeting the country’s growing need for new structures and environmental control projects.

Construction firms vary in size from large corporations to small proprietorships and partnerships. These are often classified according to the kind of construction work they do: general contractors, heavy and highway contractors, specialty contractors including mechanical and electrical, and residential builders and developers. Many firms engage in more than one category of work. Some larger companies incorporate the architectural and engineering design functions as part of their activity as a design/build firm. Collectively, Constructors build our entire man-made environment–buildings for housing, commerce, industry, and government; transportation services including highways, railroads, waterways, and airports; municipal service facilities and utilities, such as power plants and energy distribution systems; military bases and space center complexes. Thus the construction management field is broad and challenging, requiring a unique educational background for its professional practitioners.

Educational standards and criteria for construction education are established by the American Council for Construction Education (ACCE) which is the accrediting agency for construction education programs at all levels. The program at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, having met these standards and criteria, is currently fully accredited by ACCE.

Although the range of construction activities appears wide and diverse, the general educational requirements for construction management are universal regardless of a particular firm’s area of specialization. Since construction is primarily a business enterprise, the graduate must have a sound background in business management and administration areas, as well as an understanding of the fundamentals of architecture and engineering as they relate to the project design itself as well as to the actual construction process in the field. Professional expertise lies in the fields of construction science, methods, and management. A working knowledge of structural design, mechanical and electrical systems, soil mass behavior, and construction equipment is also essential.

The construction management curriculum embraces a course of study in specifications, contractual agreements, labor relations, personnel management, materials, methods, and work analysis techniques. Technical and humanity electives provide for a well-rounded education that leads to a challenging career in the construction industry.

Students interested in obtaining a degree in civil engineering and construction management are advised to enroll in civil engineering. Because some civil engineering courses require prerequisites beyond those required for similar construction management courses, students should obtain a civil engineering degree first. While in civil engineering, they will be advised by an adviser familiar with the construction management curriculum. After completing requirements for the civil engineering degree, the student will move to the construction management department to complete the requirements for the second degree in construction management.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree (Lincoln campus)

Construction management students must pass all courses offered within the College of Engineering and all math and science courses with a grade of “C” or higher. Students must complete 28 semester hours or be classified as a sophomore before applying for admission to the construction management degree program. In addition, all seniors must take a program exit examination along with the American Institute of Constructors’ Level I examination before graduation.

First Semester Hours

CNST 131 Intro to the Construction Industry 1

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument 3

GEOL 101 Physical Geology 4

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Total 16

Second Semester Hours

CNST 112 Construction Communications 3

JGEN 200 Technical Communications I 3

STAT 218 Intro to Statistics 3

PHYS 151 Elements of Physics 4

PHYS 153 Elements of Physics Lab 1

Total 14

Third Semester Hours

CIVE 221 Geometric Control Systems 3

CNST 241 Construction Methods & Equipment I 3

CNST 252 Construction Materials & Testing 3

ECON 200 Economic Essentials & Issues 3

ENGM 220 Statics 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

Total 15

Fourth Semester Hours

ACCT 200 Accounting for Business Decisions 3

CNST 242 Construction Equipment & Methods II 3

CNST 251 Construction Materials & Specifications 3

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication 3

ENGM 324 Strength of Materials 3

Total 15

Fifth Semester Hours

ARCH 331 Architectural Structures I 3

BLAW 300 Business, Government & Society 3

CNST 305 Building Environmental Technical Systems I (ARCH 333) 3

CNST 378 Construction Estimating I 3

MNGT 300 Management Essentials for Contemporary Organizations 3

Total 15

Sixth Semester Hours

ARCH 332 Architectural Structures II 3

CNST 306 Physical Environmental Systems II 3

CNST 379 Construction Estimating II 3

FINA 300 Financial Decision Making 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Total 15

Seventh Semester Hours

MRKT 300 Contemporary Marketing 3

CNST 476 Project Budgets & Controls 3

CNST 480 Productivity & Human Factors in Construction 3

CNST 485 Construction Planning, Scheduling, & Controls 3

Technical Elective 3

Total 15

Eighth Semester Hours

CNST 420 Professional Practice & Ethics 3

CNST 489 Senior Construction Project 3

Construction Management Elective 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Technical Elective 3

Total 15

Total Credit Hours Required 120

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

This minor is for engineering majors ONLY.

The College of Engineering enables its students to participate in this approved minor subject to the following conditions:

1. A minor will not reduce or alter the existing course or degree requirements for students electing to pursue a minor.

2. A student’s minor program must be organized and approved by an adviser prior to the submission of the senior check to the department chair or head.

3. The minor must be approved by the adviser, the department chair or head, the Dean and the cognizant program offering the minor.

4. The College of Engineering will follow the “Plan A/B” format of the Arts and Sciences College in which a student pursuing a single minor must complete the “Plan A” requirements. A student pursuing a double (or greater) minor must fulfill either the “Plan A” or “Plan B” requirements for both minors depending on which plan is offered by the cognizant department.

5. Minors on the Lincoln or Omaha campuses may be added by approval of the College of Engineering Curriculum Committee and faculty.

Course Requirements

Plan A only. All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Hours

Required Courses 27

BLAW 300 Business, Government & Society 3

CNST 112 Construction Communications 3

CNST 241 Construction Methods & Equipment I 3

CNST 305 Building Environmental Technical Systems I 3

CNST 378 Construction Estimating I 3

CNST 379 Construction Estimating II 3

CNST 480 Productivity & Human Factors in Construction 3

CNST 485 Construction Planning, Scheduling & Controls 3

MNGT 300 Management Essentials for Contemporary Organizations 3

Criminology & Criminal Justice

COLLEGE: Public Affairs and Community Service

MAJOR: Criminology and Criminal Justice

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Criminology and Criminal Justice

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 to transfer to major; 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Karen Fulton

DESCRIPTION

Director: Dr. Candice Batton

Assistant Director for Academic and Student Affairs: Karen Fulton, 310 Nebraska Hall, 402-472-3677

Faculty: Anderson, Batton, Brauer, Brennan, Clinkinbeard, Crank, Eskridge, Hobbs, Hoffman, Hughes, Jacobs (emeriti), Kadleck, Marshall, Meier, Ogle, Sample, Savolainen, Simi, Spohn, Steiner, Wakefield, Walker (emeriti), Wright

The School of Criminology and Criminal Justice provides its students with the foundation for entering many diversified criminal justice related careers including the courts, law, corrections and law enforcement. The school curriculum is composed of a broad range of ideas and interests, including courses in organization and administration, statistics, research methods, law enforcement, corrections, criminology, courts, juvenile delinquency, and law, as well as various special topics. Through the internship program, students can obtain work experience within various criminal justice agencies.

Although the bachelor of science in criminology and criminal justice degree can be earned in its entirety on the Lincoln campus, the degree is granted by the University of Nebraska at Omaha.

Degree at a Glance

Requirements for the Bachelor of Science in Criminology and Criminal Justice (120 Hours)

Hours

Core Requirements 48

English Composition 9

Social Science 12

Natural Science and Math 12

Humanities and Fine Arts 12

Statistics 3

Major Requirements 39

Concentration 18

Electives 15

TOTAL 120

ADMISSION

Major/College Admission

Students who have been admitted to the University may apply for entrance to the College of Public Affairs and Community Service as a Pre-Criminology and Criminal Justice major during initial registration by indicating their preference in the appropriate place on the University Application for Admission form.

Students who wish to transfer into the College from one of the schools or colleges within the University or from another institution must have a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5.

Other Admission Requirements

Pre-Criminology and Criminal Justice (PCCJ)

The first 45 hours of course work is defined as the PCCJ curriculum. Entering freshmen who declare PCCJ as their major must complete all of the 45 hour PCCJ curriculum with a minimum grade of C- in their criminology and criminal justice courses. These courses must include:

CRIM 101 (3 hrs)

CRIM 251 (3 hrs)

CRIM 203, CRIM 211 or CRIM 221 (6-9 hrs)

ENGL 101, ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 250, ENGL 252, ENGL 254, ENGL 258 (6 hrs)

MATH 100A, MATH 101, MATH 103, MATH 104 or MATH 106 (3-5 hrs)

Students are encouraged to fulfill the remaining 19-24 hours with course work from their general distribution requirements.

Upper Division Criminology and Criminal Justice (CRCJ)

Students seeking entrance into the upper division criminology and criminal justice program (CRCJ) must apply to the School of Criminology and Criminal Justice. Students may apply with fewer than 45 hours if they are enrolled for the remaining hours during the semester in which they make application. In such cases, students may be granted admission contingent upon completion of the hours with a minimum grade of C- in their criminology and criminal justice courses.

Transfer Students Declaring Pre-Criminology and Criminal Justice

Students wishing to transfer from another institution or department within the University of Nebraska must have a 2.5 cumulative grade point average to declare pre-criminology and criminal justice. Transfer students must complete the PCCJ curriculum stipulated above and apply for admission to the School of Criminology and Criminal Justice before being admitted to the upper division CRCJ program. Students wishing to transfer are encouraged to contact the school for more details on the transfer policy.

The policies set out above are intended to apply to all students who seek admission to the upper division CRCJ program. For good cause shown, the school has the discretion to make exceptions to the admission policy.

Application forms may be obtained at the School of Criminology and Criminal Justice office.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Bachelor of Science in Criminology and Criminal Justice (BSCCJ)

Core Requirements

A. English Composition (9 hours). Select 3-6 hours from: ENGL 101, ENGL 150, ENGL 151 (fulfills ACE 1 requirement). At least 3 credit hours must be in courses 200 level or higher selected from: ENGL 250, ENGL 252, ENGL 254, ENGL 258, or ENGL 354. Acceptable alternatives must be approved by the student’s adviser.

B. Social Science (12 hours). Courses will be selected from the departments of economics, gerontology, history, political science, psychology, educational psychology (EDPS 450, EDPS 451, EDPS 463), sociology, social work, anthropology, nonphysical geography, and child, youth and family studies (CYAF 160, CYAF 270, CYAF 271, CYAF 280) (see adviser for upper-level options). No more than 6 hours from any one department may be used to meet this requirement.

C. Natural Sciences and Mathematics (12 hours). Select one math course from MATH 100A, MATH 101, MATH 103, MATH 104 or MATH 106 and one natural science with lab course from ACE 4. Select additional courses from the following disciplines: astronomy, biological sciences, chemistry, computer science CSCE 101 or higher (CSCE labs do not fulfill the lab requirement), entomology, forensic science (FORS 120, FORS 300, FORS 414, FORS 445, FORS 446, FORS 407), geology, math (above 101), meteorology, nutrition (NUTR 131), and physical geography (GEOG 155).

D. Humanities and Fine Arts (12 hours). Select one 3-hour course from ACE 5 and one 3-hour course from ACE 7. An additional course may be selected from art and art history, classics, communication, dance, English literature, foreign languages, journalism, music, philosophy, religion, or theatre. Not more than 8 hours may be applied from any one department. Each student must also complete one 3-hour course in oral communication to be selected from: COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 286 (fulfills ACE 2 requirement).

E. Statistics (3 hours). Each student must complete one 3-hour course in basic statistics selected from CRIM 300 (recommended), EDPS 459, ECON 215, SOCI 206 or STAT 218 (fulfills ACE 3 requirement). Only one of these basic statistics courses may apply to the degree.

NOTE: CRIM 300 will not apply toward the 39 hours of required CRCJ courses.

Specific Major Requirements

Criminology and Criminal Justice Requirements (39 semester hours)

All candidates for the BSCCJ degree must complete CRIM 101 Survey of Criminal Justice (fulfills ACE 6 requirement), CRIM 251 Research Methods, and select 6-9 hours from CRIM 203 Police and Society, CRIM 211 Criminal Court System, and CRIM 221 Survey of Corrections. After admission to the Upper Division Program students must complete a minimum of 21 hours of upper division CRCJ courses including CRIM 335 Criminology and CRIM 351 Criminal Procedure.

A minimum grade of C- is required in criminology and criminal justice courses used as part of the 39-hour major requirement.

Students are not required to complete an internship (CRIM 397), however, up to 6 hours of internship may be included in the program of study. Participation in the internship requires admission to the upper-division CRCJ program, 75 earned hours and a GPA of 2.5.

Students must register for and complete CRIM 499 (Senior Assessment) in the semester in which they plan to graduate.

NOTE: Credit toward the degree may be earned in only one of the following: CRIM 251 or SOCI 205, CRIM 337 or SOCI 311, CRIM 413 or SOCI 474.

Concentration Requirement

Area of Concentration (18 hours)

Students will select an area of concentration with their advisers. At least 12 hours must be completed in upper division courses (300/400 level). Students who wish to integrate a minor into their program should work closely with their CRCJ adviser.

Electives

Elective Requirements (15 semester hours)

Students may select electives after consultation with their adviser. Elective courses may include non-required criminology and criminal justice courses.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Ethical Principles, Civics and Stewardship

Each student must select one 3-hour course from ACE 8 which explains ethical principles, civics, and stewardship and their importance to society. This course may be applied toward the appropriate group requirement.

Global Awareness/Diversity

Each student must select one 3-hour course from ACE 9 which exhibits global awareness or knowledge of human diversity through analysis of an issue. This course may be applied toward the appropriate group requirement.

Creative or Scholarly Product

Each student must select one 3-hour course from ACE 10. This will typically be completed with a course in the major area.

Other Requirements/Rules

The BSCCJ degree requires the completion of 120 semester hours of credit. A minimum of 30 of the last 36 credit hours must be earned by the student in residence within the University of Nebraska system. Summer independent study courses are not considered in residence.
At least 21 hours of criminology and criminal justice must be taken at the University of Nebraska.
A maximum of 30 hours from any one department may be applied toward the BSCCJ degree.
A maximum of 6 credit hours for basic military training is applicable to the BSCCJ degree.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

A minimum grade of C- is required in criminology and criminal justice courses used as part of the 39-hour major requirement.

Pass/No Pass Limits

A maximum of 24 hours may be taken Pass/No Pass and none of the 39 hours required for the criminology and criminal justice major may be taken Pass/No Pass (excluding CRIM 397 Internship).

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules

A maximum of 25 credit hours from nontraditional or non classroom courses (correspondence, independent study, internet mediated) may be applied toward the BSCCJ degree.

A maximum of 12 credit hours of departmental independent study or internship courses may be applied toward the BSCCJ degree. Of these, no more than 6 hours from one department and no more than 6 hours from another institution.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Criminology and Criminal Justice Minor

Hours

Requirements for Minor (minimum) 18

CRIM 101 Survey of Criminal Justice 3

Select two courses from: 6

CRIM 203 Police & Society (3 cr)

CRIM 211 The Criminal Court System (3 cr)

CRIM 221 Survey of Corrections (3 cr)

Select three upper level (300/400) CRCJ courses (excluding CRIM 300 Applied Statistics) 9

An overall C average in courses applied to the minor is required and all courses must be taken for a letter grade (not Pass/No Pass). In addition, all 9 credit hours of upper division CRCJ course work must be taken in residence at the University of Nebraska.

OTHER

Other College Requirements

Total Hours

Each candidate must present a total of at least 120 semester hours of college credit to meet graduation requirements.

Quality of Work

Each candidate for the degree must attain a cumulative grade point average of at least 2.0. A minimum grade of at least C- must be earned in all required courses within the major, unless a higher grade is designated by the department/school. All grades reported by the faculty to the registrar become a part of the student’s permanent record and are included in the computation of the grade point average, even though some of these grades may be for work done in excess of the 120 hours required for graduation.

Transfer of Courses

The transfer of D grades in non-major courses are accepted only from within the University of Nebraska system. Students from other institutions must present a grade of C- or above for all course work.

Residence

Thirty of the last 36 hours required for the degree must be registered for and carried within the University of Nebraska system.

Acceptability of credits

The student should refer all questions concerning the acceptability of credits earned in programs such as Cooperative Education and Credit by Examination to the department in which enrolled. Credit earned in courses below the 100 level may not be applied toward the degree offered by the College of Public Affairs and Community Service.

Achievement-Centered Education (ACE)

All criminology and criminal justice students who are following the 2011-2012 Undergraduate Bulletin must fulfill the Achievement-Centered Education (ACE) requirements. The 30-hour ACE requirement will include a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement-Centered Education (ACE student learning outcome areas which can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of courses they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes.

Courses required for the BSCCJ degree will also fulfill ACE requirements. Students should carefully review course work with ACE options to make the best use of courses to fulfill both degree requirements as well as their ACE requirements.

Prerequisite Courses

Completion of a course within the major with a grade below a C- will not be considered as having fulfilled prerequisite requirements for additional courses taken in the major field of study. A higher grade may be designated by the department/school.

Choice of Catalog Policy

A student registering in the College of Public Affairs and Community Service for the first time may, except for limitations described below, complete work for the degree according to the requirements of 1) the catalog in effect the year the student enters CPACS or 2) the catalog current at the time the student applies for the degree.

Students entering the College for the first time in the summer will be subject to the catalog for the academic year immediately following.

Students formerly in a CPACS program who drop out of the College for one year must complete requirements of the catalog current at the time of readmission.

Failure to complete the requirements for the degree within seven years after the date the student first enters the College will subject the student to graduation under the requirements of a later catalog to be approved by the Dean.

The College reserves the right to institute and make effective, after due notice, during the course of a student’s work toward a degree, any new ruling which may be necessary for the general good of the College and to substitute courses currently offered for those no longer offered.

Grade Appeals Procedure

Students who wish to appeal a grade which they feel was capriciously or prejudicially given shall first discuss the matter with the instructor within 30 days of the final course grade being posted. If the matter is not resolved, the student must meet with the department/school chairperson. If a satisfactory agreement cannot be reached, the student must appeal, in writing, to the department/school curriculum committee. If a satisfactory agreement cannot be reached, the student may submit a written appeal to the Office of the Dean within 20 working days of the exhaustion of the departmental procedures.

The Committee on Academic Standards and Curriculum for the College of Public Affairs and Community Service is the official body for handling the appeal.

In the event that the instructor is unavailable for handling a grade complaint, the student will meet with the school director and the dean to determine the most appropriate course of action agreeable to all parties.

Copies of the CPACS Procedures for Student Grades and Suspension Appeals are available from the chair of the Committee on Academic Standards and Curriculum for the College and the Office of the Dean.

Degree Audit and Application for Degree

During the second semester of their junior year, or after completing approximately 89 hours, students should apply for an audit of their academic records to be sure that all requirements will be met before the anticipated date of graduation. Criminology and criminal justice majors may request the audit at the CPACS Office, 310 Nebraska Hall.

Criminology and criminal justice majors must also file an application for graduation at Graduation Services either just prior to or early in the semester they intend to graduate. Failure to meet the published deadline may delay graduation until the next semester.

Culinary Science

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Nutrition & Health Sciences

PROGRAM: Culinary Science

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

The Culinary Science (Culinology®) option is the emerging discipline of the culinary arts, nutrition and the science of food. Culinology® is becoming a recognized and valued discipline that will significantly impact food research and development in the global market. Culinologists are skilled chefs who are creating a new generation of exciting, high-quality food products. The food industry needs, and rewards, people who understand and can apply the principles of this specialty.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 31

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. ECON 211 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. ECON 212 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 (Professional Requirement) 3

ACE 10. FDST 460 (Professional Requirement) 3

Culinary Arts Concentration 22

(Select any culinary arts electives from an accredited Institution)

Professional Requirements 32

HRTM 173 and NUTR 245 1 hr ea 2

NUTR 244, NUTR 250, NUTR 344, (NUTR 372 or BIOS 312) and NUTR 449 15

NUTR 441 &/or NUTR 445 &/or FDST 448 (3 hrs ea – select two) 6

FDST 205, FDST 403 and FDST 430 (3 hrs ea) 9

Supporting Courses 17-20

MATH 101 or higher 3-5

MRKT 341 3

BIOC 321 3

CHEM 110 4

CHEM 251 (3 hrs) & CHEM 253 (1 hr) 4

Processing Electives 6

Select any two courses from the following: (ASCI 210, ASCI 213, ASCI 310, ASCI 410) or (FDST 363, FDST 405, FDST 412, FDST 420, FDST 429, FDST 455) or NUTR 343

Electives 9-12

Total Hours 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Area of Concentration

Culinary Arts electives from an accredited Culinary Arts Institution

Professional Requirements

Nutrition and Health Sciences

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

HRTM 173 Field Experience in Culinology®

NUTR 244 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation

NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation Lab

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

NUTR 344 Food & Nutrition for Healthy Living

NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation or BIOS 312 Microbiology

NUTR 441 Functional Properties of Food &/or FDST 448 Food Chemistry &/or NUTR 445 Experimental Foods

NUTR 449 Culinology® Research Experience

Food Science and Technology

FDST 205 Food Composition & Analysis

FDST 403 Food Quality Assurance

FDST 430 Sensory Evaluation

FDST 460 Food Product Development Concepts

Supporting Sciences

BIOC 321 Elements of Biochemistry

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab

Supporting Courses

ECON 211 & ECON 212 Principles of Macroeconomics & Microeconomics

MATH 101 College Algebra

If a student does not place into MATH 101, they must complete the appropriate course(s) plus complete MATH 101. If a student places above MATH 101, the student will take either MATH 101 or the MATH course they placed into.

MRKT 341 Marketing

STAT 218 Intro to Statistics

Processing Electives

Select two courses from:

ASCI 210 Animal Products

ASCI 213 Meat Specifications & Procurement

ASCI 310 Fresh Meats

ASCI 410 Processed Meats

FDST 363 Heat & Mass Transfer

FDST 405 Food Microbiology

FDST 412 Cereal Technology

FDST 420 Fruit & Vegetable Technology

FDST 429 Dairy Products Technology

FDST 455 Microbiology of Fermented Foods

NUTR 343 Meat Culinology® III: Foodservice Applications (Grade of C or better required in NUTR 343)

Electives

OTHER

Meat Culinology® Certificate Program

The Meat Culinology® Certificate program at UNL concentrates on meat because it is the center of most meals and is the major portion of the food budget in the food service industry. Proper handling and preparation is paramount to the success of a meal and a food establishment. The faculty at UNL who developed this program know that food industry professionals are busy. With little time to take courses on campus, the online Meat Culinology® Certificate program allows professionals the opportunity to advance their education and career by learning more about the science and art of meat. The six-course sequence will teach you everything from harvest to consumption of livestock and poultry. The Meat Culinology® Certificate program consists of six courses. Students must successfully complete all six courses in order to earn certification. Successful completion is considered an earned grade of ‘C’ or higher.

Meat Culinology® Certificate Program

ASCI 210 Animal Products

ASCI 213/NUTR 213 Meat Specification & Procurement

ASCI 310 Fresh Meats

NUTR 343/ASCI 343 Meat Culinology® III: Foodservice Applications

ASCI 410 Processed Meats

ASCI 411 HACCP & Food Safety Systems for the Food Industry

Dietetics

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Nutrition & Health Sciences

PROGRAM: Dietetics (Didactic Program in Dietetics)

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

The Dietetics (Didactic Program in Dietetics) option is designed for students who wish to become registered dietitians and practitioners in clinical, community, food industry, and foodservice areas of nutrition and may be employed by hospitals, community agencies, and various government or private organizations. The University of Nebraska–Lincoln Didactic Program in Dietetics is currently granted accreditation status by the Accreditation Council for Education in Nutrition and Dietetics of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics, 120 South Riverside Plaza, Suite 2000, Chicago, IL 60606-6995.

The process to become a registered dietitian involves three steps: completion of a bachelors degree with attainment of the Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics; admission into and the completion of an accredited dietetic internship program; and successfully passing the registration exam to earn the Registered Dietitian (RD) credential.

Meeting requirements for the bachelors degree Dietetics option does not automatically result in the student being awarded a Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics. Requirements for attainment of the Verification Statement are listed on the dietetics program website. The Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics is required for admission into an accredited dietetic internship program.

Acceptance into an accredited dietetic internship program is competitive. Currently, there is a significant shortage of available internship positions for the number of students applying for acceptance into an internship program. Acceptance into an internship program cannot be guaranteed.

All required accreditation information and requirements for attainment of the Verification Statement can be found at http://cehs.unl.edu/nhs/undergrad/dietetics.shtml.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 33

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 (Professional Requirement) 3

ACE 10. NUTR 452 & NUTR 452L (Professional Requirement) 4

Professional Requirements (A grade of C or above is required) 40

NUTR 100, NUTR 244, NUTR 250, NUTR 251, NUTR 344, NUTR 356, NUTR 370, NUTR 402, NUTR 450, NUTR 453, NUTR 455, NUTR 473 (3 hrs ea) 36

NUTR 150, NUTR 245, NUTR 371, NUTR 490 (1 hr ea) 4

Supporting Courses 25-29

MATH 101 or higher 2-5

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L 4

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L or BIOS 102 or BIOS 103 & BIOS 103L 4

BIOS 111 (4 hrs) or BIOS 312 (3 hrs) & BIOS 314 (1 hr) or NUTR 372 (3 hrs) 3-4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L 4

CHEM 110 4

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 4

Electives 18-22

Total Hours 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

* These (*) courses, required in your major, will also meet ACE Requirements.

Professional Requirements

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health

NUTR 150 Foundations in Nutrition & Health Promotion

NUTR 244 & NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation & Lab

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

NUTR 251 Nutrition Through the Life Cycle

*NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

NUTR 344 Food & Nutrition for Healthy Living

NUTR 356 Nutrition Education in the Community

NUTR 370 Food Production Management

NUTR 371 Applied Food Production Lab

NUTR 402 Facts & Fiction in Fitness & Food

NUTR 450 Medical Nutrition Therapy I

*NUTR 452 Medical Nutrition Therapy II

*NUTR 452L Medical Nutrition Therapy II Lab

NUTR 453 Nutrition & Fitness Communication Strategies

NUTR 455 Advanced Nutrition

NUTR 473 Organization & Administration of Foodservice

NUTR 490 Professional Preparation for Careers in Dietetics

Supporting Courses

*EDPS 459 Statistical Methods or *STAT 218 Intro to Statistics

*PSYC 181 Intro to Psychology

MATH 101 College Algebra or higher, trigonometry or calculus

*BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab or *BIOS 102 Cell Structure & Function or *BIOS 103 & BIOS 103L Organismic Biology

BIOS 111 The Biology of Microoganisms or BIOS 312 & BIOS 314 Microbiology & Lab or NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation (3-4 hrs)

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grades Earned at UNL, UNO, UNK

Grades of D-, D, D+, C- satisfy requirements of the programs in human sciences unless specified otherwise under the Programs and Departments section of the bulletin. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, or C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course, particularly if it is in the major area.

Grades Earned Outside UN System

Up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Policy for Pass/No Pass Courses

The Pass/No Pass (P/N) option is designed for students who want to study elective areas or topics when they may have minimum preparation. If used for this purpose, the option can enrich the student’s academic experience without lowering the student’s grade point average. Free electives may be taken P/N. Students can earn no more than 12 hours of pass credit excluding courses offered on Pass/No Pass only basis. Not all classes can be taken under the Pass/No Pass option. All courses, specified by course and number, must be taken for a grade. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed by the appropriate department.

Economics (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Economics

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Roger Butters

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Scott M. Fuess, Jr., 340 College of Business Administration Building

Professors: Allgood, Anderson, Cushing, Edwards, Fuess, Hayden, MacPhee, May, Rosenbaum, Schmidt, van den Berg, Walstad

Associate Professors: Kim, McGarvey, Thompson

Assistant Professors: Butters, Giertz

Assistant Professor of Practice: Asarta

Economic analysis is useful in many decisions made by individuals, businesses, nonprofit organizations, and governments. In addition to opportunities in teaching, economists are employed in many branches of government and on the staffs of corporations in manufacturing, insurance, banking, brokerage and other financial services. Economists often serve as consultants, either individually or in consulting firms. Today’s economists deal with problems ranging from monetary and fiscal policy, monopoly and competition, environmental improvement, labor relations, regional development, urban reconstruction, economic development and international business and finance. Economics is also a popular major for students planning to enter professional and graduate programs, particularly in law, foreign service, labor relations, or business administration.

The department of economics offers the opportunity for intensive study in twelve specialized economic areas:

General Economics and Theory. Develops fundamental reasoning skills and analytical tools necessary to understand and evaluate economic issues such as specialization, trade, efficiency, costs, markets, prices, resource allocation, money, labor, and government and think critically about economic theory and social provisioning.

Comparative International and Regional Development. Examines how human capital, fiscal policy, natural features, and industry clusters influence the comparative advantage, growth, and standard of living in urban and regional economies between and within countries.

Econometrics.

Economic Education.

Economic History. Examines the transformation in economic life that accompanied the rise of market capitalism in the United States and focus on the impact of this transformation on the environment, society, and individuals. Courses in this area are integrative in nature and allow students the opportunity to examine the complex nature of economic development throughout American history.

Industrial Organization and Regulation.

Institutional Economics.

International Trade and Finance. Examines the causes and effects of imports, exports, foreign investment, and migration and their implications for exchange rates, the balance of payments, and economic welfare.

Labor Economics. Focuses on how labor markets function and thus, how wages and employment are determined. The decisions of labor market participants are studied, as are employment practices and public policies related to employment issues.

Monetary Economics. Studies the role of money and banking system, and of Federal Reserve’s monetary policy in the determination of output, employment, interest rates, prices and business cycles in the domestic and open-economy context.

Public Finance. Survey of taxation and public expenditures in theory and practice. Understanding the logic of collective action, the theory of public goods, social welfare, redistribution and intergovernmental fiscal relations.

Quantitative Economics.

For some careers, study in related areas is advisable. If you’re interested in:

Human Resource Management – take additional courses in labor economics and economic history
Finance – courses in money and banking, intermediate microeconomics, and macroeconomics are helpful
Marketing – econometrics courses add to your resume
Accounting – econometrics and public finance courses covering taxes are useful

In planning a program of studies, students should consult a faculty adviser or talk to any member of the economics faculty who would be glad to make suggestions about complementary courses.

Many economics courses also satisfy ACE requirements, (see Other.)

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

An economics major must complete 30 credit hours of economics. These 30 hours must include:

Hours

ECON 211 Principles of Macroeconomics 3

ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics 3

ECON 215 Statistics* 3

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics 3

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics 3

Economics 300- or 400-level courses 6

Economics 400-level courses 9

Total 30

*NOTE for economics majors: STAT 218 may be substituted for ECON 215 if STAT 218 was completed before declaring economics as a major; otherwise student must take ECON 215.

Track/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, students majoring in economics may choose to pursue areas of interest in the following disciplines to fulfill requirements for the major. Course options appear under each area.

General Economics and Theory

ECON 389 Current Economic Issues

ECON 413 Social Insurance

ECON 433 History of Economic Thought

ECON 445 Gender, Economics, & Social Provisioning

Comparative International and Regional Development

ECON 322 Intro to Development Economics

ECON 323 The Economic Development of Latin America

ECON 340 Intro to Urban-Regional Economics

ECON 388 Comparative Economic Systems

ECON 423 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

ECON 440 Regional Development

ECON 442 Regional Analysis

ECON 466 Pro-seminar in International Relations I

ECON 467 Pro-seminar in International Relations II

ECON 487 Economies in Transition

Econometrics

ECON 417 Introductory Econometrics

Economic Education

(Also see courses in Quantitative Economics)

ECON 450 Economics for Teachers

ECON 451 Economics Issues for Teachers

Economic History

ECON 375 Women & Work in United States History

ECON 457 19th Century United States Economic History

ECON 458 20th Century United States Economic History

Industrial Organization and Regulation

ECON 426 Government Intervention in Markets

ECON 435 Market Competition

Also see the following economics courses:

ECON 457/857 19th Century U.S. Economic History

ECON 458/858 20th Century U.S. Economic History

ECON 472/872 Efficiency in Government

ECON 487/887 Economies in Transition

ECON 900 Seminar in Economic Theory & Policy

Institutional Economics

ECON 475 Theory & Analysis of Institutional Economics

International Trade and Finance

ECON 321 Intro to International Economics

NOTE: ECON 321 is also an ACE 9 course option and can be taken to fulfill the NBR 6–ACE 9 requirement as well as a course for the major (AND it is also an IBCR).

ECON 421 International Trade

ECON 422 International Finance

For additional courses, see Comparative International & Regional Development

Labor Economics

ECON 381 Intro to Labor Economics

ECON 481 Economics of the Labor Market

ECON 482 Labor in the National Economy

ECON 485 Government & Labor

Monetary Economics

ECON 303 An Intro to Money & Banking

ECON 365 Financial Institutions & Markets

ECON 403 Money & the Financial System

ECON 404 Current Issues in Monetary Economics

Public Finance

ECON 371 Elements of Public Finance

ECON 471 Public Finance

ECON 472 Efficiency in Government

Quantitative Economics

ECON 409 Applied Public Policy Analysis

ECON 416 Statistics for Decision Making

ECON 419 Topics in Applied Research

Also see Econometrics area for additional courses in quantitative economics.

Research and Thesis

Seminar and research courses in specific fields are listed in their respective divisions.

ECON 189H University Honors Seminar

ECON 198 Freshman Seminar

ECON 399 Independent Study

ECON 399H Honors: Independent Study

ECON 499H Honors Thesis

This department participates in the program for International Studies. For a full description of the program, see “International Studies.”

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details of these programs see the Graduate Studies Bulletin. Refer to the Graduate Studies Bulletin for 800/900-level courses.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Students are required to complete ECON 211, ECON 212, and ECON 215 before completing additional required economics course work. The completion of BSAD 150 and MATH 104 are required prior to enrollment in ECON 215. We strongly recommend students complete the intermediate theory sequence, ECON 311 and ECON 312, prior to completing elective 300 and 400 level classes.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

All courses for the major, with the exception of ECON 399, must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass). If ECON 399 is taken as Pass/No Pass, it may only be used as an elective.

Course Level Requirement

Completion of ECON 311 and ECON 312 is recommended before taking other 300/400-level economics courses.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A: 18 hours

Plan B: 12 hours

OTHER

All students are required to meet the prerequisites listed for each course, including any specific grade or GPA requirement, to include all requirements for enrollment in 300- or 400-level economics courses.

ECON 211 and ECON 212 Macro- and Microeconomics are ACE 6 and ACE 8 approved course work.

ECON 215 Statistics is an approved ACE 3 course and may be used to fulfill the ACE 3 requirement of the University.

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics is an approved ACE 9 course and while most students will complete ACE 9 during the freshman and sophomore year with other course work, transfer and upper-class students meeting the prerequisite, may wish to take this class.

Economics (CBA)

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Economics (CBA)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (21 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Roger Butters

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Scott M. Fuess, Jr., 340 CBA

Professors: Allgood, Anderson, Cushing, Edwards, Fuess, Hayden, MacPhee, May, Rosenbaum, Schmidt, van den Berg, Walstad

Associate Professors: Kim, McGarvey, Thompson

Assistant Professors: Butters, Giertz

Associate Professor of Practice: Asarta

Assistant Professor of Practice: Miller

Economic analysis is useful in many decisions made by individuals, businesses, nonprofit organizations, and governments. In addition to opportunities in teaching, economists are employed in many branches of government and on the staffs of corporations in manufacturing, insurance, banking, brokerage, and financial services. Economists often serve as consultants, either individually or in consulting firms. Today’s economists deal with problems ranging from monetary and fiscal policy, monopoly and competition, environmental improvement, labor relations, regional development, urban reconstruction, economic development and international business and finance. Economics is also a popular major for students planning to enter professional and graduate programs, particularly in law, foreign service, labor relations, or business administration.

The Department of Economics offers the opportunity for intensive study in twelve specialized economic areas:

General Economics and Theory. Develops fundamental reasoning skills and analytical tools necessary to understand and evaluate economic issues such as specialization, trade, efficiency, costs, markets, prices, resource allocation, money, labor, and government and think critically about economic theory and social provisioning.

Comparative International and Regional Development. Examines how human capital, fiscal policy, natural features, and industry clusters influence the comparative advantage, growth, and standard of living in urban and regional economies between and within countries.

Econometrics.

Economic Education.

Economic History. Examines the transformation in economic life that accompanied the rise of market capitalism in the United States and focus on the impact of this transformation on the environment, society, and individuals. Courses in this area are integrative in nature and allow students the opportunity to examine the complex nature of economic development throughout American history.

Industrial Organization and Regulation.

Institutional Economics.

International Trade and Finance. Examines the causes and effects of imports, exports, foreign investment, and migration and their implications for exchange rates, the balance of payments, and economic welfare.

Labor Economics. Focuses on how labor markets function and thus, how wages and employment are determined. The decisions of labor market participants are studied, as are employment practices and public policies related to employment issues.

Monetary Economics. Studies the role of money and banking system, and of Federal Reserve’s monetary policy in the determination of output, employment, interest rates, prices and business cycles in the domestic and open-economy context.

Public Finance. Survey of taxation and public expenditures in theory and practice. Understanding the logic of collective action, the theory of public goods, social welfare, redistribution and intergovernmental fiscal relations.

Quantitative Economics.

For some careers, study in related areas is advisable. If you’re interested in:

Human Resource Management – take additional courses in labor economics and economic history
Finance – courses in money and banking, intermediate microeconomics, and macroeconomics are helpful
Marketing – econometrics courses add to your resume
Accounting – econometrics and public finance courses covering taxes are useful

In planning a program of studies, students should consult a faculty adviser or talk to any member of the economics faculty who would be glad to make suggestions about complementary courses.

Many economics courses also satisfy ACE requirements (see Other).

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 21 hours of course work for the major.
All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take MATH 104 or equivalent, ECON 211, ECON 212, and ECON 215 as part of the Business Core Foundation requirements.
NONE of these courses may be used to count toward the major, and cannot be taken Pass/No Pass.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

In addition to the 9 general credit-hours of the Business Core Foundation Course requirements (ECON 211, ECON 212 and ECON 215), an economics major must complete 21 credit hours of economics.
All courses for the major, with the exception of ECON 399, must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass). If ECON 399 is taken as Pass/No Pass, it may only be used as an elective.
Completion of ECON 311 and ECON 312 is recommended before enrolling in additional 300/400-level economics course work.

The requirements for the major include:

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics (3 hrs)

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics (3 hrs)

Economics 300- or 400-level course (6 hrs)

Economics 400-level courses (9 hrs)

Total (21 hrs)

Faculty approval required on proposed program of course work.

Recommended Order of Studies

Students must first complete all Core courses including MATH 104, ECON 211, ECON 212 and ECON 215. We strongly recommend students complete the intermediate theory sequence, ECON 311 and ECON 312, prior to completing elective 300- and 400-level classes.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, students majoring in economics may choose to pursue areas of interest in the following disciplines to fulfill requirements for the major. Course options appear under each area.

General Economics and Theory

ECON 389 Current Economic Issues

ECON 413 Social Insurance

ECON 433 History of Economic Thought

ECON 445 Gender, Economics, & Social Provisioning

Comparative International and Regional Development

ECON 322 Intro to Development Economics

ECON 323 The Economic Development of Latin America

ECON 340 Intro to Urban-Regional Economics

ECON 388 Comparative Economic Systems

ECON 423 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

ECON 440 Regional Development

ECON 442 Regional Analysis

ECON 466 Pro-seminar in International Relations I

ECON 467 Pro-seminar in International Relations II

ECON 487 Economies in Transition

Econometrics

ECON 417 Introductory Econometrics

Economic Education

(Also see courses in Quantitative Economics)

ECON 450 Economics for Teachers

ECON 451 Economics Issues for Teachers

Economic History

ECON 375 Women & Work in United States History

ECON 457 19th Century United States Economic History

ECON 458 20th Century United States Economic History

Industrial Organization and Regulation

ECON 426 Government Intervention in Markets

ECON 435 Market Competition

Also see the following economics courses:

ECON 457/857 19th Century U.S. Economic History

ECON 458/858 20th Century U.S. Economic History

ECON 472/872 Efficiency in Government

ECON 487/887 Economies in Transition

ECON 900 Seminar in Economic Theory & Policy

Institutional Economics

ECON 475 Theory & Analysis of Institutional Economics

International Trade and Finance

ECON 321 Intro to International Economics

NOTE: ECON 321 is also an ACE 9 course option and can be taken to fulfill the NBR 6–ACE 9 requirement as well as a course for the major (AND it is also an IBCR).

ECON 421 International Trade

ECON 422 International Finance

For additional courses, see Comparative International & Regional Development

Labor Economics

ECON 381 Intro to Labor Economics

ECON 481 Economics of the Labor Market

ECON 482 Labor in the National Economy

ECON 485 Government & Labor

Monetary Economics

ECON 303 An Intro to Money & Banking

ECON 365 Financial Institutions & Markets

ECON 403 Money & the Financial System

ECON 404 Current Issues in Monetary Economics

Public Finance

ECON 371 Elements of Public Finance

ECON 471 Public Finance

ECON 472 Efficiency in Government

Quantitative Economics

ECON 409 Applied Public Policy Analysis

ECON 416 Statistics for Decision Making

ECON 419 Topics in Applied Research

Also see Econometrics area for additional courses in quantitative economics.

Research and Thesis

Seminar and research courses in specific fields are listed in their respective divisions.

ECON 189H University Honors Seminar

ECON 198 Freshman Seminar

ECON 399 Independent Study

ECON 399H Honors: Independent Study

ECON 499H Honors Thesis

This department participates in the program for Global Studies. For a full description of the program, see “Global Studies.”

Graduate Work

The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details of these programs see the Graduate Studies Bulletin. Refer to the Graduate Studies Bulletin for 800/900 level courses.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

All courses for the major, with the exception of ECON 399, must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass). If ECON 399 is taken as Pass/No Pass, it may only be used as an elective.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

Course Level Requirement

Completion of ECON 311 and ECON 312 is recommended before taking other 300/400-level economics courses.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Economics Minor Requirements

The economics minor offered through CBA is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college expects that 50% of the course work for the minor will be completed at UNL.
Economics course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation (BCF), intermediate (BCI), or advanced-major (BCA-M; BCA-A) degree requirements, for another major, nor any other business minor requirements (with the exception of business electives).
Business students choosing to minor in economics must follow the CBA economics minor requirements.
College of Arts and Sciences (ASC) students interested in completing an economics minor must refer to the ASC section for the ASC economics major/minor.

To fulfill the requirements for an economics minor, CBA students must complete:

Nine (9) graded hours of 300/400-level economics course work
All course work must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass)

Economics Minor Requirements for Arts and Science economics major:

If majoring in economics through the College of Arts and Sciences, please see economics minor for ASC for specific requirements.

OTHER

All students enrolling in CBA courses are required to meet the prerequisites listed for each course, including any specific grade or GPA requirement, to include all requirements for enrollment in most 300- or 400-level economics courses.

ECON 211 and ECON 212 Macro- and Microeconomics are ACE 6 and ACE 8 approved course work and have been double counted to fulfill both the ACE requirement of the University (for ACE 6 and 8) and the College’s Business Core Foundation (BCF) requirements.

ECON 215 Statistics is an approved ACE 3 course and may be used to fulfill the ACE 3 requirement of the University.

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics is an approved ACE 9 course and while most students will complete ACE 9 during the freshman and sophomore year with other course work, transfer and upper-class students meeting the prerequisite, may wish to take this class, counting it for both an NBR 6–ACE 9 and as a course for the Business Core Advanced–Major (MCA–M) in economics. It also may be used to fulfill the International Business Course Requirement (IBCR), allowing it to be counted three ways.

Regardless of its double or triple counting, there are only 3 hours of credit awarded and students must still meet the 120 hour requirement for graduation.

Electronics Engineering (Omaha)

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Electronics Engineering (Lincoln)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Electronics Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 127

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISER: Roger Sash

DESCRIPTION

Interim Chair: Roger Sash, PKI 201E

Professors: Chen, Sharif, Wysocki

Associate Professors: Ci, Jang, Nguyen, Peng, Qian, Sash

Assistant Professor: Yang

Senior Lecturers: Detloff, Gilmore

Phone: 402-554-2288

FAX: 402-554-2289

Website: http://ceen.unl.edu

Email: rsash1@unl.edu

The electronics engineering program is administered by the Department of Computer and Electronics Engineering (CEEN) and the bachelor of science degree program is accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of ABET, http://www.abet.org.

Mission

The mission of the Department of Computer and Electronics Engineering (CEEN) at the University of Nebraska is to develop and maintain programs of excellence in teaching and research which meet the educational needs of its constituents, which will support the state of Nebraska in its development as a leading center for high-technology computer/electronics/telecommunications industry and which will support national needs for well-educated computer and electronics engineering professionals.

Program Educational Objectives

The Department’s Program Educational Objectives are a statement of what its graduates are doing or are capable of doing three to five years after graduation. The students in the electronics engineering program receive a strong foundation in engineering science and design that will enable them to pursue productive careers in not only the electronics engineering field, but can also be used as the foundation for careers in other areas such as business, management, and medicine. Typical industries in which the electronics engineering graduate would be employed could include those in communication systems, telecommunication networks, analog systems, hardware/software integration, and digital and microprocessor systems.

The Electronic Engineering program prepares our graduates for their professional career with the objectives that within five years after graduation they will be:

Employed in industry, academia or government
Successful engineers who develop innovative solutions for design and construction of electrical/electronic systems and other applications of modern engineering
Functioning on teams, exhibiting leadership, and making effective contributions to the benefit of their workplace and community
Engaging in postgraduate education or pursuing professional development for continuously renewing and expanding their knowledge base
Performing engineering practice in context that reflects awareness of the ethics of their profession, and of the impacts of their work on the profession and society at large.

These Program Educational Objectives were developed with input from the program’s educational objectives constituency consisting of employers (including CEEN Industry Advisory Board), graduates of the program, and faculty of the department.

The individual holding this degree will have advanced knowledge in his or her field of engineering interest and in addition will have a university educational background involving mathematics, the physical sciences, and the humanities and social sciences. The curriculum has a strong focus in telecommunications engineering. Completion of this program will enable the graduate to enter employment in positions involving telecommunications engineering design, analog circuit design, telecommunications network performance analysis, and technical management of telecommunications networks. The program also leads to the preparation for graduate work in electronics engineering or electrical engineering.

Concentrations

The department offers several areas of concentration so students can attain an in-depth study of a topic in computer engineering or electronics engineering. The electronics engineering concentrations are:

Bioelectronics

Electrical Engineering

Network Security

Robotics and Control

Telecommunications

Wireless Systems

ADMISSION

General Requirements

Advisement

Upon entry into the curriculum, each student will be assigned a faculty academic adviser. It is required that the student meet with the adviser prior to each class registration period and that all courses to be applied toward the degree be selected with the advice and approval of the adviser. Students are expected to have their academic records reviewed and obtain approval from the department prior to application to the University registrar for award of the degree in order to insure that all curricular requirements will be satisfied by the time of intended graduation.

Curriculum

Because of the rapid developments in the fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering, the curricular requirements are continually reviewed and upgraded to reflect technological advances. Curricular sequence and course descriptions contained herein are intended to serve as general guidelines. Contact the department for information on any changes to the requirements that are currently in effect but not listed in this catalog. Currently enrolled students are expected to modify their programs to take advantage of such revisions. Students who do not maintain continuous progress toward the degree through enrollment in applicable course work will be considered as new students upon reentering the computer or electronics engineering curricular sequence and will be subject to the requirements of the curriculum current at the time of their reentry. Certain courses may not be valid as prerequisites or as credit toward the degree after two academic years; the student’s academic adviser should be consulted regarding applicability.

The department maintains a high standard of excellence in meeting its objective of providing the student with extensive experience in the fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. The development of both hardware and software and the knowledge of the interrelationship of these areas is enhanced through the extensive use of laboratory equipment. The applicable University bulletins and College academic policies must be followed to ensure that the student satisfies the campus general education requirements.

Senior Thesis

The capstone senior thesis requirement provides a unique and challenging opportunity for the undergraduate student to demonstrate his/her ability to apply the knowledge gained in the course work sequence to the planning, design, execution, testing and reporting of a significant project in the applications of engineering principles. The initiative and responsibility expected of the student executing the senior thesis parallel the expectations of the employer of the program graduate.

Electives

Computer engineering and electronic engineering courses which are described in the catalog but are not shown as requirements in the semester sequences are offered as the need arises to provide co-interest areas wherein the students may broaden their background in the applications of computer engineering or electronics engineering. In addition, appropriate specified technical electives will be selected to augment the student’s particular area of interest. The applicability of transfer course work with engineering content toward credit in the curriculum is determined on a case-by-case basis by the department.

Special Interest Areas

Opportunities are provided for the development of areas of special interest through enrollment in the Individual Study in Computer and Electronics Engineering courses which are offered at the freshman through senior level for the student who may wish to develop a topic under the guidance of a department faculty member. Enrollment is by permission after the department chair has approved a written proposal. Special Topics in Computer and Electronics Engineering classes also are offered by the department as the need arises to cover topics needing emphasis as a result of the rapidly developing fields of computer engineering and electronics engineering. Academic advisers should be consulted regarding the particular topics to be covered and the necessary prerequisites for each offering of this course.

Students who expect to continue their education at the graduate level after the award of the baccalaureate degree should consult their adviser regarding course selections that would enhance that objective.

Students are encouraged to develop their professional and leadership potential through participation in student chapters of related professional organizations and in University extracurricular activities. Participation in the University Honors Program is encouraged for those who qualify.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Typical Schedule

First Semester Hours

CEEN 103 Computer & Electronics Engineering Fundamentals 4

CSCE 155A Computer Science I or 155E Computer Science I: Systems Engineering Focus 3

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument 3

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

Total 15

Second Semester Hours

CEEN 106 Microprocessor Applications 3

CEEN 225 Computer & Electronics Engineering Seminar 1

COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II* 4

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

PHYS 221 General Physics Lab I 1

Total 16

*Calculus II is a 5-credit course on the Omaha campus. Students taking Calculus II on the Lincoln campus will need to obtain an additional 1 credit hour of math or science.

Third Semester Hours

CEEN 213 Electrical Circuits I 4

CEEN 218 Electrical Circuits Lab 1

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

MATH 314 Applied Linear Algebra (Matrix Theory) 3

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 15

Fourth Semester Hours

CEEN 214 Electrical Circuits II 3

CEEN 222 Electronic Circuits I 4

JGEN 300 Technical Writing 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

ACE Elective SLO 5 3

Total 17

Fifth Semester Hours

CEEN 328 Applied Fields & Lines I 3

CEEN 352 Electronic Circuits II 4

CEEN 355 Signals & Linear Systems 3

MATH 380 Statistics & Applications 3

ACE Elective SLO 6 3

Total 16

Sixth Semester Hours

CEEN 313 Switching Circuit Theory 4

CEEN 325 Communications Systems 4

CEEN 361 Data & Telecommunications Transceivers 4

Conc/ENGR Elective 4

Total 16

Seventh Semester Hours

CEEN 499 Senior Thesis Proposal 1

ENGR 469 Tech, Science & Civ (UNO) 3

Conc/ENGR Elective 9

ACE Elective SLO 7 3

Total 16

Eighth Semester Hours

CEEN 499 Senior Thesis 3

Conc/ENGR Elective 6

ACE Elective SLO 8 & 9 6

Total 15

Students must complete one of the electronics engineering concentrations.

Three hours of the engineering electives can be chosen from a list of approved non-CEEN courses.

Total Credit Hours Required 127

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

All course work must be of “C” grade level or higher to be credited toward graduation requirements or to be valid as a prerequisite for another course.

Energy Science Minor

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Energy Science (Minor only)

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Assistant Professor Adam Liska, 246 Chase Hall

Professors: Conley, Hudgins, Schinstock, Yoder

Website: http://energysciences.unl.edu

The energy science minor is designed to offer an educational component to University of Nebraska students that will prepare them with the knowledge, expertise, and background to successfully compete for positions with companies that are producing or developing renewable energy sources. The minor is for students who desire a broad understanding of energy related issues and an in-depth knowledge of energy in one or more of four elective thematic areas as well as for those seeking employment in agriculture, business/industry, communication, transportation, and government plus domestic use.

Minor Requirements

A minor in energy science (ENSC) will include a minimum of 18 credit hours of energy-related courses including three core courses (ENSC 110 Energy in Perspective, ENSC 220 Introduction to Energy Systems, and ENSC 230 Energy and the Environment: Economics and Policy). The remaining energy-related courses must come from one or more of the four elective thematic tracks (Energy and Natural Resources; Plant and Animal Bioenergy; Energy Engineering; and Energy Economics, Policy, and Human Dimensions) or be approved by the student’s academic adviser and the minor coordinator. Additionally, a 1-credit-hour Energy Seminar (ENSC 300) will be required, and an optional 1-credit-hour Nebraska Energy Study Tour (ENSC 311) and an optional 1-credit-hour Independent Energy Study (ENSC 496) will be offered. Completing each of the 1-credit-hour courses will allow a student to use those 3 credit hours in place of a course from one of the four thematic areas. At least 6 credit hours must be at the 300 or 400 level and up to 3 hours of energy-related independent study course work may be included.

Courses of Instruction (ENSC)

Courses suitable for automatic inclusion in one of the four elective thematic areas have been identified and the list can be obtained from the minor coordinator or any of the minor advisers listed above. Other courses may be included with prior approval of the minor coordinator.

A student in consultation with the academic adviser and a minor adviser (chosen from those above) prepares a list of courses on the CASNR Application for Minor form, obtains the appropriate signatures and submits the minor form to the minor coordinator prior to deadline for submitting the application for graduation. Upon approval, the minor program will be forwarded to the University Registrar, with a copy supplied to the student’s major college. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript upon graduation.

English

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: English

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Kelly Payne

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Susan Belasco, 204A Andrews Hall

Vice Chair: Laura White

Professors: Agee, Bauer, Behrendt, Belasco, Brooke, Buhler, Dawes, Dixon, Foster, Garelick, Goodburn, Honey, Kaye, Kooser, Pratt, Price, Reynolds, Slater, White

Associate Professors: Abel, Castro, Condon, Dreher, Gannon, Homestead, Lynch, Minter, Montes, Ramsay, Stenberg

Assistant Professors: Capuano, Deb, Gailey, Jockers, Rutledge, Schaffert, Schleck, Stage, Vegso, Waite

Research Associate Professor: Ronning

Associate Professor of Practice: Griffin

Assistant Professor of Practice: Vespa

The Department of English seeks to provide for the diverse needs of its students by offering them the opportunity to read widely, to understand and enjoy what they read, and to express themselves both orally and in writing with ease, force and clarity. Through the practice of writing and the study of language, literature and film, the department strives to stimulate humanistic learning and the capacity to respond rationally and imaginatively to literature and the life it reflects.

The undergraduate major in English is designed for three groups: 1) those who seek a general education; 2) those who plan to teach in the elementary and secondary schools; and 3) those who plan to pursue graduate study in the field. The major is also frequently chosen as preparation for professional study in law, medicine, and business, and for careers in other fields such as publishing, editing, library science, and digital humanities. Many students find the English major is a fine complement to a major in a professional field.

A student declaring an English major will meet with the chief adviser to establish a tentative rationale and plan for the major. Thereafter the student must meet with the chief adviser at least once a year to update the major plan, review progress toward the degree, plan a concentration, and consult about course selection, scholarships, and careers or post-graduate education. The department Advising Center (201 Andrews Hall) will offer written information about these matters and others of interest to majors.

Special Programs. The Department of English houses the major in Film Studies and participates in the majors in Ethnic Studies and in Women’s and Gender Studies; in the minors in African American Studies, U.S. Latina/Latino Studies, Ethnic Studies, Native American Studies, Judaic Studies, Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and Religious Studies.

International Students. International students who are not native speakers of English must take an English placement examination. For details, see the coordinator of the English as a Second Language program in the Department of English.

The Curriculum

Course Offerings. English courses are regularly offered in drama, poetry, and fiction; the English language; periods and authors in British and American literature; women’s and minority literatures; creative and expository writing; literary and rhetorical theory and criticism; and film. For the precise courses offered or to be offered in any particular semester, see the Schedule of Classes for that semester. A course description booklet is also available in the departmental office and online before each early registration period.

Credit Hours. Undergraduate English courses will usually yield 3 semester hours of credit. Graduate-level seminars are usually offered for variable credit (normally 3 or 4 credit hours). The letter suffix “H” indicates an honors course; “X” indicates an online course.

Independent Study. This is a provision for students wishing to study areas of literature and language not covered or insufficiently covered in regularly scheduled classes. Students must secure permission from a professorial staff member willing to direct their study and must file an Independent Directed Reading Contract (available in the Advising Center, 201 Andrews Hall) with the Undergraduate Adviser.

NOTE: Neither ENGL 495 (Internship) nor ENGL 497 (Independent Study) count towards fulfilling 400-level requirements for majors and minors. A maximum of 6 credit hours of ENGL 399 (Independent Study) and/or ENGL 497 may count towards the 300-level requirement for the major.

Prerequisites. The first course in English is ordinarily chosen from courses numbered 100-151. However, international students who are not native speakers of English normally take English courses such as ENGL 140, ENGL 141, ENGL 142, ENGL 186, ENGL 187, and ENGL 188.

Course Levels

100 Level. Introductory courses are open only to freshman and sophomore students. Transfer students and others who have not met the communication requirement and have 65 or more credit hours must choose ENGL 254 or ENGL 354 to complete this requirement. (In unusual cases, exceptions to this rule may be granted by the Chief Adviser, English Department.) Writing is emphasized in courses numbered 100-199, and all such courses except ENGL 140, ENGL 141, ENGL 142, ENGL 180, ENGL 189H, ENGL 186, and ENGL 187, are designed to fulfill ACE Outcome 1. Newly admitted students who are not native speakers of English must take an English placement examination to determine their appropriate course requirement.

200 Level. Courses designed for the intermediate student who has completed or is concurrently taking one or two courses in English.

300 Level. Courses designed for the intermediate student who ordinarily will have had two courses at the 200 level. These students should normally take the remainder of their courses at the 300 level or 400 level. English majors and minors should advance to the 300 level as soon as possible.

400 Level. Courses designed for the advanced student or the student with a special interest. English majors must take at least 6 credit hours at the 400 level.

800/900 Level. Graduate courses. Graduate standing and at least 18 hours of undergraduate course work in English are prerequisite to courses at the 800- and 900-level. Advanced undergraduates may register in 800- and 900-level courses with the permission of the Dean of Graduate Studies, provided that these hours do not count towards their baccalaureate requirements.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

36 hours distributed at the following levels:

200 level or above 12

300 level or above 18

400 level 6

The major also requires a minimum number of these 36 hours in different areas or courses:

A. ENGL 200 3

B. Linguistics, writing, and/or rhetoric 3

ENGL 254, ENGL 322A, ENGL 322B, ENGL 354, ENGL 376, or ENGL 480

C. Literary or rhetorical theory 3

ENGL 270, ENGL 275, ENGL 373, ENGL 471, ENGL 475, ENGL 475A, or ENGL 478

D. Historical Literature Core 9

British Literature 3

ENGL 230, ENGL 230A*, ENGL 231, ENGL 305A, ENGL 330, ENGL 330E*, ENGL 331, ENGL 362, ENGL 363, ENGL 364, or ENGL 365

Literature Before 1800 3

ENGL 230, ENGL 230A*, ENGL 330E*, ENGL 341, ENGL 362, ENGL 363, or ENGL 364

American Literature 3

ENGL 260, ENGL 261, ENGL 332, ENGL 333, or ENGL 334

E. Literature in the Context of Culture, Ethnicity, and/or Gender 3

ENGL 212, ENGL 215, ENGL 244, ENGL 244E, ENGL 245A, ENGL 245J, ENGL 245N, ENGL 315A, ENGL 315B, ENGL 344B, ENGL 344D, ENGL 345D, or ENGL 345N

F. Capstone Course 3

ENGL 487

G. Concentration 12

(12 hours at the 300- or 400-level, only 6 of which can be in creative writing)

*Only one of these courses may count for the historical literature core.

No course which includes fewer than three authors can be used to satisfy area requirements except one course in Chaucer or Shakespeare or Milton. One advanced-level literature course in another language may count for the major, with the chief adviser’s permission. A student may receive credit for a course bearing the same course number and letter more than once with the prior permission of the chief adviser, as long as the subtitles vary.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required from time to time to complete written exit surveys and to compile portfolios of selected written work in major courses. All such work will be assessed in ways that assure student anonymity.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Concentrations. Students with particular career goals, or who desire to attend graduate school, should consider developing a concentration to support those aspirations. Students may design their own concentration in consultation with the chief adviser and appropriate faculty members. Such concentrations would typically group together four courses from sub-fields such as literary and cultural studies, creative writing, film studies, composition and rhetoric, Medieval and Renaissance studies, 19th century studies, environmental and place studies, ethnic studies, women’s and gender studies, editing and publishing, digital humanities, or other areas of the student’s choosing. In some cases, an interdisciplinary concentration may include a course from another department. Students select four courses at the 300 or 400 level. Students wishing to develop a concentration are encouraged to consult with the English Undergraduate Advising Office (201 Andrews) early in their program.

Minor Requirements

English majors are required to complete one Plan A minor or two Plan B minors or a second major.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

A student may apply up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass credit toward a major in English without securing permission; and a student may apply up to 3 hours of Pass/No Pass credit toward a minor in English, subject to the approval of the department granting the major. To secure the necessary approval, students may obtain request forms from the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

No more than 6 Pass/No Pass hours can count for the English major. No course can count for more than one requirement.

Course Level Requirement

No more than 6 hours of Independent Directed Reading (including internships) will count for the major. Neither independent study taken at the 400 level nor an internship will count for the 400-level requirement for the major. Students taking 6 hours of ENGL 399H may count for the major no more than 3 additional hours of Independent Directed Reading. No more than 3 hours of internship (ENGL 495) will count for the English major.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A. 18 hrs of English above the 100 level; 9 hrs must be above 299; of these 9 hrs, 3 hrs must be above 399.

Plan B. 12 hrs of English beyond the 100 level; 6 hrs above 299.

No more than 3 hours of Pass/No Pass may count for a minor in English.

Family & Consumer Sciences Education (6-12)

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Child, Youth & Family Studies

PROGRAM: Family & Consumer Sciences Education (6-12)

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: AnnMarie Williams

DESCRIPTION

Students who complete this field endorsement are endorsed to teach family and consumer sciences in grades 6 through 12.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the curriculum and these must be successfully completed in order to be certified in the teaching profession. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Felony and Misdemeanor Conviction” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements (or majors) are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their adviser, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 31

ACE 1. ENGL 150/ENGL 150H or ENGL 151/ENGL 151H or ENGL 101/ENGL 101H or ENGL 254 or JGEN 120 or JGEN 200 or JGEN 220 3

ACE 2. COMM 109/COMM 109H or COMM 209 or COMM 210 or COMM 286 (Pre-professional Requirement) 3

ACE 3. 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Course) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 (Pre-professional Requirement) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. TEAC 331 (Pre-professional Requirement) 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 (Endorsement Requirement) 3

ACE 10. CYAF 403 (Professional Education Requirement) 3

Pre-Professional Requirements 29

LIBR 110 1

CYAF 150, CYAF 222, *CYAF 280, *CYAF 380, & CYAF 382 (3 hrs ea) 15

CYAF 270 2

CYAF 270L 1

EDPS *251 (3 hrs) & EDPS 297 (1 hr) 4

TEAC 259 & *TEAC 330 6

Endorsement Requirements 31-32

CYAF 333 3

NUTR 244, NUTR 250, NUTR 372 (3 hrs ea) 9

NUTR 245 1

*TMFD 123 or CYAF 493 3

Emphasis Electives: Select one of three plans – see adviser 15-16

Professional Education Requirements 28

CYAF 297J & CYAF 397J (1 hr ea) 2

CYAF 451 3

CYAF 452 4

CYAF 497J 10

*EDPS 457 3

SPED 401B 3

TEAC 425 3

Electives 0-1

Total Hours 120

* These courses are also approved ACE courses and together with the 30 hours of ACE required courses meet the additional ACE/General Education requirements for secondary education students

NOTE: Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for CYAF courses.

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Additional ACE Course Work for Secondary Education

Secondary education students need additional ACE courses for a total of 40 hours to meet the requirements for the Nebraska Department of Education. One of the ACE courses must be an approved speech course. At least two of the ACE courses must be at the 300/400 level. Once again, there may be required courses within your program that will also satisfy these additional ACE requirements. Contact your adviser.

ADMISSION

All education programs have a competitive admission process. At some point-in-time, after meeting specific education requirements, all students must formally apply to their particular education program.

Pre-Education Status

All newly admitted students who are pursuing a teacher preparation program are classified as pre-education students until admitted to a specific Teacher Education Program.

Admission to a Teacher Education Program (TEP)

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission into a teacher education program. Admission to the advanced phases of teacher education is selective and, in some endorsements, highly competitive. Students must satisfy the following requirements in order to be eligible to apply to the Teacher Education Program:

1. A minimum 2.5 cumulative GPA.

2. Must have earned a minimum of 42 credit hours of college credit.

3. Completion and submission of the Teacher Education Program Application Form.

4. Completion of TEAC 331 and EDPS 251 or an approved transfer course, (must be taken prior to or be in progress, the semester in which you apply to the TEP) with a 2.5 cumulative average in the two classes, and no grade lower than C; TEAC 259 (must also be taken prior to or be in progress, the semester in which you apply to the TEP).

5. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of the Praxis I, Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST), a basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

6. Completion of one course in communication studies selected from COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, or COMM 286, or approved substitute.

7. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form (PPF) as well as the completion of a formal criminal history review, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required).

8. Specific programs may have particular learning outcomes that students must address as part of the application process.

Other Admission Requirements

Admission to Student Teaching

All students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate are required to student teach. Students who plan to student teach in the fall semester must complete the student teaching application form and submit it by the preceding March 1 to the Director of Field Experiences in 116 Henzlik Hall; students planning to student teach in the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1. The basic program for student teaching provides for a full-day experience for an entire semester. Admission to student teaching requires the following:

1. Matriculation in a teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences, the Graduate College, or dual matriculation in the College of Education and Human Sciences and another college.

2. Admission to a specific teacher education program.

3. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.5.

4. Minimum grade point average of 2.5 in the endorsement area with no grade below C.

5. A minimum grade point average of 2.5 in pre-professional and professional education courses and no grade below C in pre-professional education courses and no grade below a C+ in professional education courses.

6. All endorsement, pre-professional and professional education course work must be completed prior to student teaching. If necessary, no more than 6 hours of general education (ACE) or elective classes can be completed after the student teaching experience.

7. No additional course work can be taken during the student teaching semester unless prior approval is obtained from the Certification Officer, the Director of Field Experiences, or the Department Chair that oversees the program.

8. Completion of a second criminal history check that will be conducted, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required). For more information, contact the Director of Field Experiences or your adviser.

MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

80% of these endorsement requirements must be completed prior to enrolling in your first professional methods course. Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for CYAF courses.

CYAF 333 Families in the Economy

NUTR 244 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation

NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation Lab

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

**NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation

**TMFD 123 Clothing & Human Behavior or CYAF 493 Special Topics: Teaching Clothing in Middle & Secondary Schools

Emphasis Electives

Select one of three plans for additional content.

1. Select an emphasis area.

Nutrition and Health (15 hrs)
Hospitality and Restaurant Management (16 hrs)
Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design (15 hrs)
Family Studies (15 hrs)
Child Studies (16 hrs)
Health Occupations (15 hrs)

2. Create an emphasis area by combining courses from two areas above. Select 6 hours from one list and 9 hours from another. For example, create a Child and Family Studies emphasis by selecting 9 hours in Family Science and 6 hours in Child Studies or vice versa.

3. Select 15-16 hours of course work from any of the three Human Sciences departments (Child, Youth and Family Studies; Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design; and Nutrition and Health Sciences).

Courses for each Emphasis Area

Nutrition and Health—Select 15 hours

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health

NUTR 131 The Science of Food

NUTR 251 Nutrition Through the Life Cycle

NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

NUTR 344 Food & Nutrition for Healthy Living

NUTR 430 Nutritional Anthropology

Hospitality and Food Service—Select 16 hours

HRTM 289 Intro to the Event Industry

HRTM 373 Catering

HRTM 477 Hospitality Facility Planning & Purchasing

HRTM 489 Advanced Event Operations

NUTR 370 Food Production Management

NUTR 371 Applied Food Production Laboratory

Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design—Select 15 hours

TMFD 123 Clothing & Human Behavior (If not selected in initial requirements) or CYAF 493 Special Topics: Teaching Clothing in Middle & Secondary Schools (If not selected in initial requirements)

TMFD 206 Textiles

TMFD 212 Product Development I: Apparel Analysis & Development

TMFD 213 Merchandising I: Textile & Apparel Industry

TMFD 225 Surface Design on Textiles

TMFD 325 Woven/Non-Woven Fibers

TMFD 407 History of Costume

TMFD 408 History of Textiles

Family Studies—Select 15 hours

CYAF 285 Dating & Couple Relationships

CYAF 322 Advanced Family Finance

CYAF 446 Addictions & Families

CYAF 458 Family Stress & Crisis, Coping & Recovery

CYAF 488 Child & Family Policy

CYAF 493 Special Topics in Contemporary Family Issues

CYAF 495 Special Topics in Family & Cultural Diversity

Child Studies—Select 15-16 hours

CYAF 271/271L Infancy & Lab

CYAF 371 Methods of Working with Infants in Programs & Communities

CYAF 374 Curriculum Planning In Early Childhood Education

CYAF 383 Literacy Methods for Young Children

CYAF 384 World of Wonder: Math, Science & Nature Integrated Methods Birth to Age 5

CYAF 210 Applied Methods of Social Emotional Development & Guidance

CYAF 210L Applied Methods of Social Emotional Development & Guidance Lab

CYAF 474 Assessment in Early Childhood

Health Occupations—Select 15 hours

CYAF 446 Addictions & Families

CYAF 471/PSYC 471 Sexuality

GERO 200 Intro to Gerontology

GERO 307 Death & Dying

PHIL 106 Current Issues

PHIL 206 Medical Ethics

PSYC 280 Abnormal Psychology

Supporting Course Requirements

**CHEM 109

Pre-Professional Requirements

**EDPS 251 (Must be taken prior to the Teacher Education Program (TEP) application or during the semester the TEP application is submitted.)

EDPS 297

TEAC 259 (Must be taken prior to the Teacher Education Program (TEP) application or during the semester the TEP application is submitted.)

**TEAC 331 or an approved transfer course (Must be taken prior to the Teacher Education Program (TEP) application or during the semester the TEP application is submitted.)

**COMM 109, COMM 109H, **COMM 209, COMM 210, or COMM 286, or an approved speech class (Must be taken prior to the Teacher Education Program (TEP) application or during the semester the TEP application is submitted.)

**TEAC 330

LIBR 110

CYAF 150 Life Skills for Success

**CYAF 160 Human Development & the Family

CYAF 222 Intro to Family Finance

CYAF 270 & CYAF 270L Development of the Preschool Child & Lab

**CYAF 280 Family Science

**CYAF 380 Working with Families in Communities & Schools

CYAF 382 Parenting

Professional Requirements

Students must be admitted into this Teacher Education Program before enrolling in these courses.

**EDPS 457, SPED 401B, TEAC 425, CYAF 451, CYAF 297J, CYAF 452, CYAF 397J,

Student teaching: CYAF 497J, **CYAF 403

** These courses also meet ACE requirements. See your adviser.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their endorsement and education courses with no grade lower than a C in their pre-professional courses and no grade lower than a C+ in their professional education courses.

Transfer Grades

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Pass/No Pass Grade Option–for Education Students

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of no pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. Only one course in each subject endorsement may be taken P/N; two courses in a field endorsement may be taken P/N.

2. Pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken P/N unless a class already has a P/N designation.

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course may be taken P/N.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a P/N only basis.

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

Beyond Classroom Grades

In all fields of study, students are expected to attain certain grades and other academic accomplishments in the classroom. In addition to this, students preparing themselves to be teachers, counselors and for other careers in education, are also reviewed to evaluate their ability to successfully and safely interact with children, parents, potential educational employers, and the community-at-large, whose interest in the education of its children often exceeds its concern for other community and governmental services.

OTHER

Student Teaching Placement

The Office of Field Experiences is responsible for the placement of student teachers. Several factors are considered in determining the district and school to which an individual is assigned. The availability of a cooperating teacher and supervisor who meet the requirements established by the Nebraska Department of Education and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are among those factors. Opportunities to student teach out-of-state are limited and those placements are becoming increasingly difficult. All requests to student teach outside of the immediate Lincoln area must be individually reviewed and approved by the Director of Field Experiences.

Removal from Student Teaching

Students participating in practicum or student teaching assignments may be removed from their assigned schools if their conduct suggests a lack of professional commitment and presents a negative influence on the well-being or learning of the students in the schools. Specific guidelines that all student teachers are to follow can be found in The Student Teaching Experience: A Handbook for the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. If such a problem occurs, at the request of the cooperating teacher, building principal, and the College supervisor, the student will be removed from the school placement by the Director of Field Experiences. In such cases, a written report stating the problem and efforts to correct the situation will be forwarded to the Director of Field Experiences in the College Student Services Center.

Any student removed from a practicum or student teaching assignment may appeal that decision by submitting a written request to the College Appeals Committee within 30 days of the removal. The Appeals Committee will schedule a meeting, request pertinent information from the Director of Field Experiences, and notify the student several days in advance of the scheduled appeal meeting. Students are advised of their right to seek legal advice and may personally attend the Appeals Committee meeting. The Committee’s decision will be forwarded in writing to the student, to the Director of Field Experiences, and to the Dean of the College.

Application for a Nebraska Teaching Certificate

To actively engage in the teaching profession, a candidate must fulfill both the College degree requirements and the professional certification requirements of the State of Nebraska, Department of Education. Undergraduate students apply for the teaching certificate online at www.education.ne.gov/tcert and apply for the baccalaureate degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building. Post-baccalaureate students completing teacher certification also apply for the teaching certificate online at www.education.ne.gov/tcert, and if they complete a masters degree with their certificate program, apply for the degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building.

To be eligible for a recommendation for certification, a candidate must meet the following requirements:

1. Earn one or more undergraduate degrees from the College of Education and Human Sciences or another accredited institution approved by the College of Education and Human Sciences with a minimum 2.5 grade point average.

2. Complete the teacher education general education requirements listed for elementary, middle grades or secondary education.

3. Complete professional education requirements according to established standards.

4. Complete endorsement(s) according to established standards.

5. Successfully complete a required period of student teaching.

6. Complete application for the degree and certificate.

Graduation Without Certification

In rare cases, permission may be granted for a student to graduate without a recommendation for certification. This provision is for the student who does not qualify for or is removed from student teaching. However, there are times when because of illness or other extreme situations, a student will decide not to complete all professional requirements. In this situation, the student should contact his or her adviser, then complete a formal request to the College’s Certification Officer to be allowed to graduate without completing all certification requirements. If permission is granted, the student is expected to complete all professional requirements except student teaching. This includes a passing grade in all methods courses. If a student fails to complete at least one half of the student teaching assignment, the individual will be required to complete a culminating project not to exceed 6 credit hours.

Any student who graduates without a recommendation for certification will not be recommended for teacher certification in any state. In addition, the student will not be eligible for graduation with honors. If, at some future time, the student wishes to complete certification requirements, (s)he must first appeal for readmission to a teacher education program. At least one semester must pass after graduation before the appeal can be made. If the appeal is granted, the student will be treated as a readmitted student and will complete all requirements in effect at the time of reentry, including passing grades in all methods courses.

Education Employment Services

The Career Services Center, 230 Nebraska Union, offers a professional placement service to students and alumni who are seeking employment in education and related fields. In addition to providing on-campus interviews with select schools throughout the year, this office sponsors an annual Education Recruitment Day in the spring, which offers students an opportunity to interview with hiring officials from many schools.

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Family Science

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Child, Youth & Family Sciences

PROGRAM: Family Science

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

Family Science provides a comprehensive program grounded in family science theory, research, and professional practice and application for individuals to work with children and families. This career path provides students with knowledge and intervention skills that will assist them in helping to prevent and remedy interpersonal problems experienced by individuals in their family relationships, building on the family’s strengths. In addition, Family Science will prepare students for graduate school (e.g. family science, family therapy, social work, counseling psychology, and law), or for employment in human services agencies or programs.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30-34

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. ALEC 102, COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, COMM 283, COMM 286 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 3. ECON 215, EDPS 459, MATH 104, MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 108H, MATH 203, MATH 208, STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 4. ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L; CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 113; ENTO 115 & ENTO 116; GEOG 155; GEOL 101, GEOL 103; LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L; METR 200; NRES 108; PHYS 141, PHYS 142, PHYS 151 & PHYS 153, PHYS 260 & PHYS 262, TMFD 206 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. CYAF 150 (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 9. CYAF 495 (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 10. CYAF 497D (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

Supporting Courses 1

LIBR 110 1

CYAF Core Requirements 18-19

CYAF 222, CYAF 280, CYAF 285 or CYAF 382, CYAF 380, CYAF 488 (3 hr ea) 15

Human Development 3-4

Select one: CYAF 270 & CYAF 270L, CYAF 271 & CYAF 271L, CYAF 372; GERO 200, GERO 307, GERO 446, GERO 447; EDPS 250, EDPS 251, EDPS 450, EDPS 451; PSYC 289, PSYC 446, PSYC 489

Option Area: Choose either Option A or Option B 18-23

Option A – Human and Community Services 18

CYAF 333 (3 hrs)

CYAF 446 or CYAF 458 (3 hrs)

CYAF 471 (3 hrs)

Select one: PSYC 380, SLPA 150, SPED 201 (3 hrs)

Select one: CYAF 416, EDAD 421, EDAD 422, EDPS 362 (3 hrs)

Select one: CYAF 285, CYAF 322, CYAF 382, CYAF 446, CYAF 458, CYAF 493 (3 hrs)

Option B – Family Science Research 21-23

CYAF 333 (3 hrs)

CYAF 446 or CYAF 458 (3 hrs)

CYAF 471 (3 hrs)

CYAF 498 (3 hrs)

Select one: PSYC 380, SLPA 150, or SPED 201 (3 hrs)

Select either: PSYC 350 & PSYC 450 or SOCI 205 & SOCI 206 (6-8 hrs)

Minor Requirements 18

Approved minors: Anthropology, communication studies, education, gerontology, global studies, leadership and communications, psychology or sociology.

Electives 25-35

Total Hours 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

CYAF Core Requirements

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for all CYAF courses.

CYAF 150 Life Skills for Success

CYAF 160 Human Development & the Family

CYAF 222 Intro to Family Finance

CYAF 280 Family Science

CYAF 285 Dating & Couple Relationships or CYAF 382 Parenting

CYAF 380 Working with Families in Communities & Schools

CYAF 488 Child & Family Policy

CYAF 495 Special Topics in Family & Cultural Diversity or ETHN XXX

CYAF 497D Community Internships in Child, Youth & Family Studies

Human Development (select one):

CYAF 270 & CYAF 270L, CYAF 271 & CYAF 271L, CYAF 372; GERO 200, GERO 307, GERO 446, GERO 447; EDPS 250, EDPS 251, EDPS 450, EDPS 451; PSYC 289, PSYC 446, PSYC 489

Supporting Courses

LIBR 110

ALEC 102, COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 210, COMM 283, or COMM 286

ECON 215, EDPS 459, MATH 104, MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 108H, MATH 203, MATH 208, or STAT 218

Science Course with Lab (select from):

ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L; CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 113; ENTO 115 & ENTO 116; GEOG 155; GEOL 101, GEOL 103; LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L; LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L; METR 200; NRES 108; PHYS 141, PHYS 142, PHYS 151 & PHYS 153, PHYS 260 & PHYS 262; TMFD 206

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Students must select either an Option A or Option B career path. Courses taken that fulfill the requirements of other categories may not be counted for these credits.

Option A – Human and Community Services

This option is for students wanting to work with children and families in human services and youth organizations.

CYAF 333 Families in the Economy

CYAF 446 Addictions & Families or CYAF 458 Family Stress & Crisis, Coping & Recovery

CYAF 471 Human Sexuality & Society

Atypical Development (select one): PSYC 380, SLPA 150, SPED 201

Educational Programming/Learning (select one): CYAF 416, EDAD 421, EDAD 422, EDPS 362

CYAF Elective (select one): CYAF 285, CYAF 322, CYAF 382, CYAF 446, CYAF 458, CYAF 493

Option B – Family Science Research

This option is for students planning to pursue an advanced degree in family science or marriage and family therapy. Must have a 3.0 GPA for this option.

CYAF 333 Families in the Economy

CYAF 446 Addictions & Families or CYAF 458 Family Stress & Crisis, Coping & Recovery

CYAF 471 Human Sexuality & Society

Atypical Development (select one): PSYC 380, SLPA 150, SPED 201

PSYC 350 Research Methods & Data Analysis & PSYC 450 Advanced Research Methods & Analysis or SOCI 205 Intro to Social Research I & SOCI 206 Intro to Social Research II

CYAF 498 Research UCARE, REU, Non-UCARE Research Experience in Child, Youth & Family Studies

Minor Requirements

All family science majors must have a minor or area of concentration (18 hrs). Examples of approved minors: anthropology, communication studies, education, gerontology, global studies, leadership and communications, psychology or sociology.

OTHER

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Geography

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Geography

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: David Wishart

DESCRIPTION

Program Chair: James Merchant, 306 Hardin Hall

Professors: Amedeo, Archer, Dewey, Lawson (emeritus), Lonsdale (emeritus), Merchant, Narumalani, Rundquist, Stoddard (emeritus), Wilhite, Wishart

Associate Professors: Hanson, Zygielbaum

Assistant Professor: Guan

Research Assistant Professors: Knutson, Wardlow

The program of geography offers a wide variety of courses leading to the bachelor of arts and bachelor of science degrees in geography. The objectives of these programs are: 1) to support the goals of a broad liberal education by increasing awareness of the spatial, regional, and environmental aspects of the earth and its peoples; and 2) to provide a specialized knowledge of environmental processes, human-environment relations, American and foreign areas and cultures, and geographic techniques such as cartography, remote sensing and geographic information analysis. An education in geography prepares students for careers in government agencies as well as those involved with foreign service, land management, tourism, health care delivery systems, environmental assessment, transportation development, land use planning, air traffic control, GIS and cartographic analysis, and in a wide variety of businesses, particularly those concerned with environmental mapping, geographic information systems, and planning. A geography major also prepares students for graduate-level degrees in geography, law (especially environmental law), international business, urban and regional planning, and teaching at all levels.

Major in Geography

The major in geography consists of seven mandatory courses with a common core in human-environment relations. Students should begin their programs with introductory physical and human courses, then move to courses dealing with environmental issues, world regions, and courses in techniques of acquiring, mapping and displaying geographic data. An undergraduate seminar which covers historical and philosophical aspects of geography as well as practical matters such as jobs and graduate schools, completes the set of mandatory courses. Beyond this core of required courses are nine hours of electives.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy in geography are offered. For details on these programs, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The major entails a total of 30 hours distributed as follows:

GEOG 140 Introductory Human Geography or GEOG 120 Economic Geography 3

GEOG 155 Elements of Physical Geography 4

GEOG 181 Quality of the Environment 3

GEOG 272 World Regions 3

Techniques (see course listing), with at least 3 hrs numbered 400 or above 6

GEOG 402 Undergraduate Seminar (Senior Seminar) 3

Elective Geography courses 9

Of the total 30 hours, 14 hours must be numbered 300 or above. Students wishing to combine a geography major with other majors, environmental studies, for example, should see the respective advisers.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to complete written and oral examinations in the Senior Seminar, GEOG 402, over knowledge in all components of the major, as well as over more detailed knowledge in the student’s area of focus. Students will be informed of the scheduling and format of assessment exams in the Senior Seminar. Students will also be given exit interviews prior to graduation to gather their views on the effectiveness of the major.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

18 hours, including 10 hours in courses numbered 300 or above.

Great Plains Studies

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Great Plains Studies

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Charles Braithwaite

DESCRIPTION

Director: James Stubbendieck, 1155 Q Street, Room 306

Chief Adviser: Charles Braithwaite, 1155 Q Street, Room 504

Great Plains Studies is an interdisciplinary/ intercollegiate program of the Center for Great Plains Studies, 1155 Q Street. A major or minor in Great Plains Studies is a useful program for students who plan a career in business, education, planning, policy analysis, agriculture, public relations, marketing, and any profession or career where an in-depth understanding of the Pains region would be advantageous. Courses that comprise the program are based in the following cooperating departments: African American and African Studies; Agricultural Economics; Agronomy; Anthropology and Geography; Architecture; Art and Art History; Biological Sciences; Communication Studies; Community and Regional Planning; Earth and Atmospheric Sciences; English; Ethnic Studies; History; Latino and Latin American Studies; Modern Languages and Literatures; Music; Native American Studies; Natural Resource Sciences; Political Science; Sociology; and Women and Gender Studies. Internships are strongly encouraged and may be used to fulfill major or minor requirements. The Frances W. Kaye Scholarship for $500 is awarded each year to a Great Plains major.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

GPSP 170 Introduction to Great Plains Studies (3 cr), and GPSP 400 Seminar in Great Plains Studies (3 cr), and at least one course in each of the four categories: human heritage, natural environment, social environment, and arts and humanities, for a total of 12 hours. The remaining 12 hours can be taken from other courses listed under these categories, from at-large courses, or as independent study, except that no more than 3 hours of independent study will ordinarily be counted toward the major.

The courses should be chosen in such a way as to construct a thematically or professionally coherent program. Other courses or independent study may be substituted for some of the courses listed with permission of the chief adviser. The chief adviser may also assign an adviser for each student from among the faculty fellows of the Center.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required:

1. To develop a portfolio consisting of materials from Great Plains course work, to be submitted to the chief adviser prior to graduation. The portfolio should include a research paper from the Seminar in Great Plains Studies, GPSP 400, as well as papers from at least three other courses that apply to the major.

2. In their senior year, to participate in an exit interview. The chief adviser will inform students of the scheduling and format of assessment activities.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

A. Core Courses

All majors take at least one course from each of the following four categories:

Arts and Humanities

AHIS 398 Great Plains Art (3 cr)

ENGL 211 Literature of Place (3 cr)

Human Heritage

ANTH 434 Introduction to Great Plains Archaeology (3 cr)

GEOG 334 Historical Geography of the Great Plains (3 cr)

HIST 360 History of Nebraska and the Great Plains (3 cr)

HIST 465 History of Plains Indians (ETHN 465) (3 cr)

Natural Environment

BIOS 232 Ecological Issues in the Great Plains (3 cr)

NRES 310 Introduction to Forest Management (3 cr)

Social Environment

ANTH 130 Anthropology of the Great Plains (3 cr)

ANTH 352 Indigenous Peoples of the Great Plains (ETHN 352) (3 cr)

POLS 225 Nebraska Government & Politics (3 cr)

B. Courses at Large

Great Plains Courses at Large

AECN 201 Farm & Ranch Management (4 cr)

AECN 265 Resource & Environmental Economics I (NREE 265) (3 cr)

AECN 376 Rural Community Economics (3 cr)

AECN 388 Ethics in Agriculture & Natural Resources (ALEC 388) (3 cr)

AECN 445 Agricultural & Natural Resource Policy Analysis (NREE 445) (3 cr)

AGRO 440 Great Plains Ecosystem (RNGE 440/NRES 440) (3 cr)

AGRO 445 Livestock Management on Range & Pasture (ASCI 451/RNGE 445) (3 cr)

AGRO 475 Water Quality Strategy (CIVE 475/CRPL 475/GEOL 475/MSYM 475/NRES 475/POLS 475/SOCI 475/SOIL 475/WATS 475) (3 cr)

ANTH 451 Contemporary Issues of Indigenous Peoples in North America (ETHN 451) (3 cr)

BIOS 455 Great Plains Flora (4 cr)

BIOS 459 Limnology (NRES 459/WATS 459) (4 cr) (Offered at Cedar Point Biological Station)

BIOS 470 Prairie Ecology (4 cr) (Offered at Cedar Point Biological Station)

BIOS 475 Ornithology (3 cr) (Offered at Cedar Point Biological Station)

BIOS 482 Field Entomology (ENTO 411) (4 cr) (Offered at Cedar Point Biological Station)

BIOS 487 Field Parasitology (4 cr) (Offered at Cedar Point Biological Station)

BIOS 488 Natural History of the Invertebrates (4 cr) (Offered at Cedar Point Biological Station)

BIOS 489 Ichthyology (NRES 489) (4 cr) (Offered at Cedar Point Biological Station)

ENGL 245N Introduction to Native American Literature (ETHN 245N) (3 cr)

ENGL 405K Canadian Fiction (3 cr)

ENGL 445N Native American Literature (ETHN 445N) (3 cr)

GEOG 370 Geography of Nebraska (2-3 cr)

HIST 352 American West Since 1900 (3 cr)

HIST 359 The Mythic West (3 cr)

MUSC 489 American Music (3 cr)

NRES 484 Water Resources Seminar (AGRO 484, GEOG 484, GEOL 484) (1 cr)

SOCI 446 Environmental Sociology (3 cr)

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Course Level Requirement

At least 12 hours of course work must be at the 300 and 400 levels.

Extended Education, Independent Study Rules, Internship Credit Rules

No more than 3 hours of independent study will ordinarily be counted toward the major.

Up to 6 hours of suitable internship work can be included in the 30 hours required for the major, and Great Plains Studies students are strongly encouraged to pursue an internship through Career Services: Student Jobs and Internships as part of their program.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

18 hours, at least 6 at 300 level or above, including:

GPSP 170 Introduction to Great Plains Studies (ANTH 170/GEOG 170/NRES 170/SOCI 170) (3 cr)

GPSP 400 Seminar in Great Plains Studies (GEOG 400/HIST 400) (3 cr)

Three hours each from three out of four core areas approved for major.

Three hours to be chosen from among core courses, courses-at-large, internship, or independent study.

History

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: History

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Ann Tschetter

DESCRIPTION

Chair: William Thomas, 609 Oldfather Hall

Professors: Ambrosius, Berger, Borstelmann, A. Burnett, Cahan, Coble, Jacobs, Kleimola, LeSueur, Levin, Mahoney, Maslowski, Thomas, Winkle

Associate Professors: Akers, Coope, Garza, Gorman, J. Jones, P. Jones, Lawrence, Smith

Assistant Professors: Ari, Curry, Der Matossian, Seefeldt, Steinacher

The Department of History offers topical and period courses of general cultural and educational value to all University students to broaden their range of historical experience and sense of perspective. The particular aim of the history program is not only to provide knowledge for students who are preparing for a career in education, but also to give instruction that will aid those with interests in law, journalism, library, and museum work; in local, state, and national public service; and in business where a knowledge of domestic and foreign affairs is particularly useful.

Honors Program. The Department of History offers a four-year program of honors work beginning with honors sections in the introductory courses for freshmen and sophomores. For upperclassmen, the Departmental Honors Program consists of directed reading courses and seminars. In the senior year, an honors student is expected to prepare an honors thesis for a bachelor of arts degree with distinction.

Graduate Work. The Department of History offers the advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy. For details of these programs, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The minimum requirement for a major in history is 32 credit hours. This requirement must include the following:

6 credit hours in United States or Canadian history.

6 credit hours in European history (including British history).

6 credit hours in either Latin American, Asian or African history.

6 credit hours in the pre-1800 period.

HIST 250 The Historian’s Craft in the sophomore year or the semester after declaring history as a major.

HIST 450 Capstone Seminar in the senior year

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required:

1. To maintain and assemble a portfolio to include three examples of written work. The undergraduate adviser will inform students of the required contents, deadlines, and procedures.

2. In their senior year, to complete an exit survey or participate in an exit interview. The undergraduate adviser will inform students of the scheduling and format of this assessment activity.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

The Department of History accepts no more than 3 hours of credit taken Pass/No Pass for either a major or minor. This provision excludes HIST 398, which can only be taken Pass/No Pass.

Course Level Requirement

18 credit hours at the 300 and/or 400 level.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

18 hours including 6 hours in courses numbered 300 and above.

Integrated Science Program

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Integrated Science Program (Non-degree seeking)

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking only

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Dann Husmann

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Associate Dean Dann Husmann, 103 Agricultural Hall

Many students are unsure of which degree program to choose when entering the university. In fact, over half of all students entering UNL change their degree program at least once. The following program is available for students not yet ready to make the decision.

Integrated Science

The courses listed below compose a non-degree program entitled Integrated Science. The program is designed for students who are interested in a bachelor of science degree in the applied life sciences, agricultural sciences, natural resource sciences, or social sciences offered in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, but are uncertain about a specific degree program. Such students will receive individualized advising and mentoring from a faculty member and be encouraged to participate in clubs and other pre-professional activities to help them decide which career path is right for them.

This list of suggested courses for the first semester should provide the student maximum flexibility while ensuring that courses contribute to any of the degree programs within the College as well as most programs in other colleges. During the first semester, students should contact Associate Dean Dann Husmann to identify an appropriate adviser(s) in a degree program(s) of their area of interest to plan appropriate courses for subsequent semesters. Students may be in the program for two years (62 credit hours). Students may declare a degree program at any time, but must declare a degree program at the completion of 62 hours.

Semester 1 Hours

ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 or JOUR 200 3

NRES 103/AGRI 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

MATH 101, MATH 102, MATH 104 or MATH 106 2-5

Comprehensive elective 3

Total 15

Options:

If interested in Natural Resources and Environmental Science:

NRES 101 Natural Resources Orientation (1 cr)

If interested in Economics:

AECN 141 for humanities or social science

If interested in physical sciences:

PHYS 141, PHYS 211/ PHYS 221 or MSYM 109 for BIOS 101/ BIOS 101L

If math placement exam MATH 106:

Substitute STAT 218 (3 cr)

To learn about a particular degree program substitute humanities or social science with an entry-level course in one of the College disciplines.

Interior Design

COLLEGE: Architecture

MAJOR: Interior Design

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Design

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISERS: Betsy Gabb (pre-interior design); Assigned Faculty (interior design)

DESCRIPTION

Program Director: Betsy Gabb, 232 Architecture Hall

Professor: Gabb

Associate Professor: Hinchman

Assistant Professors: Allisma, Ellsworth-Bahe

Chief Advisers: Pre-Interior Design: Betsy Gabb (bgabb1@unl.edu); Interior Design: Assigned Faculty

The College of Architecture also administers the interior design program. The four-year interior design program consists of a two-year pre-interior design program and a subsequent two-year bachelor of science in design (BSD-Interior Design) major. After completing a two-year curriculum in pre-interior design, students apply for admission into the College of Architecture’s interior design program. This interior design program is fully accredited by the Council Interior Design Accreditation (CIDA). The interior design program also offers a post-professional MS degree through the Graduate College. The graduate degree is also available through Extended Education and Outreach.

This four-year, undergraduate program is for the student interested in becoming a professional interior designer. The professional interior designer is a person qualified by education, experience, and examination to 1) identify, research, and creatively explore issues related to the quality of the interior environment; 2) perform design services in interior spaces, including programming, design analysis, space planning and aesthetics, using specialized knowledge of interior construction, building systems and components, building codes, equipment materials and furnishings; and 3) prepare drawings and documents describing the design of interior spaces in order to enhance and protect the health, safety, and welfare of the public.

Upon successful completion of two years of pre-interior design studies and admission to the interior design program, students in the interior design program may enroll in the curriculum which leads to a bachelor of science in design (BSD-Interior Design) degree.

ADMISSION

Admission to the 2-Year Bachelor of Science in Design Program–Interior Design

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the interior design program, applicants must:

1. Be enrolled in the College of Architecture

2. Be in good scholastic standing

3. Have completed the appropriate 1st and 2nd year pre-architecture or pre-interior design program of study

Third Year Admission Process

1. An application for admission may be completed by filling out the online application. The program receives applications once a year in early February.

2. Applicants must submit a portfolio conforming to the defined criteria for the program applied for by the date posted at the completion of the spring semester.

3. Any applicant who has previously applied for admission and has not been accepted or who fails to enroll in the professional program in architecture or the interior design program after an acceptance must reapply in the regular manner. Students may apply for admission to the interior design program only three times.

Evaluation

The faculty of the interior design program will carefully evaluate the applications for admission. The committee considers three elements in their evaluation: cumulative grade point average, a weighted grade point average, and the portfolio of student work. The weighted grade point average gives additional value to the applicant’s achievement in the required ARCH or IDES prefix course or transfer equivalents in the pre-professional curriculum.

Selection

Admission to the interior design program will be awarded to applicants who show the greatest professional potential and have demonstrated scholastic achievement. The faculty reserves the right to not fill all available spaces in the professional program in the interior design program if determined that the remaining applicants have not performed at an acceptable level.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Pre-Interior Design Curriculum

The pre-interior design curriculum begins with a two-year basic design core. This core introduces students to visual literacy and design fundamentals. The pre-interior design program is followed by two years of interior design instruction leading to a bachelor of science in design–interior design. The interior design program is fully accredited by the Council for Interior Design Accreditation (formerly FIDER).

The College of Architecture, and all four years of the interior design program, are located in Lincoln. However, we do offer the option to do the first two years of the program at UNO. After successfully completing the prescribed pre-interior design program at UNO, students may transfer to UNL and apply for admission to the third year of study in the professional program of the Interior Design Program. For more information about courses at UNO, or transferring from UNO to UNL, please contact Dr. Betsy Gabb at 402-472-9245 (UNL) or 402-554-2934 (UNO).

PRE-INTERIOR DESIGN: First Year, First Semester

AHIS 102 Intro to Art History & Criticism II (ACE 7) 3

IDES 106 Intro to Design 3

IDES 140A Visual Literacy Lab: Analysis &/or Composition (ACE 2) 2

IDES 140B Visual Literacy Lab: Perceptual Drawing (ACE 2) 2

English Composition Elective: ENGL 150 Writing: Rhetoric as Inquiry or ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument (ACE 1) 3

ACE 6 Elective 3

Total 16

PRE-INTERIOR DESIGN: First Year, Second Semester

IDES 141A Visual Literacy Lab: Color (ACE 2) 2

IDES 141B Visual Literacy Lab: Speculative Drawing (ACE 2) 2

IDES 143 Visual Literacy: Art & Design 2

IDES 223 Computer Applications in Design 3

MATH Elective: MATH 203 Contemporary Mathematics or STAT 218 Intro to Statistics (ACE 3) 3

English Composition Elective: ENGL 150 Writing: Rhetoric as Inquiry or ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument (ACE 1) 3

Total 15

PRE-INTERIOR DESIGN: Second Year, First Semester

ARCH 240 Architecture History & Theory I (ACE 5) 3

IDES 210 Fundamentals of Design 5

Communication Elective: COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication or COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication (ACE 2) 3

ACE 8 Elective 3

ACE 9 Elective 3

Total 17

PRE-INTERIOR DESIGN: Second Year, Second Semester

ARCH 241 Architecture History & Theory II (ACE 7) 3

IDES 211 Elements of Architecture & Interior Design 5

IDES 300 Interior Design–Materials 3

Natural Sciences Elective (ACE 4) 4

Total 15

INTERIOR DESIGN: Third Year, First Semester

IDES 301 Material Applications 3

IDES 350 Interior Design Studio I 5

IDES 433 Interior Construction Documents 3

IDES 445 History of Interiors & Designed Objects (ACE 5 or 7) 3

Total 14

INTERIOR DESIGN: Third Year, Second Semester

ARCH 334 Building Environmental Technical Systems II 3

IDES 351 Interior Design Studio II 5

Professional Elective 3

Open Elective 4

Total 15

INTERIOR DESIGN: Summer Session (Between 3rd & 4th Year)

IDES 491 Selected Topics in Interior Design: Interior Design Internship 3

INTERIOR DESIGN: Fourth Year, First Semester

IDES 318 Professional Practices for Interior Design 3

IDES 450 Interior Design Studio 3 5

Behavior Elective: ARCH 456 Behavioral & Social Factors in Environmental Design or ARCH 457 Housing Issues in Contemporary Society or ARCH 458 The Changing Workplace 3

Open Elective 4

Total 15

INTERIOR DESIGN: Fourth Year, Second Semester

IDES 451 Interior Design Studio 4 5

Professional History Elective 3

Professional Elective 3

Open Elective 3

Total 14

Total for Graduation 120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Minimum Grades

Students must earn at least a C (2.0) in all courses with an ARCH, IDES, or LARC prefix to earn credit toward their degree. Students will be required to retake all core required courses with a grade of C- or below, but will not be required to repeat courses that were taken as electives.

Pass/No Pass Limits

None of the required classes offered in the professional program are offered Pass/No Pass, but a maximum of 12 Pass/No Pass credit hours of humanities, social sciences, or open electives may be taken from departments outside the College of Architecture.

Courses taken outside the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs to fulfill the upper level outside elective requirement at the 800 level or 900 level, with or without a 400-level counterpart, in a minor, collateral, or supporting area of work, can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis.

GPA Requirements

Pre-Professional Program, Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Interior Design Manufacturing Methods & Processes

Students in the first year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average at or above 2.0. The standard rises to a grade point average of 2.6 in the second year. Admission into the third year of both programs requires a cumulative grade point average of 2.6. The College places students who fail to meet these standards on academic probation.

Third and Fourth Year, Interior Design and Landscape Architecture

Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to maintain a 2.6 cumulative grade point average to remain in good academic standing. The program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Product Design Minor

Program Director and Chief Adviser: Betsy Gabb, 232 Architecture Hall

Faculty: Allisma, Bicak, Ellsworth-Bahe, Hinchman, Saroka, Day (architecture), Ford (architecture), Hardy (architecture), Hemsath (architecture), Hoistad (architecture) D. Jones (engineering), Pinnell (art)

Product Design

The common core of courses shared by students in the College of Architecture (interior design, architecture, landscape architecture) provides students with an understanding of the design and fabrication process at a range of scales. The minor in product design provides an opportunity to explore design at a smaller, yet related scale. It allows students to develop academic strengths that will prepare them for advanced study and careers in the design of objects that people interact with on a personal level, of a size and function related to human dimensions. This includes furniture and a variety of manufactured objects.

The minor is available to students in interior design, architecture, landscape architecture, and art.

Requirements for the Minor (18 credits)

A minimum of 12 hours of course work to include the following:

Hours

GRPH 221 Building Graphic Design 3

IDES 301 Material Applications 3

IDES 417 Product Design 3

IMSE 275 Intro to Manufacturing Processes 3

6 credits of additional course work to be selected from:

Hours

ARCH 418 Fabrication & Construction Team 1-6

ARCH 516 Modern Craft 3

ARCH 526 Digital Fabrication 3

IDES 482 Advanced Color Theory 3

IDES 484 Material Culture: The Social Life of Things 3

IDES 491 Selected Topics in Interior Design: Branding 3

IDES Signage & Wayfinding (course to be developed) 3

MECH 370 Manufacturing Methods & Processes 3

International Agriculture & Natural Resources Minor

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: International Agriculture & Natural Resources (Minor only)

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 12 or 18

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Professor Ousmane Youm, 103 Agricultural Hall

Professors: Brink, Husmann, Francis, Mason, Powell, Schinstock, Peterson, Weller, Fulginiti

Associate Professor: Yiannaka

Assistant Professor: Thomas

Professor of Practice: Hardin

Undergraduate Adviser: Swartz

The International Agriculture and Natural Resources minor is designed for students who seek a broad understanding of the nature and role of agriculture and natural resources in the integrated world economy and of the implications of world events for agriculture and natural resources in both the United States and abroad. The minor adds a global perspective to professional preparation. It is for students who desire a broad understanding of international trade and development issues as well as for those seeking employment in business firms or government agencies with international operations or interests.

Students typically build their minor program from courses organized around three areas: 1) a group of international courses in CASNR; 2) complimentary international courses offered in arts and sciences, and business administration; and 3) optional but highly recommended modern language instruction or experience as a base for building international communications skills. Two minor plans are available. One plan requires 12 credits in courses at or above the 300 level while the other plan requires 18 credits, including a minimum of 6 credits in courses at or above the 300 level.

12-Credit-Hour Plan

Overall 12 credits in approved courses* at or above the 300 level
Minimum 3 credits in CASNR courses other than Independent Study, AGRI 310 or NRES 315
Maximum 6 credits from any one department or program
Maximum 6 credits of modern languages at or above the 200 level
Maximum 3 credits of Independent Study and AGRI 310 or NRES 315 combined

18-Credit-Hour Plan

Overall 18 credits in approved courses*
Minimum 6 credits in CASNR courses
Minimum 6 credits in courses at or above the 300 level
Maximum 9 credits from any one department or program
Maximum 6 credits of modern languages at or above the 200 level
Maximum 3 credits of Independent Study
Maximum 3 credits of AGRI 310 or NRES 315

A student in consultation with the academic adviser and a minor adviser (chosen from those above) prepares a list of courses on the CASNR Application for Minor form, obtains the appropriate signatures and submits the minor form to the minor coordinator prior to deadline for submitting the application for graduation. While students may apply during their senior year, planning for the minor and application are recommended earlier in order to get maximum benefit from the minor.

Upon approval, the minor program will be forwarded to the University Registrar, with a copy supplied to the student’s college. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript upon graduation. Students interested in pursuing an International Agriculture and Natural Resources minor should contact the minor coordinator or the CASNR Dean’s Office, 103 Agricultural Hall.

Jewish Studies Minor

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Jewish Studies (Minor only)

DEGREES OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Naomi Leite

DESCRIPTION

Director: Jean Cahan, 324 Seaton Hall

Assistant Director and Chief Adviser: Naomi Leite, 324 Seaton Hall

Faculty: Burnett (classics and religious studies), Cahan (philosophy and political science), Crawford (classics and religious studies), Der Matossian (history), Gross (Judaic studies), Kohen (political science), Leite (anthropology), Steinacher (history), Turner (classics and religious studies)

Jewish Studies is an interdisciplinary program housed in the Norman and Bernice Harris Center for Judaic Studies, 324 Seaton Hall. The minor in Jewish Studies is for students of diverse disciplinary backgrounds who are interested in Jewish cultures and peoples, past and present; the ways in which Judaism and other religious traditions have influenced each other, Near Eastern and Middle Eastern history and politics; and/or the origins and effects of anti-Semitism and other forms of discrimination. Courses in Jewish Studies are offered by cooperating faculty in departments in the College of Arts and Sciences including: anthropology, classics, English, history, modern languages and literatures, philosophy, political science, psychology, religious studies, and sociology. Language courses in Biblical Hebrew are available. Students minoring in Jewish Studies are eligible for several scholarships awarded by the Harris Center for Judaic Studies.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Program Advising. Students are encouraged to meet with the Jewish Studies program adviser as early as possible to discuss their intention to pursue the minor. Courses with significant Jewish Studies content that are not listed below may be eligible for approval as electives.

18 hours taken from:

a. 2 core courses: HIST 219 Intro to Jewish History and JUDS 350 Literature of Judaism

b. 12 hrs of electives in any combination chosen from List 1 and List 2

Credits earned using the Pass/No Pass option do not count toward this minor.

Elective Courses

List 1 – Jewish Studies

JUDS 205 Intro to the Hebrew Bible/Old Testament

JUDS 217 Israel: The Holy Land

JUDS 308 Dead Sea Scrolls

JUDS 331 Ancient Israel

JUDS 332 Jews in the Middle Ages

JUDS 333 Jews in the Modern World

JUDS 340 Women in the Biblical World

JUDS 398 Special Topics in Judaic Studies

JUDS 406 Second Temple Judaism

List 2 – Other Departments

CLAS 409. Religion of Late Western Antiquity

ENGL 245J Jewish American Fiction

ENGL 341 The Bible as Literature

HEBR 101 Elementary Biblical Hebrew I

HEBR 102 Elementary Biblical Hebrew II

HEBR 301 Biblical Hebrew Prose

HEBR 302 Biblical Hebrew Poetry

HIST 209 Ancient Greece

HIST 339 The Holocaust

MODL 232 Jewish Idea in Modern Literature

PHIL 116 Philosophy & Religious Belief

PHIL 223 Intro to the Philosophy of History

PHIL 265 Philosophy of Religion

PHIL 332 Spinoza

POLS 477 Israel & the Middle East

SOCI 217 Nationality & Race Relations

SOCI 452 Sociology of Religion

Journalism

COLLEGE: Journalism & Mass Communications

MAJOR: Journalism

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Journalism

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Michael Goff

DESCRIPTION

Professors: Bender, Berens, Botts (emeritus), Kebbel, Norton (emeritus), Starita, Tuck (emeritus)

Associate Professors: Anderson, Bullard, Frazell (emeritus), Kimbrough, Neal (emeritus), Pagel (emeritus), Quinlan, Thorson, Weber

Assistant Professor: Winter

Professor of Practice: Waite

The College of Journalism and Mass Communications offers three majors: broadcasting, journalism, and the combined area of advertising and public relations.

The journalism curriculum, combined from broadcasting and traditional print journalism programs, is built on intensive reporting and writing. All students are required to take courses in reporting and writing, copy editing, visual literacy, mass media law, contemporary issues in mass media and multimedia journalism. Elective choices include courses in magazine writing, depth reporting, feature writing, sports writing, business writing, science writing, photography, design, broadcast news writing, videography and advanced editing. Students may also choose an emphasis in broadcast production, in which they will enroll in courses in audio and video production.

Many of the journalism faculty members have extensive industry experience at media organizations such as The Wall Street Journal, The Miami Herald, The Detroit News, ABC News and The New York Times. The faculty continues to be connected to the industry, and its members are actively involved in professional media organizations. Students, likewise, are encouraged to further their professional goals through participation in student organizations such as the Alpha Epsilon Rho national broadcasting society, the Society of Professional Journalists, the Radio Television Digital News Association and the American Copy Editors Association.

Faculty members prepare students for the job market by combining class work with actual experience. The primary college outlet for student journalism is NewsNetNebraska, the college’s student-produced website. In addition, students have the opportunity to work on the Star City News, a weekly television news broadcast; KRNU, a professionally managed FM radio station; and regularly scheduled magazines, which publish the work of depth reporting and photography students.

The journalism program places a great deal of importance on professional internships, and students in recent years have worked at such media organizations as ABC News, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The Dallas Morning News, Fox News, The Omaha World-Herald, The Des Moines Register, The Norfolk Daily News and The St. Paul Pioneer Press, as well as numerous other newspapers and local television stations. The college also has partnerships with two media organizations that offer paid internships during the school year in Lincoln.

The Omaha World-Herald, Nebraska’s largest newspaper, works with the college to teach a course called “The Real World” in which World-Herald staff members offer students insight into working for a newspaper. Each semester the World-Herald chooses four students to be “fellows,” and they work in the newspaper’s Lincoln bureau.

Additionally, journalism students achieve national recognition by successfully competing in such programs as the Hearst Journalism Awards, Sigma Delta Chi Awards, the Dow Jones News Fund editing internship program, the Robert F. Kennedy Journalism Awards and the Society of Professional Journalists’ Mark of Excellence Awards.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

The courses required for a 38-hour major in journalism are as follows:

JOMC 101, JOMC 162, JOMC 163, JOMC 164, JOMC 165, JOUR 201, JOUR 202, JOUR 302, JOUR 450, JOMC 486, JOMC 487; and 3 hours from BRDC 369, BRDC 370, BRDC 372, JOUR 303, and either JOUR 305 or a 400-level reporting course; and 6 elective hours from the college.

Students may complete two majors in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications by completing all requirements for each major; however, the second major in the college will not take the place of a concentration or any of the 80 hours required outside the college.

Landscape Architecture

COLLEGE: College of Architecture

MAJOR: Landscape Architecture

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Design (BSD) (end of two two-year segments); Professional Bachelor of Landscape Architecture (BLA) (end of the fifth year)

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 for BSD; 163 for BSD & BLA

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Landscape Architecture

CHIEF ADVISER: Kim Wilson

DESCRIPTION

Program Director: Kim Wilson, 302 Architecture Hall

Professors: Day, Hoistad, Sutton, Wilson

Associate Professor: Rodie

Assistant Professor: Betnar, Tang, Thomas

Chief Adviser: Kim Wilson, kwilson4@unl.edu

The primary responsibility of the landscape architecture profession is the design and stewardship of the built and natural environments. Therefore, landscape architects must be able to understand the process of nature and the impact human settlement has on ecosystems. This requires professionals to manage storm water, select appropriate plant material, and anticipate human impact all with an eye on a sustainable future.

The landscape architecture program seeks to increase students’ capacity for critical thinking, collaborative skills, and creative potential in service to the environment and humanity. Specifically, the curriculum provides the background and means for the student to:

1. Analyze and understand the relationship between humanity and the natural world it inhabits;

2. Creatively explore the potential of interventions into the developed and underdeveloped environments;

3. Search out new challenges and contribute to solutions through research and experimentation; and

4. Participate in the community that makes decisions affecting the physical environment.

General

The landscape architecture program is a five-year course of study that has been subdivided into a two-year pre-professional, two-year para-professional, and a one-year professional degree unit. Students receive a bachelor of science in design (BSD) at the end of the two two-year segments and a professional bachelor of landscape architecture (BLA) at the end of the fifth year. At the end of the first two year pre-professional segment, students are required to apply for admission into the professional segment of the curriculum. This review involves an evaluation of the students academic record and a portfolio of their work during the preprofessional studies. The landscape architecture program is a candidate program for accreditation. It is anticipated it will be granted for all students as soon as it is allowed under the rules of accreditation defined by the Landscape Architectural Accreditation Board (LAAB).

Students are required to take an array of courses in support of the core studio sequence in addition to the university’s general education courses. These courses include material in horticulture, architecture, planning, and engineering in addition to core landscape architecture classes. This curriculum exposes students to various issues facing the landscape architecture profession including plant material, soils, landscape ecology, construction issues, stormwater management, infrastructure and issues created by urbanism.

ADMISSION

Admission to the Landscape Architecture Program

After completion of the first two years of pre-landscape architecture studies, either within the College of Architecture or at another institution, students may apply for admission to the architecture program.

Pre-landscape architecture majors should apply for admission to the professional program in landscape architecture. Successful applicants will have their major changed from pre-landscape architecture to BSD-Landscape Architecture option.

Available teaching resources and space capacities limit enrollment to the third year of architectural studies; therefore enrollment limits are established each semester.

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the landscape architecture program, applicants must:

1. Be enrolled in the College of Architecture

2. Be in good scholastic standing

3. Have completed the 1st and 2nd year pre-landscape architecture program of study

Third-Year Admission Process

1. An application for admission may be completed by filling out the online application. The Program receives applications once a year in early February.

2. Applicants must submit a portfolio conforming to the defined criteria for the program applied for by the date posted at the completion of the spring semester.

3. Any applicant who has previously applied for admission and has not been accepted or who fails to enroll in the professional program in architecture after an acceptance must reapply in the regular manner. Students may apply for admission to the landscape architecture program only three times.

Evaluation

A faculty committee of the program will carefully evaluate the applications for admission. The committee considers three elements in their evaluation; cumulative grade point average, a weighted grade point average, and the portfolio of student work. The weighted grade point average gives additional value to the applicant’s achievement in the required LARC prefix course or transfer equivalents in the pre-professional curriculum.

Selection

Admission to the landscape architecture program will be awarded to applicants who show the greatest professional potential and have demonstrated scholastic achievement. The faculty reserves the right to not fill all available spaces in the professional program in landscape architecture if it determines that the remaining applicants have not performed at an acceptable level.

Admission to the 1-Year Bachelor of Landscape Architecture Program

Students from both inside and outside the program must apply to gain admission to the 1-year BLA degree program. Applications are available in October from the department office and are reviewed once a year in February.

All applications for admission are subject to approval of the faculty. Enrollment shall be limited by the teaching resources and space capacities of the program. An enrollment quota is established prior to each admissions cycle.

Students in the professional program are governed by the rules, procedures and policies established in the landscape architecture program. These are published in the Student Guide or by official notification by the faculty.

Minimum Entrance Requirements

To be considered for admission to the BLA Professional Program in Landscape Architecture, applicants must:

Have a 4-year degree from an accredited landscape program or its equivalent as determined by the program director
Present a portfolio of design work
Be in good scholastic standing
Have a B average or its equivalent in past academic programs

The faculty of the landscape architecture program require a minimum TOEFL score of 550 or 213 computer-based or 79-80 Internet-based score for all international student applicants whose first language is not English.

Evaluation

A portfolio of an applicant’s recent design work will be evaluated by the faculty of the landscape architecture program and is considered to be a very important part of the application review process, along with the applicant’s educational profile, letters of recommendation (required for outside applicants only), transcripts, and application form.

Selection

The limited number of spaces available each semester will be awarded to applicants who have displayed the highest abilities in a combination of scholastic achievement, design capability, and professional potential.

The Admissions Committee reserves the right to reject applicants who, in its opinion, have not reached an acceptable level of design proficiency.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Pre-Landscape Architecture Curriculum

The pre-landscape curriculum begins with a two-year basic design core. This core introduces students to visual literacy and design fundamentals. The pre-landscape architecture program is followed by two years of focused landscape architecture instruction leading to a bachelor of science in design. After receipt of the bachelors degree, students may continue with one additional year of study, leading to a professional bachelor of landscape architecture degree. The professional bachelor of landscape architecture degree is the degree accredited by the Landscape Architectural Accreditation Board (LAAB). UNL’s BLA Program currently has “candidacy” accreditation status from LAAB.

The College of Architecture, and all five years of the architecture program, are located in Lincoln. However, we do offer the option to do the first two years of the program at UNO. After successfully completing the prescribed pre-landscape architecture program at UNO, students may transfer to UNL and apply for admission to the third year of study in the professional program of the College of Architecture.

For more information about courses at UNO, or transferring from UNO to UNL, please contact us.

PRE-LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: First Year, First Semester

LARC 101 Survey of Landscape Architecture: Approach, Process, & Practice 2

LARC 140A Visual Literacy Lab: Analysis &/or Composition (ACE 2) 2

LARC 140B Visual Literacy Lab: Perceptual Drawing (ACE 2) 2

AGRO 131 Plant Science (3 cr) & HORT 133 Horticultural Plant Science Lab (1 cr) (ACE 4) 4

ENGL Composition Elective (ACE 1) 3

Communication Elective: COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication or COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication (ACE 2) 3

Total 16

PRE-LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: First Year, Second Semester

LARC 141A Visual Literacy Lab: Color (ACE 2) 2

LARC 141B Visual Literacy Lab: Speculative Drawing (ACE 2) 2

LARC 143 Visual Literacy: Art & Design 2

LARC 223 Computer Applications in Design 3

LARC 200 Landscape & Environmental Appreciation (ACE 7 or 9) 3

MATH Elective: MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I or STAT 218 Intro to Statistics (ACE 3) 3-5

Total 15-17

PRE-LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Second Year, First Semester

LARC 210 Fundamentals of Design 5

LARC 240 Architecture History & Theory I (ACE 5) 3

LARC 212 Landscape Plants I 3

HORT 153 Soil Resources 4

Total 15

PRE-LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Second Year, Second Semester

LARC 211 Design Studio I: Fundamental Methods of Design Process 5

LARC 230 Site Systems I: Materiality in Landscape Architecture 3

LARC 213 Landscape Plants II 3

ENGL Composition Elective (ACE 1) 3

Total 14

LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Third Year, First Semester

LARC 310 Design Studio I: Site Design 5

LARC 330 Site Systems II: Grading & Stormwater Management 3

LARC 340 History & Theory in Contemporary Landscape Architecture 3

HORT 467 Planting Design 2

Elective (Open) 2

Total 15

LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Third Year, Second Semester

LARC 311 Design Studio II: Site & Building 5

LARC 331 Site Systems III: Layout, Utilities, & Construction Documentation 3

CIVE 353 Hydrology 3

CRPL 430 GIS in Environmental Planning 3

Total 14

LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Fourth Year, First Semester

LARC 410 Design Studio III: Community Planning & Design 5

CRPL 400 Intro to Planning 3

LARC 453 Urban Soil Properties & Management 3

BIOS 220 Principles of Ecology 3

Elective (ACE 7 or 9) 3

Total 17

LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Fourth Year, Second Semester

LARC 411 Design Studio IV: Urban Design 5

LARC 461 Urbanism 3

GEOG 406 Spatial & Environmental Influences in Social Systems or GEOG 361 Urban Geography 3

Elective (ACE 6) 3

Total 14

Total for Graduation 120

BACHELOR OF LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Fifth Year, Summer

LARC 495 Internship or Study Abroad Opportunity 2

BACHELOR OF LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Fifth Year, First Semester

LARC 412 Design Studio V: Ecological Planning & Design 5

LARC 480 Professional Practice 3

LARC 486 Research Methods 3

LARC 487 Intro to Landscape Ecology 3

Total 14

BACHELOR OF LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE: Fifth Year, Second Semester

LARC 413 Capstone Studio 5

LARC 497 Selected Topics in Landscape Architecture: Professional Elective 3

LARC 497 Selected Topics in Landscape Architecture: Professional Elective 3

LARC 497 Selected Topics in Landscape Architecture: Professional Elective 3

Total 14

Total for Graduation 150

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Minimum Grades

Students must earn at least a C (2.0) in all courses with an ARCH, IDES, or LARC prefix to earn credit toward their degree. Students will be required to retake all core required courses with a grade of C- or below, but will not be required to repeat courses that were taken as electives.

Pass/No Pass Limits

None of the required classes offered in the professional program are offered Pass/No Pass, but a maximum of 12 Pass/No Pass credit hours of humanities, social sciences, or open electives may be taken from departments outside the College of Architecture.

Courses taken outside the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs to fulfill the upper level outside elective requirement at the 800 level or 900 level, with or without a 400-level counterpart, in a minor, collateral, or supporting area of work, can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis.

GPA Requirements

Pre-Professional Program, Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Interior Design

Students in the first year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average at or above 2.0. The standard rises to a grade point average of 2.6 in the second year. Admission into the third year of both programs requires a cumulative grade point average of 2.6. The College places students who fail to meet these standards on academic probation.

Third and Fourth Year, Interior Design and Landscape Architecture

Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to maintain a 2.6 cumulative grade point average to remain in good academic standing. The Program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Minors

The landscape architecture minor is administered through the College of Architecture’s landscape architecture program.

The minor in landscape architecture is designed to provide a basic understanding of the nature of the profession of landscape architecture. Knowledge of landscape architecture history, theory, and context provides a useful addition to a student in any of the University disciplines.

The minor is open to all UNL students. Entrance to the minor is by application, grade review,and permission of the program director, Kim L. Wilson. Contact Leslie Brehm, admissions coordinator (232 Architecture Hall West, 402-472-4065, lbrehm2@unl.edu) for the application.

Hours

Required Courses 18

ARCH 240 Architecture History & Theory I 3

CRPL 400 Intro to Planning 3

LARC 101 Survey of Landscape Architecture: Approach, Process, & Practice 2

LARC 200 Landscape & Environmental Appreciation 3

LARC 340 History & Theory in Contemporary Landscape Architecture 3

LARC 461 Urbanism 3

LARC 498 Topics in Landscape Architecture 1

Language Arts Education (7-12)

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Teaching, Learning & Teacher Education

PROGRAM: Language Arts Education (7-12)

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Beverly Jensen

DESCRIPTION

Students who complete this field endorsement are endorsed to teach English and direct curricular and co-curricular activities in composition/language, literature, speech, theatre, mass communication, journalism, and reading in grades 7 through 12.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the curriculum and these must be successfully completed in order to be certified in the teaching profession. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Felony and Misdemeanor Conviction” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements (or majors) are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their adviser, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30

ACE 1. ENGL 254 (Endorsement Requirement) 3

ACE 2. COMM 109 or COMM 209 or COMM 210 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 3. 3

ACE 4. 3

ACE 5. British Literature (Endorsement Requirement) 3

ACE 6. EDPS 251 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 7. ENGL 252 (Endorsement Requirement) 3

ACE 8. TEAC 331 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 9. TEAC 330 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 10. TEAC 403B (Professional Education Requirement) 3

Pre-Professional Education Requirements 4

EDPS 297 1

TEAC 259 3

Language Arts 7-12 Endorsement Requirements 61

COMM 200, COMM 201, COMM 212, COMM 412 (3 hrs ea) 12

ENGL 357 3

ENGL 377. 3

ENGL 322B or ENGL 427B, D, E, or ENGL 478 or TEAC 413A, M 3

*ENGL (American Literature) 3

*ENGL (Non-traditional Cultural Perspective) 3

JOMC 101 3

JOUR 201 & JOUR 467 6

JOUR 202 4

TEAC 411 & TEAC 441 6

TEAC 438 3

TEAC 439 3

THEA 114, THEA 201, THEA 202 (3 hrs ea) 9

Professional Education Requirements 24

TEAC 451N 3

TEAC 452N 3

TEAC 397N 3

*EDPS 457 3

SPED 401B 3

TEAC 497N 9

Electives 1

Total Hours 120

* These courses are also approved ACE courses and together with the 30 hours of ACE required courses meet the additional ACE/General Education requirements for secondary education students.

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Additional ACE Course Work for Secondary Education

Secondary education students need additional ACE courses for a total of 40 hours to meet the requirements for the Nebraska Department of Education. One of the ACE courses must be an approved speech course. At least two of the ACE courses must be at the 300/400 level. Once again, there may be required courses within your program that will also satisfy these additional ACE requirements. Contact your adviser.

ADMISSION

All education programs have a competitive admission process. At some point in time, after meeting specific education requirements, all students must formally apply to their particular education program.

Pre-Education Status

All newly admitted students who are pursuing a teacher preparation program are classified as pre-education students until admitted to a specific Teacher Education Program.

Admission to a Teacher Education Program (TEP)

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission into a teacher education program. Admission to the advanced phases of teacher education is selective and, in some endorsements, highly competitive. Students must satisfy the following requirements in order to be eligible to apply to the Teacher Education Program:

1. A minimum 2.5 cumulative GPA.

2. Must have earned a minimum of 42 credit hours of college credit.

3. Completion and submission of the Teacher Education Program Application Form.

4. Completion of TEAC 331 and EDPS 251 or an approved transfer course, (must be taken prior to or be in progress, the semester in which you apply to the TEP) with a 2.5 cumulative average in the two classes, and no grade lower than C; TEAC 259 (must also be taken prior to or be in progress, the semester in which you apply to the TEP).

5. Documentation of proficiency in reading, writing, and mathematics through successful completion of the Praxis I, Pre-Professional Skills Test (PPST), a basic skills examination that meets the Nebraska Department of Education competency requirement.

6. Completion of one course in communication studies selected from COMM 109, COMM 205, COMM 209, COMM 210, or COMM 286, or approved substitute.

7. Faculty recommendations.

8. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form (PPF) as well as the completion of a formal criminal history review, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required).

9. Specific programs may have particular learning outcomes that students must address as part of the application process.

Admission to Student Teaching

All students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate are required to student teach. Students who plan to student teach in the fall semester must complete the student teaching application form and submit it by the preceding March 1 to the Director of Field Experiences in 116 Henzlik Hall; students planning to student teach in the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1. The basic program for student teaching provides for a full-day experience for an entire semester. Admission to student teaching requires the following:

1. Matriculation in a teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences, the Graduate College, or dual matriculation in the College of Education and Human Sciences and another college.

2. Admission to a specific teacher education program.

3. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.5.

4. Minimum grade point average of 2.5 in the endorsement area with no grade below C.

5. A minimum grade point average of 2.5 in pre-professional and professional education courses and no grade below C in pre-professional education courses and no grade below a C+ in professional education courses.

6. All endorsement, pre-professional and professional education course work must be completed prior to student teaching. If necessary, no more than 6 hours of general education (ACE) or elective classes can be completed after the student teaching experience.

7. No additional course work can be taken during the student teaching semester unless prior approval is obtained from the Certification Officer, the Director of Field Experiences, or the Department Chair that oversees the program.

8. Completion of a second criminal history check that will be conducted, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required). For more information, contact the Director of Field Experiences or your adviser.

MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

80% of these endorsement requirements must be completed prior to enrolling in your first professional methods course.

Endorsement Requirements

Reading Courses

TEAC 411 Reading Processes & Practices

TEAC 441 Content Area Reading, Grades 4-12

Writing Courses

ENGL 357 Composition Theory & Practice

Select two courses from the following:

**ENGL 252, ENGL 253, ENGL 254, ENGL 352, ENGL 353, ENGL 354

UNL English courses with a middle digit of 5 are considered writing courses.

Language Courses

TEAC 438 Linguistics for the Classroom School Teacher

Select one course from the following:

ENGL 322B Linguistics & Society

ENGL 427B, D, E Applications of Linguistics

ENGL 478/878 Electronic Text

TEAC 413A/813A Second Language Acquisition

TEAC 413M/813M Teaching ELL in the Content Areas

Literature Courses

ENGL 377 Reading Theory & Practice

TEAC 439 Literature for Adolescents

British Literature *pre-1800

Select one course from the following:

ENGL 230 English Authors to 1800*

ENGL 230A Shakespeare*

ENGL 330E Chaucer, Shakespeare, Milton*

ENGL 362 Intro to Medieval Literature*

ENGL 363 Intro to Renaissance Literature*

ENGL 364 Intro to Restoration & 18th Century Literature*

ENGL 405A 19th Century British Novel*

ENGL 430A Shakespeare I*

ENGL 462 Survey of Medieval Literature*

ENGL 464 British Literature, 1660-1800*

**American Literature

Select one course from the following:

ENGL 211 Literature of Place

ENGL 260 American Literature before 1865

ENGL 261 American Literature since 1865

ENGL 332A Mark Twain

ENGL 334 American Literary Traditions

ENGL 402 Poetry

ENGL 403 American Short Story

ENGL 405M American Novel I

ENGL 405N American Novel II

ENGL 432 American Authors to 1900

ENGL 433 American Authors Since 1900

**Literature with Nontraditional Cultural Perspectives

Select one course from the following:

ENGL 212 Intro to Lesbian & Gay Literature

ENGL 215 Intro to Women’s Literature

ENGL 244 African-American Literature since 1865

ENGL 244A Intro to African Literature

ENGL 244E African-American Literature before 1865

ENGL 245N Intro to Native American Literature

ENGL 315A Survey of Women’s Literature

ENGL 315B Women in Popular Culture

ENGL 344B Black Women Authors

ENGL 345D Chicana &/or Chicano Literature

ENGL 345N Native American Women Writers

ENGL 401K Gay & Lesbian Drama

ENGL 414 Women’s Literature

ENGL 414B Modern & Contemporary Women Writers

ENGL 445 Ethnic Literature

ENGL 445K Topics in African Literature

ENGL 445N Topics in Native American Literature

Speech

COMM 200 Communication, Collaboration, & Community: Intro

COMM 201 Intro to Research Methods Communication Studies

COMM 212 Debate

COMM 412 Directing Forensics

Dramatic Arts

THEA 114 Basic Acting Techniques I

THEA 201 Technical Theatre Practice

THEA 202 Play Direction I

Journalism and Mass Media

JOMC 101 Principles of Mass Media

JOUR 201 Editing I

**JOUR 202 Reporting I

JOUR 467 School Publications

Pre-Professional Education Requirements

With the exception of EDPS 297 and TEAC 330, students must complete the following before applying to their Teacher Education Program (TEP).

**EDPS 251

EDPS 297

TEAC 259

**TEAC 331

**COMM 109, COMM 205, **COMM 209, **COMM 210, or COMM 286, or an approved speech class

**TEAC 330

Professional Education

Students must be admitted into this Teacher Education Program before enrolling in these courses.

TEAC 397, TEAC 451, TEAC 452, **EDPS 457, SPED 401B

Student Teaching: **TEAC 403B, TEAC 497

** These courses also meet ACE requirements. See your adviser.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their endorsement and education courses with no grade lower than a C in their pre-professional courses and no grade lower than a C+ in their professional education courses.

Transfer Grades

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Pass/No Pass Grade Option–for Education Students

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of no pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. Only one course in each subject endorsement may be taken P/N; two courses in a field endorsement may be taken P/N.

2. Pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken P/N unless a class already has a P/N designation.

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course may be taken P/N.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a P/N only basis.

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

Beyond Classroom Grades

In all fields of study, students are expected to attain certain grades and other academic accomplishments in the classroom. In addition to this, students preparing themselves to be teachers, counselors and for other careers in education, are also reviewed to evaluate their ability to successfully and safely interact with children, parents, potential educational employers, and the community-at-large, whose interest in the education of its children often exceeds its concern for other community and governmental services.

OTHER

Student Teaching Placement

The Office of Field Experiences is responsible for the placement of student teachers. Several factors are considered in determining the district and school to which an individual is assigned. The availability of a cooperating teacher and supervisor who meet the requirements established by the Nebraska Department of Education and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are among those factors. Opportunities to student teach out-of-state are limited and those placements are becoming increasingly difficult. All requests to student teach outside of the immediate Lincoln area must be individually reviewed and approved by the Director of Field Experiences.

Removal from Student Teaching

Students participating in practicum or student teaching assignments may be removed from their assigned schools if their conduct suggests a lack of professional commitment and presents a negative influence on the well-being or learning of the students in the schools. Specific guidelines that all student teachers are to follow can be found in The Student Teaching Experience: A Handbook for the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. If such a problem occurs, at the request of the cooperating teacher, building principal, and the College supervisor, the student will be removed from the school placement by the Director of Field Experiences. In such cases, a written report stating the problem and efforts to correct the situation will be forwarded to the Director of Field Experiences in the College Student Services Center.

Any student removed from a practicum or student teaching assignment may appeal that decision by submitting a written request to the College Appeals Committee within 30 days of the removal. The Appeals Committee will schedule a meeting, request pertinent information from the Director of Field Experiences, and notify the student several days in advance of the scheduled appeal meeting. Students are advised of their right to seek legal advice and may personally attend the Appeals Committee meeting. The Committee’s decision will be forwarded in writing to the student, to the Director of Field Experiences, and to the Dean of the College.

Application for a Nebraska Teaching Certificate

To actively engage in the teaching profession, a candidate must fulfill both the College degree requirements and the professional certification requirements of the State of Nebraska, Department of Education. Students apply for the teaching certificate online at www.education.ne.gov/tcert/ and apply for the baccalaureate degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building.

To be eligible for a recommendation for certification, a candidate must meet the following requirements:

1. Earn one or more undergraduate degrees from the College of Education and Human Sciences or another accredited institution approved by the College of Education and Human Sciences with a minimum 2.5 grade point average.

2. Complete the teacher education general education requirements listed for elementary, middle grades or secondary education.

3. Complete professional education requirements according to established standards.

4. Complete endorsement(s) according to established standards.

5. Successfully complete a required period of student teaching.

6. Complete application for the degree and certificate.

Graduation Without Certification

In rare cases, permission may be granted for a student to graduate without a recommendation for certification. This provision is for the student who does not qualify for or is removed from student teaching. However, there are times when because of illness or other extreme situations, a student will decide not to complete all professional requirements. In this situation, the student should contact his or her adviser, then complete a formal request to the College’s Certification Officer to be allowed to graduate without completing all certification requirements. If permission is granted, the student is expected to complete all professional requirements except student teaching. This includes a passing grade in all methods courses. If a student fails to complete at least one half of the student teaching assignment, the individual will be required to complete a culminating project not to exceed 6 credit hours.

Any student who graduates without a recommendation for certification will not be recommended for teacher certification in any state. In addition, the student will not be eligible for graduation with honors. If, at some future time, the student wishes to complete certification requirements, (s)he must first appeal for readmission to a teacher education program. At least one semester must pass after graduation before the appeal can be made. If the appeal is granted, the student will be treated as a readmitted student and will complete all requirements in effect at the time of reentry, including passing grades in all methods courses.

Education Employment Services

The Career Services Center, 230 Nebraska Union, offers a professional placement service to students and alumni who are seeking employment in education and related fields. In addition to providing on-campus interviews with select schools throughout the year, this office sponsors an annual Education Recruitment Day in the spring, which offers students an opportunity to interview with hiring officials from many schools.

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Management

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (21 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–for CBA students only

CHIEF ADVISER: Gwendolyn M. Combs

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Gwendolyn M. Combs

Professors: Duchon, Luthans, Olson, Plowman, Schniederjans, Uhl-Bien, Welbourne

Associate Professors: Combs, Sebora, Swenseth, Trimi

Assistant Professors: Batur, Chakrabarty, Harms, Pieper, Thornton, Titus, Tuggle, Yu

Associate Professor of Practice: Jones

Assistant Professor of Practice: Nelson

A major in management at the University of Nebraska equips students with the essential skills to effectively manage people and resources in today’s business systems and organizational structures. Our management curriculum prepares students for careers in leadership and supervision of employees in the workplace, starting up and managing a business, and utilizing the critical role of information in strategy and operations of the business world.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take the following courses as part of the Business Core Intermediate Requirements:
MNGT 331 Operations & Supply Chain Management
MNGT 350 Intro to Management Information Systems
MNGT 360 Managing Behavior in Organizations

and for the Business Core Advanced Capstone requirement:

MNGT 475 Business Policies & Strategies
NONE of these courses may be used to count toward the major.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
MNGT 398, MNGT 399 may not count toward the major or minor in management.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 21 hours of course work for the management major. Students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in management will complete 9 hours of core management courses and one management Option consisting of four courses (12 credit hours) to meet the requirements for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M).

Required Management Courses (9 hours):

MNGT 311 Leadership, Communications, & Teams

MNGT 321/ENTR 321 Entrepreneurship & Innovation in Organizations

MNGT 361 Human Resource Management

The management major offers course work in the following Options of specialization:

Human Resource Management
Entrepreneurship and Innovation
Leadership in Organizations
General Management

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Management majors must declare one of these specializations as a formal Option within their major. Multiple options may not be chosen.

OPTION: Human Resource Management

Required Courses:

MNGT 461 Strategic Human Resource Management

MNGT 463 Compensation Administration

MNGT 464 Talent Acquisition & Staffing

MNGT 466 The Regulatory Environment for Employment & Labor

Students pursuing the Human Resource Management Option may wish to consider selecting from the following courses to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context

ECON 481 Economics of the Labor Market

OPTION: Entrepreneurship and Innovation

Required Courses:

MNGT 421/ENTR 421 Initiating & Managing Entrepreneurial Growth

MNGT 422/ENTR 422 Managing Rapid Growth & Change in Organizations

MNGT 423/ENTR 423 Business Plan Development & Decision Making

One course from the following list:

MNGT/ENTR 322 Family Business

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MRKT 345 Market Research

Students pursuing the Entrepreneurship and Innovation Option may wish to consider selecting from the following courses to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MNGT 464 Talent Acquisition & Staffing

MRKT 345 Market Research

OPTION: Leadership in Organizations

Required Courses:

MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects

MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management

MNGT 413 Building Ethical & Sustainable Organizations

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context

Students pursuing the Leadership in Organizations Option may wish to consider selecting from the following courses to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

MNGT 365 Managing Diversity in Organizations

MNGT 421/ENTR 421 Initiating & Managing Entrepreneurial Growth

MNGT 422 Business Plan Development & Decision Making

MNGT 464 Talent Acquisition & Staffing

SCMS 436 Project Management

OPTION: General Management

This Option is open to students who do not wish to specialize in one of the specified Options of the management major. In addition to the three core courses for the management Option, students must take 12 additional hours (four courses): three of these courses must be selected from the management options (Human Resource Management, Leadership, and Entrepreneurship, and one elective from the management or supply chain management systems course offerings.

Required Courses - 12 hours (four courses)

Select one course from each Option:

Human Resource Management

Entrepreneurship and Innovation

Leadership in Organizations

Select one elective from the management or supply chain management systems course offerings.

(NOTE: SCMS courses that are cross-listed with MRKT are not allowed in this requirement.)

Students pursuing the General Management Option may select from the course bulletin to fulfill elective requirements within the College.

Additional restrictions beyond those noted per individual courses above include:

NBR 6–ACE 9 – MNGT 365 or MNGT 414 can be double counted to fulfill NBR 6–ACE 9 AND course work for the major.
MNGT 414 may also be counted for the IBCR.
In any option where double counting is permitted, only 3 hours of credit are used; students must still meet the 120 hour requirement for the degree.
In any option where double counting is permitted for NBR requirements and the major, course work cannot, in turn, be used for any minor.
MNGT 121/ENTR 121, MNGT 331, MNGT 350/MIST 350/SCMS 350, MNGT 360, MNGT 398, MNGT 399 (Independent Study), and MNGT 475 may NOT be counted toward the major.
BSAD 491 may count for a maximum of 3 hours credit, only for those students who take it as part of the Nebraska at China Education Abroad Program or the Senshu University Program, or for a transfer course from an international institution for which ‘management-related’ course work was done, evaluated, and approved for credit toward the major.

REQUIREMENTS FOR THE MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

The management minor is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college requires that 75% of the course work for the minor will be completed at UNL.
Management course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation (BCF) intermediate (BCI) or advanced-major (BCA-M; BCA-C) degree requirements, for another major, or any other business minor requirements.
All course work for the management minor must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).
MNGT 399, MNGT 499, may NOT be used toward the minor.
To fulfill the requirements for a management minor, students must complete 12 graded hours of 300/400-level management course work.

Electives

As noted in the Options area, students may choose to take elective course work required for the degree in the suggested course options as listed under the areas of Options. See College Degree Requirements–Electives for additional options/restrictions regarding elective credit for the degree.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College Grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

Course Level Requirement

MNGT 475 Business Policies and Strategies is the capstone requirement for ALL business students and is to be taken the final semester in the program. Refer to the course description for other specific course prerequisites. This course may NOT be used toward the major (BCA-M).

Marketing

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Marketing

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (18 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–for CBA students only

DESCRIPTION

Chair: A. Dwayne Ball

Professors: Carlson, Gentry, Sohi

Associate Professors: Ball, Kennedy, Saini

Assistant Professors: Eilert, Friend, Kumar, Zhao

Associate Professor of Practice: Simon, Welton

The field of marketing includes many different career opportunities such as advertising, distribution, marketing research, merchandising, marketing communication, retailing, product management, sports marketing, professional selling, and sales management. The management of activities related to the flow of both goods and services from producer to consumer has become increasingly important in this age of consumer-oriented production. This importance has increased the demand for well-qualified persons, both as specialists in technical aspects of marketing and as general marketing managers. New developments are appearing in quantitative analysis of marketing problems, in studies of consumer behavior, in international marketing, and in the social responsibilities of marketing. These developments hold exciting promise for the future.

Academic preparation for some careers is best achieved by combining marketing courses with courses in other departments of the University. For this reason it is important for the student to consult with a faculty member in the Department of Marketing before deciding on a particular course of study. Courses within the department include those from the following disciplines: Marketing, Marketing Communication, Distribution Channels, Retailing, Sales Management, Marketing Research, Professional Selling, Sports Marketing, Consumer Behavior, and International Marketing. Outside the College, courses in psychology, sociology, journalism, mathematics, communication studies, art, and geography may be helpful.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take MRKT 341 Marketing as part of the Business Core Intermediate requirements.

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 21 hours of course work for the major.
As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.
MRKT 399/ MRKT 499 may not count toward the major or minor in marketing.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in marketing will complete 21 hours of marketing course work (plus MRKT 341 for the Business Core Intermediate requirement) for the Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M):

6 required hours selected from:

MRKT 345 Market Research or MRKT 350 Marketing Information Systems (if not taken in Business Core Intermediate) or MRKT 355 Marketing Metrics

MRKT 442 Marketing Management (capstone requirement for the marketing major taken during the final semester in the program. Refer to course description for other specific course prerequisites.)

15 additional hours of marketing to be selected from the following courses:

MRKT 225/AECN 225/EAEP 225 Agribusiness Entrepreneurship in Food Products Marketing

MRKT 325/AECN 325 Marketing of Agricultural Commodities

MRKT 345 Market Research (if not selected or in lieu of MRKT 350 or MRKT 355)

MRKT 346 Marketing Channels Management (if not selected for above requirement)

MRKT 347 Marketing Communication Strategy (if not selected for above requirement)

MRKT 350 Marketing Information Systems (if not selected or in lieu of MRKT 345 or MRKT 355, or used in lieu of MNGT 350 for BCI)

MRKT 355 Marketing Metrics (if not selected or in lieu of MRKT 345 or MRKT 350)

MRKT 357 Professional Selling

MRKT 425 Retailing Management

MRKT 426 Services Marketing

MRKT 428 Sports Marketing

MRKT 441 Digital Marketing & Electronic Commerce

MRKT 443 Consumer Behavior: Marketing Aspects

MRKT 444 Supply Chain Logistics Management

MRKT 446 Quantitative Analysis in Marketing

MRKT 449 Marketing Communication Campaigns

MRKT 450 Strategic Database Marketing

MRKT 453 International Marketing

MRKT 458 Sales Management

MRKT 490 Special Topics in Marketing

MRKT 399 may not be used toward the major
As part of the Business Core Intermediate (BCI) requirements, marketing majors may substitute MRKT 350 for the MNGT 350 requirement.
Note that although only one of MRKT 345 or MRKT 350 or MRKT 355 is required, a student may elect to take all, one as required and the other two as part of the 15 hours of marketing electives.
The marketing curriculum specifies that MRKT 442 cannot be taken until MRKT 341, MRKT 345, MRKT 350, or MRKT 355 and 6 hours of marketing electives have been completed. This is the capstone requirement for the marketing major and should be taken during the final semester in the program.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, students majoring in marketing may choose to pursue three different options and have these minors declared to pursue the course options. Course work will count toward the ELECTIVES in the College.

Advertising Emphasis requirements (12 hours):

9 hours from:

JOMC 160 Visual Production: Photography & Videography or JOMC 161 Visual Design Fundamentals: Graphic Design & Web (3 cr)

ADPR 251 Principles of Strategic Communication (3 cr)

ADPR 283 Writing for Strategic Communications (3 cr)

3 hours – One course from ADPR (300 or 400 level) or select one of the following from JOMC:

JOMC 485 Mass Media History (3 cr)

JOMC 486 Mass Media Law

JOMC 487 Mass Media & Society

JOMC 160, JOMC 161 and ADPR 251 have no prerequisites. ADPR 251 should be completed before ADPR 283.
ADPR 283 must be completed before taking any of the 300- or 400-level courses.
Marketing majors must have the prerequisites for courses in ADPR and JOMC.

Marketing majors may minor in textiles, clothing and design by choosing either a Merchandising Track or a Merchandising/Design Track.

Minor in Textiles, Clothing and Design: Merchandising Track requirements (15 hours)

Required:

TMFD 206 Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 213 Merchandising I: Textile & Apparel Industry (3 cr)

TMFD 313 Merchandising II: Merchandise Buying & Control (3 cr)

Also select two courses from the following:

TMFD 405 Advanced Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 407 History of Costume (3 cr)

TMFD 408 History of Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 410 Socio-Psychological Aspects of Clothing (3 cr)

TMFD 413 Merchandising III: Merchandise Development & Sourcing (3 cr)

Minor in Textiles, Clothing and Design: Merchandising/Design Track requirements (21 hours)

Required:

TMFD 141A Visual Literacy Lab: Color (3 cr)

TMFD 141B Visual Literacy Lab: Speculative Drawing (3 cr)

TMFD 143 Visual Literacy: Art & Design (3 cr)

TMFD 206 Textiles (3 cr)

TMFD 213 Merchandising I: Textile & Apparel Industry (3 cr)

TMFD 313 Merchandising II: Merchandise Buying & Control (3 cr)

TMFD 314 Visual Merchandising (3 cr)

TMFD 413 Merchandising III: Merchandise Development & Sourcing (3 cr)

Minor Requirements

Refer to: Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in upper-level marketing courses requires completion of MRKT 341 as well as other prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions for specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

Course Level Requirement

MRKT 442 Marketing Management is the capstone requirement for the marketing major taken during the final semester in the program. Refer to course description for other specific course prerequisites.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Marketing Minor

The marketing minor is available to College of Business Administration students only. The college requires that 75% of the course work for the minor will be completed at UNL.
Marketing course work used for this minor cannot be double counted toward business core foundation (BCF) intermediate (BCI) or advanced-major (BCA-M; BCA-A) degree requirements, for another major, nor any other business minor requirements.
To fulfill the requirements for a marketing minor, students must complete:
Twelve (12) graded hours of 300/400-level marketing course work.
All course work for the minor must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).
MRKT 399 may not be used toward the minor (or major).

OTHER

The marketing department requires and enforces that specific prerequisite requirements be completed by the first class meeting. Concurrent registration in a class that is a prerequisite for another class is not allowed. Transfer credit assumes that the prerequisites have been transferred to UNL and appear on the transcripts.

The marketing department reserves the right to administratively drop students who do not attend the first class meeting and/or who do not have the appropriate prerequisites for any marketing class.

Mechanical Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Mechanical Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 129

MINIMUM cumulative gpa: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Jeffrey Shield

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Jeffrey E. Shield

Associate Chair for Research and Graduate Studies: Mehrdad Negahban

Professors: Barton, Bishu, Chandra, Cole, Dzenis, Farritor, Feng, Gogos, Hallbeck, Negahban, Rajurkar, Reid, Robertson, Shield, To, Turner, Yang

Associate Professors: Baesu, Bobaru, Nelson, Szydlowski, Tan, Williams, Zhang

Assistant Professors: Gu, Huang, Lim, Ryu

Lecturers: Coen-Brown, Dick

Mechanical engineering is a broad field of study that significantly impacts many technologies, including those that expand our energy resources and improve medical care. Mechanical engineers are concerned with all forms of energy conversion and transmission; the flow of fluids and heat; the development, design, manufacturing, and operation of machinery and equipment; material structure and properties; solid and applied mechanics; and transportation processes. The course of study is designed to give the student fundamental preparation to enter the fields of research, design, operation, production, sales, or management.

The mechanical engineering curriculum is structured so that students are well prepared in the fundamental areas of solid mechanics, thermal-fluid sciences, systems and design engineering, and materials engineering. Students can develop an emphasis area of study by concentrating elective courses in specific areas such as aerospace engineering, automotive engineering, robotics, biomedical engineering, computational methods, materials, manufacturing and others depending upon the technical courses available and the interest of the student.

Mission and Objectives

Mission Statement

The mission of the Department of Mechanical and Materials Engineering at the University of Nebraska is to impact society locally and globally through our educational programs, research, and service, developing knowledge and sharing our expertise in the best traditions of land-grant universities. We strive for excellence in teaching and learning at both the undergraduate and graduate levels, seek to develop novel educational opportunities, grow our public and private support for research and education, and expand our scholarship, outreach and service.

Program Educational Objectives

Within a few years of graduation, our mechanical engineering graduates are expected to:

1. have started successful careers based on their education or have completed a professional degree or a graduate degree in engineering or related field;

2. have begun life-long learning and development in order to remain current in their knowledge and skills and to advance in their careers; and

3. have established a record of professionalism, leadership, respect and integrity in working to serve humanity and to use resources responsibly.

Student Outcomes

The educational program leading to the BS in mechanical engineering ensures that students attain the following outcomes:

an ability to apply knowledge of mathematics, science, and engineering;
an ability to design and conduct experiments, as well as to analyze and interpret data;
an ability to design a system, component, or process to meet desired needs within realistic constraints such as economic, environmental, social, political, ethical, health and safety, manufacturability, and sustainability;
an ability to function on multidisciplinary teams;
an ability to identify, formulate, and solve engineering problems;
an understanding of professional and ethical responsibility;
an ability to communicate effectively;
the broad education necessary to understand the impact of engineering solutions in a global, economic, environmental, and societal context;
a recognition of the need for, and an ability to engage in, life-long learning;
a knowledge of contemporary issues;
an ability to use the techniques, skills, and modern engineering tools necessary for engineering practice.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree (Lincoln campus)

First Semester Hours

CHEM 111 Chemistry for Engineering & Technology 4

CHEM 109 and 110 may be substituted for CHEM 111. Only 4 credits count toward graduation.

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

ACE Electives 6

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 15

Second Semester Hours

CSCE 155N Computer Science I: Engineering and Science Focus 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 5

MECH 130 Intro to CAD 3

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

PHYS 221 General Physics Lab I 1

Or, instead, PHYS 222 General Physics Lab II (1 cr) may be taken in the Third Semester

Total 16

Third Semester Hours

ENGM 223 Engineering Statics 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

IMSE 206 Engineering Economy I 3

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 17

Fourth Semester Hours

ENGM 325 Mechanics of Elastic Bodies 3

ENGM 373 Engineering Dynamics 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

MECH 200 Engineering Thermodynamics 3

METL 360 Elements of Materials Science 4

Total 16

Fifth Semester Hours

ELEC 211 Elements of Electrical Engineering I 3

ELEC 231 Electrical Engineering Lab 1

MATH 314 Applied Linear Algebra (Matrix Theory) 3

MECH 310 Fluid Mechanics 3

MECH 342 Kinematics & Dynamics of Machinery 3

Communication Studies Elective 3

Choose one course from the following: COMM 210, COMM 283, or COMM 286 (ACE 2).

Total 16

Sixth Semester Hours

IMSE 321 Engineering Statistics & Data Analysis or STAT 380 Statistics & Applications 3

MECH 300 Thermal Systems & Design 3

MECH 343 Elements of Machine Design 3

MECH 350 Intro to Dynamics & Control of Engineering Systems 3

MECH 380 Mechanical Engineering Measurements 3

Total 15

Seventh Semester Hours

MECH 370 Manufacturing Methods & Processes 3

MECH 420 Heat Transfer 3

MECH 446 Mechanical Engineering Design I 3

The capstone design sequence must be taken in the order shown in the curriculum and should be taken in the last two semesters of the program (MECH 446 and MECH 447).

MECH 488 Kinematics & Machine Design Lab 2

Mechanical Engineering Technical Elective 3

Design and technical electives must be chosen from a list of approved 400-level mechanical engineering elective courses. Consult adviser for suggested choices.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 17

Eighth Semester Hours

ENGR 400 Professional Ethics 1

MECH 447 Mechanical Engineering Design II 2

MECH 487 Thermal Fluids Lab 2

Mechanical Engineering Design Elective 3

Design and technical electives must be chosen from a list of approved 400-level mechanical engineering elective courses. Consult adviser for suggested choices.

Senior Elective 3

Senior electives may be either another mechanical engineering technical elective, another mechanical engineering design elective, or, with prior written approval of your adviser, a 300 or higher level engineering, science, or math course.

ACE Elective 6

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, or 9.

Total 17

Total Credit Hours Required 129

OTHER

Admittance to Degree Program

Students are expected to meet minimum college entrance requirements. After being admitted to the college as pre-mechanical engineering students, students wishing to pursue a degree in mechanical engineering must further be admitted to the degree program. Students who have completed 43 credit hours applicable to their mechanical engineering degree are considered for formal admission to the eechanical engineering degree program. Typically, this occurs the semester the student is enrolled in MECH 200 or METL 360. Those exceeding 61 credit hours must receive formal admission to the mechanical engineering degree program if they are to continue to take mechanical engineering courses. Transfer students must have at least 12 credit hours of course work from the University of Nebraska on record before an application will be considered. Applications are judged on a competitive academic performance basis; consult your adviser or the Department of Mechanical and Materials Engineering for specific details.

Hands-on Opportunities

One major focus of the Department is to provide students with many hands-on opportunities both within the curriculum (through formal laboratory courses) and through extracurricular activities. Brief descriptions of some of the laboratories in the department are given below.

The Materials Laboratory is designed to study the development of microstructures during processing, and to correlate the properties of materials with the observed structures. Undergraduates utilize arc melting facilities for solidification processing and alloy formation, rolling mills for deformation processing, and a variety of furnaces for thermal treatments. Characterization facilities include x-ray diffractometry and optical microscopy, while property measurements are completed using hardness testing (including microhardness), tensile testing, and impact testing facilities. Other facilities associated with the materials laboratory include rapid solidification processing facilities and electron microscopy facilities.

The Measurements Laboratory is associated with the required MECH 380 Mechanical Engineering Measurements course which includes two hours of lecture and two hours of laboratory work each week. The course covers the fundamentals of mechanical engineering measurements including data analysis (statistics, graphing, spectral analysis), signal conditioning, data readout, and the measurement of length/displacement, rate of rotation, stress/strain, temperature, pressure, fluid velocity, fluid flowrate, vibration/acceleration, and sound. The MECH 380 Lab has four workbenches. Each workbench has set of basic measurement equipment including a digital oscilloscope, an electronic counter, a digital multimeter, a DC power supply, a function generator, and a computer-based data acquisition system consisting of a personal computer with data acquisition software and interfaced analog-to-digital converter and digital counter cards. In addition, on a week-to-week basis, specialized equipment is brought out of the cabinets and set up for each of the nine (some one week, some two week) labs.

The Kinematics and Machine Design Laboratory is a teaching laboratory for undergraduate students. The laboratory consists of equipment and instruments for conducting experiments in kinematics and machine design. One piece of major equipment is the rapid prototyping machine, which accepts design specifications from a computer and forms a prototype of the design using plastic injection. This machine provides the student with experience in design integration from concept to product. We have also recently upgraded the rapid prototyping laboratory with the acquisition of the MakerBot Thing-O-Matic 3-D printer kit. This 3D printer uses ABS plastic to create rapid prototyped objects with better than 1 mm feature resolution; it accepts standard CAD models converted to g-code and is a low-cost alternative to high-end rapid prototyping services or equipment. Accessories in this laboratory include desktop computers, a wide-carriage printer, and other instruments. Kawasaki also donated a retired robot that is now utilized in this laboratory.

The Thermal Fluids Laboratory involves design, execution and evaluation of physical experiments in the areas of thermodynamics, fluid mechanics, and heat transfer. There are three major, heavily-instrumented experiments: 1) a two stage air-compressor with intercooling, 2) a versatile air conditioning unit, and 3) a Ford gasoline engine with a Superflow water brake dynamometer, supported with a data acquisition system. The course involves design, execution and evaluation of physical experiments in the areas of thermodynamics, fluid mechanics, and heat transfer. In addition, the facilities include “table top” instrumentation for viscosity measurement, measurement of pressure distribution on an airfoil, flow visualization and head loss across a valve on which students conduct experiments.

The Mechatronics Laboratory is well-equipped for teaching courses in mechatronics and robotics. It is used primarily for MECH 457, but is also used for other courses, and by both undergraduate and graduate students working on research projects. The laboratory contains desktop computers, modular robots, digital oscilloscopes, function generators, computer controllers, soldering systems, and many other accessories.

The Department also has computational facilities available to students. The computer lab has a suite of personal computers with a full complement of computing resources available to students.

Research Laboratories. These laboratories, extensions of those described above, are equipped for research in the fields of fluid mechanics, heat transfer, thermodynamics, turbulence, flow visualization, fluid mechanics, measurements, turbomachinery and engine research, combustion, materials, mechanical design, dynamics, computational, solid and applied mechanics, biomedical engineering, and controls. Many of our undergraduate students gain valuable experience working on research projects under the guidance of professors. These are funded by research grants or the University’s UCARE program.

Some of the extracurricular opportunities for students to gain hands-on engineering experience include SAE Baja, SAE Formula (both through Husker Motorsports), NASA microgravity, AIAA competitions, and others.

Mild/Moderate Disabilities Education (7-12)

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Special Education & Communication Disorders

PROGRAM: Mild/Moderate Disabilities Education (7-12)

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Beverly Jensen

DESCRIPTION

Students who complete this field endorsement are endorsed to teach children and youth who have mild or moderate disabilities and who are verified as students with one or more of the following disabilities: developmental delay, specific learning disabilities, speech language impairment (language verification only), mild or moderate mental handicap, behavior disorders, orthopedic impairments, autism, other health impairments, and traumatic brain injury and those verified children who are placed in multi-categorical programs in grades 7 through 12.

General Information

The College offers undergraduate programs leading to a bachelor of science in education and human sciences degree in more than 40 different teaching endorsements. Some students in other UNL colleges choose to seek certification, completing a degree in their home college while meeting all requirements for teacher certification in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Early field placement in public and private schools is a nationally recognized hallmark of the teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. While internships are a valuable enhancement to many students’ education, in the College of Education and Human Sciences, practicum experiences and student teaching are a critical and essential part of the curriculum and these must be successfully completed in order to be certified in the teaching profession. A student’s inability to complete these field experiences, for any reason, may adversely impact the candidate’s ability to gain admission into the College or maintain enrollment in a teacher preparation program. Students unlikely or unable to complete the field experience may be counseled to seek other opportunities where success is more attainable. (See “Felony and Misdemeanor Conviction” and “Professional and Ethical Behavior” under the OTHER heading for additional information with respect to behaviors impacting field experience participation.)

Teacher education endorsements are divided into field endorsements or single-subject endorsements. Field endorsements certify the candidate to teach a broader range of courses compared to single-subject endorsements, which certify the candidate to teach in one subject area only. Consequently, a teacher holding a field endorsement is typically more marketable than a teacher holding a single-subject endorsement.

Candidates may also elect to complete requirements for supplemental endorsements; these are additional endorsements that can be added to a field or single-subject endorsement but cannot be taken alone. Supplemental endorsements require additional credit hours beyond those needed for the first endorsement (field or single-subject). Teachers may increase their marketability by adding supplemental endorsements.

Students may also choose to complete requirements for two endorsements simultaneously. Completing a second endorsement will require additional credit hours beyond those required for the first endorsement. Often the completion of two endorsements requires more than 120 credit hours of course work and may require additional semesters of course work. Students may contact the College Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, or their adviser, for assistance in deciding whether to complete: field or single-subject endorsements, one or more supplemental endorsements, or multiple endorsements.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30-32

ACE 1. ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 or ENGL 254 3

ACE 2. COMM 109 or COMM 209 or COMM 210 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 3. MATH 104 or MATH 106 or MATH 203 or STAT 218 or EDPS 459 3-5

ACE 4. 3

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. EDPS 251 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. TEAC 330 (Pre-Professional Education Requirement) 3

ACE 10. SPED 403 (Professional Education Requirement) 3

Pre-Professional Education Requirements 10

EDPS 297 1

*EDPS 457 3

TEAC 259 3

*TEAC 331 3

Mild/Moderate Disabilities 7-12 Endorsement Requirements 40-46

SPED 201 or SPED 400 3

SPED 303 3

SPED 310 3

SPED 406 2

SPED 406A 2

SPED 407 3

SPED 408 3

SPED 412 3

SPED 414 3

SPED 436 3

SPED 480 3

TEAC 441 3

TEAC 446 3

Select 3-9 hrs from: TEAC 397, TEAC 451, TEAC 452 3-9

Professional Education Requirements 12

SPED 496M 3

SPED 497M 9

Electives 20-28

Total Hours 120

* These courses are also approved ACE courses and together with the 30 hours of ACE Required Courses meet the additional ACE/General Education requirements for secondary education students.

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

Additional ACE Course Work for Secondary Education

Secondary education students need additional ACE courses for a total of 40 hours to meet the requirements for the Nebraska Department of Education. One of the ACE courses must be an approved speech course. At least two of the ACE courses must be at the 300/400 level. Once again, there may be required courses within your program that will also satisfy these additional ACE requirements. Contact your adviser.

ADMISSION

All education programs have a competitive admission process. At some point-in-time, after meeting specific education requirements, all students must formally apply to their particular education program.

Pre-Education Status

All newly admitted students who are pursuing a teacher preparation program are classified as pre-education students until admitted to a specific Teacher Education Program.

Admission to a Teacher Education Program (TEP)

Admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences does not guarantee admission into a teacher education program. Admission to the advanced phases of teacher education is selective and, in some endorsements, highly competitive. Students must satisfy the following requirements in order to be eligible to apply to the Teacher Education Program:

1. Must have earned a minimum of 42 credit hours of college credit with an overall minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA.

2. A minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA in the following endorsement courses: SPED 201, SPED 303, and SPED 412 with no grade below a C+.

3. Students must earn a minimum of a C+ in each of the classes indicated below and an average GPA of 2.5 or higher: COMM 109, COMM 205, COMM 209, COMM 210, COMM 286 or an approved substitute; TEAC 259, TEAC 331; EDPS 251 (or an approved transfer course).

4. Completion of a personal and professional fitness self-disclosure form (PPF) and a formal criminal history review, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required).

5. Completion of the Basic Skills Test as required by the Nebraska Department of Education, with documented passing scores in math, reading, and writing.

6. All classes MUST be completed prior to submitting admission application to this program.

Make an appointment or come during a Walk-in Wednesday and get a signed Teacher Education Program (TEP) form from your adviser in the Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, that verifies your eligibility to apply.
Attach an unofficial copy of your transcripts from MyRed.
Submit the materials to your adviser in the Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall, no later than 4 pm on February 1st or May 6th depending upon when you have met all criteria. Your application will then be forwarded to the SPED faculty for review and determination of admission to the Teacher Education Program.

Admission to Student Teaching

All students who are candidates for an appropriately endorsed Nebraska Teacher’s Certificate are required to student teach. Students who plan to student teach in the fall semester must complete the student teaching application form and submit it by the preceding March 1 to the Director of Field Experiences in 116 Henzlik Hall; students planning to student teach in the spring semester must apply by the preceding October 1. The basic program for student teaching provides for a full-day experience for an entire semester. Admission to student teaching requires the following:

1. Matriculation in a teacher education program in the College of Education and Human Sciences, the Graduate College, or dual matriculation in the College of Education and Human Sciences and another college.

2. Admission to a specific teacher education program.

3. Senior standing (89 hours or more) with a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.5.

4. Minimum grade point average of 2.5 in the endorsement area with no grade below C.

5. A minimum grade point average of 2.5 in pre-professional and professional education courses and no grade below C in pre-professional education courses and no grade below a C+ in professional education courses.

6. All endorsement, pre-professional and professional education course work must be completed prior to student teaching. If necessary, no more than 6 hours of general education (ACE) or elective classes can be completed after the student teaching experience.

7. No additional course work can be taken during the student teaching semester unless prior approval is obtained from the Certification Officer, the Director of Field Experiences, or the Department Chair that oversees the program.

8. Completion of a second criminal history check that will be conducted, for CEHS, by the vender approved by CEHS (fee required). For more information, contact the Director of Field Experiences or your adviser.

MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

SPED 201 Intro to Special Education or SPED 400 Characteristics of Exceptional Persons

SPED 303 Behavior Management

SPED 310 Collaborative Practices

SPED 406/SPED 406A Reading & Writing Disabilities: Adolescents

SPED 407 Teaching Students with Disabilities in the Secondary School

SPED 408 Issues in Secondary Programs for Students with Mild Disabilities

SPED 412 Assessment Techniques for Diverse Learners

SPED 414 Instructional Methods for Students with Diverse Needs

SPED 436 Career Education for the Special Needs Student

SPED 480 Educating Students with Intellectual Impairments & Developmental Disabilities

TEAC 441 Content Area Reading, Grades 4-12

TEAC 446 The Middle Level Program

Select 3-9 hrs from: TEAC 397, TEAC 451, TEAC 452

Pre-Professional Education Requirements

With the exception of EDPS 297 and TEAC 330, students must complete the following before applying to their Teacher Education Program (TEP).

**EDPS 251

EDPS 297

TEAC 259

**TEAC 331

**COMM 109, COMM 205, **COMM 209, **COMM 210, or COMM 286, or an approved speech class

**TEAC 330

Professional Education Requirements

**SPED 403 Seminar: Mildly Handicapped

SPED 496M Field Experience: Mild/Moderate

SPED 497M Practicum: Mild/Moderate

** These courses also meet ACE requirements. See your adviser.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Requirements in Education Programs

Requirements for completion of an undergraduate degree in a teacher preparation program include a minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5. Students seeking certification must also have a 2.5 GPA in their endorsement and education courses with no grade lower than a C in their pre-professional courses and no grade lower than a C+ in their professional education courses.

Transfer Grades

Up to 9 hours of transfer credit with grades below C may be applied to the General Education requirements and elective classes in programs leading to the undergraduate degree in teacher preparation. Transfer grades of C- and D may not be used in the major/endorsement area courses or in the professional courses in teacher preparation programs.

Pass/No Pass Grade Option–for Education Students

A student enrolled at the University may, in certain instances, take a grading option of Pass/No Pass (P/N) for a specific course. A grade of pass represents satisfactory completion of a course with a grade of C or better. Credits earned under the pass grade option count toward graduation, but no grade points are tabulated in the cumulative grade point average. Likewise, a grade of no pass is not tabulated in the grade point average. The following rules apply to students who are enrolled in teacher preparation programs who choose the Pass/No Pass option:

1. All Special Education Endorsement courses must be taken for a letter grade.

2. Pre-professional and professional education classes may not be taken P/N unless a class already has a P/N designation.

3. Any course in the general education requirements unless otherwise stipulated by the department of the course may be taken P/N.

4. Total P/N credits may not exceed 12 credit hours. This limit does not include courses offered on a P/N only basis.

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL.

Beyond Classroom Grades

In all fields of study, students are expected to attain certain grades and other academic accomplishments in the classroom. In addition to this, students preparing themselves to be teachers, counselors and for other careers in education, are also reviewed to evaluate their ability to successfully and safely interact with children, parents, potential educational employers, and the community-at-large, whose interest in the education of its children often exceeds its concern for other community and governmental services.

OTHER

Student Teaching Placement

The Office of Field Experiences is responsible for the placement of student teachers. Several factors are considered in determining the district and school to which an individual is assigned. The availability of a cooperating teacher and supervisor who meet the requirements established by the Nebraska Department of Education and the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are among those factors. Opportunities to student teach out-of-state are limited and those placements are becoming increasingly difficult. All requests to student teach outside of the immediate Lincoln area must be individually reviewed and approved by the Director of Field Experiences.

Removal from Student Teaching

Students participating in practicum or student teaching assignments may be removed from their assigned schools if their conduct suggests a lack of professional commitment and presents a negative influence on the well-being or learning of the students in the schools. Specific guidelines that all student teachers are to follow can be found in The Student Teaching Experience: A Handbook for the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. If such a problem occurs, at the request of the cooperating teacher, building principal, and the College supervisor, the student will be removed from the school placement by the Director of Field Experiences. In such cases, a written report stating the problem and efforts to correct the situation will be forwarded to the Director of Field Experiences in the College Student Services Center.

Any student removed from a practicum or student teaching assignment may appeal that decision by submitting a written request to the College Appeals Committee within 30 days of the removal. The Appeals Committee will schedule a meeting, request pertinent information from the Director of Field Experiences, and notify the student several days in advance of the scheduled appeal meeting. Students are advised of their right to seek legal advice and may personally attend the Appeals Committee meeting. The Committee’s decision will be forwarded in writing to the student, to the Director of Field Experiences, and to the Dean of the College.

Application for a Nebraska Teaching Certificate

To actively engage in the teaching profession, a candidate must fulfill both the College degree requirements and the professional certification requirements of the State of Nebraska, Department of Education. Undergraduate students apply for the teaching certificate online at www.education.ne.gov/tcert and apply for the baccalaureate degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building. Post-baccalaureate students completing teacher certification also apply for the teaching certificate online at www.education.ne.gov/tcert, and if they complete a masters degree with their certificate program, apply for the degree in 109 Canfield Administration Building.

To be eligible for a recommendation for certification, a candidate must meet the following requirements:

1. Earn one or more undergraduate degrees from the College of Education and Human Sciences or another accredited institution approved by the College of Education and Human Sciences with a minimum 2.5 grade point average.

2. Complete the teacher education general education requirements listed for elementary, middle grades or secondary education.

3. Complete professional education requirements according to established standards.

4. Complete endorsement(s) according to established standards.

5. Successfully complete a required period of student teaching.

6. Complete application for the degree and certificate.

Graduation Without Certification

In rare cases, permission may be granted for a student to graduate without a recommendation for certification. This provision is for the student who does not qualify for or is removed from student teaching. However, there are times when because of illness or other extreme situations, a student will decide not to complete all professional requirements. In this situation, the student should contact his or her adviser, then complete a formal request to the College’s Certification Officer to be allowed to graduate without completing all certification requirements. If permission is granted, the student is expected to complete all professional requirements except student teaching. This includes a passing grade in all methods courses. If a student fails to complete at least one half of the student teaching assignment, the individual will be required to complete a culminating project not to exceed 6 credit hours.

Any student who graduates without a recommendation for certification will not be recommended for teacher certification in any state. In addition, the student will not be eligible for graduation with honors. If, at some future time, the student wishes to complete certification requirements, (s)he must first appeal for readmission to a teacher education program. At least one semester must pass after graduation before the appeal can be made. If the appeal is granted, the student will be treated as a readmitted student and will complete all requirements in effect at the time of reentry, including passing grades in all methods courses.

Education Employment Services

The Career Services Center, 230 Nebraska Union, offers a professional placement service to students and alumni who are seeking employment in education and related fields. In addition to providing on-campus interviews with select schools throughout the year, this office sponsors an annual Education Recruitment Day in the spring, which offers students an opportunity to interview with hiring officials from many schools.

Felony and Misdemeanor Convictions

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS), along with the public and private schools and community agencies who provide services or programs for children, are all keenly attuned to the safety of the educational community, and particularly children in the classroom. We have the responsibility to ensure that our students who interact with individuals served by schools or other agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior.

The Nebraska Department of Education policy requires that a person with any felony conviction or a misdemeanor conviction involving assault, abuse, neglect, or sexual misconduct shall not be allowed to participate in pre-student teaching laboratory and classroom experiences or student teach without approval of the State Board of Education. To comply with this policy, the College of Education and Human Sciences will require each student in a teacher education program to complete a “Personal and Professional Fitness” form (PPF) and two formal reviews of their criminal history, which is conducted by the approved CEHS vender. The first review and the PPF will be completed during the first semester of the individual’s entry into the College. The second criminal history background check will take place as part of the student teaching application process. Each student is responsible for the cost of the two criminal history reviews. Students in non-teacher education programs who interact with children in a public agency setting must also complete an official criminal history background check by the approved CEHS vender, upon entry into the College and prior to the student’s culminating field experience or internship and are responsible for the cost of the reviews. Each student who has completed an initial Criminal History Background Check is required to report any new charge or conviction acquired after the initial check, to the Director of Field Experiences.

If a student does have any felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, he/she is required to meet with the Certification Officer or with the Director of Field Experience as soon as possible. This meeting will be held so that the student can receive guidance with respect to the impact of the conviction on the student’s future in the College, the State Board of Education approval and, more broadly, on the student’s ability to find success in the profession of education.

The College of Education and Human Sciences aims to train and graduate teachers of the highest caliber possible, and therefore, the standards the College sets for its students may be more stringent than the rules the Department of Education sets for field experience. A student should not assume that merely because the State Board of Education would approve placement in the field, that the College is willing to make such a placement, or that a participating partner school is willing to accept the student’s placement into its midst.

The consequences of one conviction compared to another may vary significantly, depending upon the facts underlying the convictions. Those facts are determined by the College. In some instances, the behavior associated with the conviction may be so egregious as to render placement in a field experience virtually impossible. In such instances, termination or long-term suspension from a teaching program may be appropriate. In other instances, a responsible passage of time without further criminal incident may indicate that the student has matured and is ready to reconvene his or her education. Consequences will very likely be different from case to case, as each of these difficult matters is unique. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that the safety of children in the classroom, the best interest of the student, and the reputation of the College, are all recognized and promoted. Failure to honestly disclose a conviction may be cause for disciplinary action separate from the conviction itself. Students willing to honestly address the challenges that arise from the past mistakes are more likely to reach a favorable outcome, than those who further jeopardize their integrity with a lie.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

In additional to criminal convictions, other non-criminal behaviors which: involve risks that are unacceptable for future teachers and the children charged to their care; demonstrate a lack of professionalism and good judgment; and evidence a disregard for one’s personal reputation, the integrity of the College and the teaching profession, may bring into question a student’s ability to be successful in an education career. Before engaging in such questionable behavior, students must consider how the College, the profession, educational employer, parents of school-aged children, and the community which is the State of Nebraska, would perceive or evaluate the impact of that behavior with respect to the students’ ability to serve children. To be allowed to teach is a great honor and a great responsibility. Teaching is a profession that requires its potential candidates to be individuals of the highest integrity. Prospective teachers must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and for their students. They serve as important role models and mentors for children during very impressionable years. Teachers are responsible for the education, safety and well-being for anyone in their charge. Indeed, teachers hold the future of all in their care. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences is most interested in training future teachers who show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act responsibly. These individuals must be able to serve as representatives of our College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. These standards and practices also apply to individuals in CEHS programs intended to serve children in a community setting.

Should the College, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience, determine that a student’s individual behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or otherwise indicates a potential of risk to young persons and others in the educational community, the College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to deny entry to or dismiss such a student from any program which leads to certification or to service of children in a community agency. More specifically, these kinds of behavior shall be adequate foundation to deny any candidate or potential candidate from participation in any practicum, pre-practicum, student teaching or similar field experience, since the interests and safety of the children, and young people present in the classroom, schools and other venues where these practicum experiences take place are paramount.

Problematic behaviors, which the College of Education and Human Sciences reasonably determines renders the candidate a risk to the educational community or demonstrates a likelihood of illegal activity, may be established by any credible means, including the facts surrounding a record of arrests and/or convictions.

Similarly, behaviors which result in a finding by a court or other governmental body that the individual is:

a mentally ill and dangerous person;
mentally incompetent to stand trial;
acquitted of criminal charges because of insanity;
an incapacitated person;
a person in need of a guardian or conservator, or;
a person unable to manage his or her property due to mental illness, mental deficiency, or chronic use of drugs or chronic intoxication are the kind of behaviors which are likely to disqualify a candidate from participation in practicum experiences and other College of Education and Human Sciences programs.

Similar to the discussion concerning criminal convictions above, the consequences for unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will very likely be different in each case, due to the unique circumstances involved in each matter. The College reserves its prerogative to evaluate students’ fitness for the profession in its discretion, so that safety in the classroom, the reputation of the College, and the best interest of the student, are all recognized and promoted.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience with respect to a criminal behavior matter, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing within no greater than ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student’s written appeal shall clearly explain to the Dean the basis for the student’s appeal. The Dean will review the student’s basis for appeal, and is authorized, but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student’s written appeal. The Dean is authorized to collect such additional information as she or he deems necessary to review an investigation (including but not limited to the student’s educational records maintained by the College, other documentation, personal interviews and meetings with the student, College faculty, administration and staff, and others with relevant information). The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possibly, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Field Experience or both, a written decision, which decision shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review within the University of Nebraska.

Nutrition & Dietetics

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Nutrition & Health Sciences

PROGRAM: Nutrition & Dietetics (Didactic Program in Dietetics)

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

The Nutrition and Dietetics (Didactic Program in Dietetics) option is designed for students who wish to become registered dietitians and practitioners in clinical, community, food industry, and foodservice areas of nutrition and may be employed by hospitals, community agencies, and various government or private organizations. The University of Nebraska–Lincoln Didactic Program in Dietetics is currently granted accreditation status by the Accreditation Council for Education in Nutrition and Dietetics of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics, 120 South Riverside Plaza, Suite 2000, Chicago, IL 60606-6995, 312-899-0040, ext. 5400.

The process to become a registered dietitian involves three steps: completion of a bachelors degree with attainment of the Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics; admission into and the completion of an accredited dietetic internship program; and successfully passing the registration exam to earn the Registered Dietitian (RD) credential.

Meeting requirements for the bachelors degree Nutrition and Dietetics option does not automatically result in the student being awarded a Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics. Requirements for attainment of the Verification Statement are listed on the dietetics program website. The Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics is required for admission into an accredited dietetic internship program.

Acceptance into an accredited dietetic internship program is competitive. Currently, there is a significant shortage of available internship positions for the number of students applying for acceptance into an internship program. Acceptance into an internship program cannot be guaranteed.

All required accreditation information and requirements for attainment of the Verification Statement can be found at http://cehs.unl.edu/nhs/undergrad/dietetics.shtml.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 33

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 4. CHEM 109 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. PSYC 181 (Supporting Courses) 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. NUTR 253 (Professional Requirement) 3

ACE 10. NUTR 452 & NUTR 452L (Professional Requirement) 4

Professional Requirements (A grade of C or above is required) 40

NUTR 100, NUTR 244, NUTR 250, NUTR 251, NUTR 344, NUTR 356, NUTR 370, NUTR 402, NUTR 450, NUTR 453, NUTR 455, NUTR 473 (3 hrs ea) 36

NUTR 150, NUTR 245, NUTR 371, NUTR 490 (1 hr ea) 4

Supporting Courses 29-33

MATH 101 or higher 2-5

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L 4

BIOS 111 (4 hrs) or BIOS 312 (3 hrs) & BIOS 314 (1 hr) or NUTR 372 (3 hrs) 3-4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L 4

CHEM 110 4

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 4

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L 4

Electives 14-18

Total Hours 120

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their adviser prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

* These (*) courses, required in your major, will also meet ACE Requirements.

Professional Requirements

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health

NUTR 150 Foundations in Nutrition & Health Promotion

NUTR 244 & NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation & Lab

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

NUTR 251 Nutrition Through the Life Cycle

*NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

NUTR 344 Food & Nutrition for Healthy Living

NUTR 356 Nutrition Education in the Community

NUTR 370 Food Production Management

NUTR 371 Applied Food Production Lab

NUTR 402 Facts & Fiction in Fitness & Food

NUTR 450 Medical Nutrition Therapy I

*NUTR 452 Medical Nutrition Therapy II

*NUTR 452L Medical Nutrition Therapy II Lab

NUTR 453 Nutrition & Fitness Communication Strategies

NUTR 455 Advanced Nutrition

NUTR 473 Organization & Administration of Foodservice

NUTR 490 Professional Preparation for Careers in Dietetics

Supporting Courses

*EDPS 459 Statistical Methods or *STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics

*PSYC 181 Introduction to Psychology

MATH 101 College Algebra or higher, trigonometry or calculus

BIOS 111 The Biology of Microoganisms or BIOS 312 & BIOS 314 Microbiology & Lab or NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation (3-4 hrs)

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grades Earned at UNL, UNO, UNK

Grades of D-, D, D+, C- satisfy requirements of the programs in human sciences unless specified otherwise under the Programs and Departments section of the bulletin. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, or C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course, particularly if it is in the major area.

Grades Earned Outside UN System

Up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Policy for Pass/No Pass Courses

The Pass/No Pass (P/N) option is designed for students who want to study elective areas or topics when they may have minimum preparation. If used for this purpose, the option can enrich the student’s academic experience without lowering the student’s grade point average. Free electives may be taken P/N. Students can earn no more than 12 hours of pass credit excluding courses offered on Pass/No Pass only basis. Not all classes can be taken under the Pass/No Pass option. All courses, specified by course and number, must be taken for a grade. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed by the appropriate department.

PGA Golf Management

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: PGA Golf Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in PGA Golf Management

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Alan Baquet

DESCRIPTION

Director: Alan Baquet, PGA Golf Management Program, 203 Keim Hall

Faculty Advisory Committee: Heng-Moss (entomology); Karels (finance); Reicher (agronomy and horticulture); Schnepf (nutrition and health sciences)

Website: http://pgm.unl.edu

For students who wish to be educated in all aspects of the golf industry and become PGA members.
One of 19 accredited PGA Golf Management University Programs in the country.
Classroom instruction, a player development program taught by PGA professionals, and structured internship experiences provide a basic background in managing golf facilities and related organizations, business and personnel management, restaurant and hospitality management, recreation, and golf instruction methods.
PGA Golf Management Student Club conducts many tournaments each semester.
Graduates are eligible for PGA Class “A” membership.
Additional PGA Golf Management fees apply.

ADMISSION

Additional requirements for entrance to the PGA Golf Management Program

Proof of playing ability equivalent to 12 handicap or better.
Letter of acceptance from UNL PGA Golf Management Office (no separate application required).
Fall semester entrance only.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

Hours

College Integrative Courses 3

AGRI 103 Intro to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

Mathematics and Statistics (beyond college algebra) (ACE 3) 5-6

Select from: MATH 102, MATH 104, MATH 106 and STAT 218.

Communications 9

Written Communication (ACE 1) 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 120, JGEN 200, JGEN 300

Oral Communication (ACE 2) 3

Select from: COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 286

Leadership (ACE 2) 3

ALEC 102 Interpersonal Skills for Leadership

Natural Sciences 10-11

AGRO 131 Plant Science (ACE 4) 3

CHEM 105 Chemistry in Context I or CHEM 109 General Chemistry I (ACE 4) 4

CASNR Approved Life Sciences (select one from): 3-4

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab (4 hrs)

BIOS 109 General Botany (4 hrs)

ENTO 115 Insect Biology (3 hrs) (preferred)

Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences 12

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

Specific Major Requirements

Hours

Additional Plant Sciences 8

AGRO 153 Soil Resources 4

PGAM 227 Introductory Turfgrass Management & PGAM 229 Turfgrass Management Lab 4

Food Service Management 9

HRTM 374 Guest Services Management 3

HRTM 373 Catering 3

HRTM 474 Food & Beverage Management 3

Business (constitutes Business Minor) 18

ACCT 200 Survey of Accounting 3

BLAW 300 Business, Government & Society 3

ECON 200 Survey of Economic Principles (ACE 6) 3

FINA 300 Survey of Finance Principles 3

MNGT 300 Survey of Management 3

MRKT 300 Survey of Marketing 3

NOTE: The above block of six courses is for non-business majors. If a student switches to the College of Business Administration, these courses will not satisfy requirements for a business major or minor.

PGAM Courses 24

PGAM 101 Intro to Professional Golf Management 3

PGAM 112 PGM Professional Development: First Year 3

PGAM 201 Professional Golf Management Program: Level 1 3

PGAM 212 PGM Professional Development: Second Year 3

PGAM 295 Professional Golf Management Extended Internship 0

PGAM 301 Professional Golf Management Program: Level 2 3

PGAM 312 PGM Professional Development: Third Year 3

PGAM 401 Professional Golf Management Program: Level 3 3

PGAM 489 Professional Golf Management Integration (ACE 10) 3

Free Electives 20-22

Total Credit Hours 120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

GPA Requirements (related to the major)

Students are expected to maintain a 2.5 grade point average, which is required for the College of Business Administration courses.

Internship Credit Rules (related to the major)

Complete 16 months of internships in at least three different settings, the first of which must be at a golf course.

OTHER:

Participate in Playing Ability Test once in first year and twice each succeeding year until the PAT is passed.
Complete Level 3 of the PGA Golf Management program.

Pre-Forestry

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Pre-Forestry (Non-degree seeking)

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking only

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: James Brandle

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Professor James R. Brandle, School of Natural Resources, 407 Hardin Hall

Forestry deals with the development and use of forests and related lands for a variety of uses– wood, water, wildlife, forage, recreation, and aesthetics. Multiple use is the foundation upon which management of our national forests is based; foresters today, through their forest management programs, are expected to provide a broad array of benefits to meet public demands. Students graduating from forestry programs find employment with federal, state, and local governments, and with private industry.

CASNR offers a two-year pre-forestry program, but does not offer a four-year forestry degree. Students must transfer at the end of their freshman or sophomore year. Graduate training in forestry is offered by the School of Natural Resources.

The pre-forestry curriculum consists of 60-70 hours selected from the courses listed below. Course selection is based on a student’s background and career goals. A program of study will be developed by the student and the adviser that involves one or two years at the University of Nebraska before transferring to the University of Missouri or another accredited forestry school. If a student desires to enter the University of Nebraska and later transfer to a forestry school other than the University of Missouri, the student should obtain information about the school’s entrance requirements and curriculum as early as possible to avoid unnecessary loss of credit.

An agreement with the University of Missouri allows Nebraska residents with the proper scholastic qualifications to enter that institution without paying out-of-state fees. Under this program a student may enter the University of Missouri directly from high school or transfer after one or two years at the University of Nebraska. Students interested in pursuing a pre-forestry program should select courses from the list below:

Hours

STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics 3

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab 4

BIOS 109 General Botany 4

BIOS 112 Introduction to Zoology 4

CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 General Chemistry I & II 8

COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication or COMM 209 Public Speaking 3

ECON 211 Principles of Macroeconomics or ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics 3

ENGL 150 Writing: Rhetoric as Inquiry or ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument or ENGL 254 Writing & Communities 3

GEOL 101 Physical Geology 4

JGEN 200 Technical Communication 3

MATH 104 Calculus for Managerial & Social Sciences (3 cr) or MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I (5 cr) 3-5

NRES 101 Natural Resources Orientation 1

NRES 103/AGRI 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

PHYS 151/ASTR 151 Elements of Physics 4

SOIL 153 Introduction to Soil Science 4

Pre-Health

COLLEGE: Exploratory & Pre-Professional Advising Center

MAJOR: Pre-Health

DESCRIPTION

Pre-health areas of study are not majors at UNL but rather advising categories. Students interested in pursuing health care careers but have not yet decided on a major start their program of studies in the College of Arts and Sciences. Some students declare an academic major while working toward their professional school requirements and earn a degree from UNL before entering professional school. Some professional programs allow students to enter after completing school requirements without earning an undergraduate degree. In either case, students may choose a course of study in any of the following Pre-Health Categories while they are preparing for professional school and/or deciding on a major and degree. Students pursuing these categories while earning degrees from any undergraduate college at UNL can receive guidance and advice from the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center by declaring their pre-health category with their college advising office. Students who do not know which career path they might pursue are encouraged to explore the many options available by using ExploreHealthCareers.org website in addition to Career Services and the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center website and resources.

Pre-Chiropractic

Chiropractic is a branch of health care that focuses on manipulation as the best mode of care and treatment of many injuries and illnesses. It emphasizes the inter-relatedness of the body parts as a whole set, but especially as they relate to the function of the nervous system. Since the majority of the body’s organs are innervated by nerves which enter or leave the spine, a major emphasis is on the correct structure and function of the spine and the body joints.

Pre-Clinical Laboratory Science

Clinical Lab Science (formally Medical Technology) is the allied health profession concerned with performing laboratory tests that are used in the diagnosis, treatment, and prognosis of disease and in the maintenance of health. The clinical lab scientist performs a full range of laboratory tests, from simple pre-marital blood tests to more complex tests to uncover diseases, such as AIDS, diabetes, and cancer. The clinical lab scientist is also responsible for confirming the accuracy of test results and reporting laboratory findings to the pathologist and other doctors.

Pre-Clinical Perfusion Science

Perfusionists are skilled allied health professionals, qualified by academic and clinical education, who deal with all phases of regulating and controlling blood flow outside the body, called extracorporeal circulation. The perfusionist operates extracorporeal equipment during any medical situation where it is necessary to support, or temporarily replace, the patient’s circulatory or respiratory function. The perfusionist has diverse responsibilities which include the mechanical support of a patient’s circulation and pulmonary function during open heart surgery and is an integral member of the cardiovascular surgery team involved in infant and adult cardiac surgery.

Pre-Cytotechnology

Cytotechnology is an allied health specialty which offers exciting possibilities for those who want a career in science and a significant role in health care. Working with a microscope, cytotechnologists study specimens from all body sites. Using subtle clues in the cells themselves, cytotechnologists can solve the mystery of disease by diagnosing cancer, precancerous lesions, benign tumors, infectious agents, and inflammatory processes. Cytotechnologists help save lives by discovering certain diseases early when treatment is most effective.

Pre-Dental Hygiene

A dental hygienist is a preventive oral health professional licensed in dental hygiene to provide educational, clinical and therapeutic services supporting total health through the promotion of optimal oral health. The dental hygienist is responsible for providing treatment that helps to prevent oral diseases such as dental caries (cavities) and periodontal disease (gum disease) and for educating the patient to maintain optimal oral health.

Pre-Dentistry

Dentistry is devoted to maintaining the health of teeth and gums, as well as other hard and soft tissues of the mouth. Early detection of oral cancer and systemic conditions that manifest themselves through the mouth are necessary for the maintenance of general health. The dentist is, in fact, a person dedicated to the highest standards of health throughout the prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of all oral diseases and conditions.

Pre-Medicine

The medical profession (allopathic, osteopathic, or podiatric) offers a wide variety of career options that are exciting, challenging, and rewarding. Although the environment in which medical services are provided has been changing rapidly and will continue to change, the physician’s role as diagnostician, healer, and patient advocate remains central to the provision of health care in our country. Although most physicians provide direct patient care, some medical degree recipients concentrate on basic or applied research, become teachers or administrators, or combine various elements of these activities.

Pre-Mortuary Science

Completion of a professional program in mortuary science leads to licensure as a funeral director/embalmer. Morticians deal with funeral planning, death registration, embalming, and the grief and bereavement issues of families and friends of the deceased.

Pre-Nursing

The nursing profession offers a wide variety of career opportunities for men and women. Career choices range from highly technical positions in research or intensive care to “high touch” specialties such as hospice care or the newborn nursery. Nursing training programs range from associates to bachelors educational levels. Students who earn the BSN are prepared to assume staff nurse level positions in areas such as public health, gerontology, pediatrics, industrial settings, emergency medicine, psychiatric and mental health facilities, and acute care agencies. Students who desire advanced nursing degrees will find graduate programs leading to the masters and doctor of philosophy degrees in a variety of specialty areas.

Pre-Occupational Therapy

Occupational therapy is a health care profession using purposeful activity (occupation) as a means of preventing, reducing, or overcoming physical, social, and emotional challenges in people of all ages. An occupational therapist works with individuals whose participation in daily activities has been impaired by physical injury/illness, developmental/learning disabilities, psychological/emotional problems or the aging process. The occupational therapist carefully evaluates each person to determine physical and/or mental strengths and weaknesses, and, in conjunction with other health professionals, develops a program using purposeful activities and adaptive equipment to encourage the patient’s involvement in meaningful daily living.

Pre-Optometry

Optometry is the primary health profession dedicated to caring for vision. Through academic and clinical training, optometrists acquire the knowledge and skills needed to diagnose, treat, and prevent problems of the visual system. Providing health education, managing curative or preventive regimes, and supplying vision care to special groups of patients are all parts of an optometrist’s work.

Pre-Pharmacy

Pharmacists are responsible for drug therapy and drug distribution and must possess the scientific and technical knowledge necessary to evaluate drug therapy for each individual patient. They must develop skill in personal relations with patients and other health professionals. Above all, they must be able to make good use of acquired knowledge and experience in arriving at sound judgments and policy decisions.

Pre-Physical Therapy

As an important member of the health care team, physical therapists assess and treat disabilities and promote wellness to individuals of all ages. Their primary objective is to promote optimum human health and function. The physical therapist conducts physical evaluations to determine the patient’s potential for rehabilitation and life style changes indicated, as well as educates the patient and family.

Students can declare Pre-Physical Therapy through the College of Arts and Sciences or the College of Education and Human Sciences. The Pre-Physical Therapy category does not vary based on the UNL undergraduate college. Students who see themselves pursuing an undergraduate major in the College of Arts and Sciences should choose that college for their degree program, while students interested in an academic major offered through the College of Education and Human Sciences should declare that college for completing their degree. The academic advisers in the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center will assist students from any college with their pre-physical therapy requirements.

Pre-Physician Assistant

The physician assistant (PA) practices medicine with the supervision of a physician. As a result of extensive medical training, the PA can assume many tasks traditionally performed only by a medical doctor, thereby helping the physician to be more efficient. Each supervising physician utilizes the services of a PA based on his/her own practice needs. Typically the PA obtains the patient’s medical history, performs a comprehensive physical examination, and orders appropriate laboratory and x-ray studies. The PA diagnoses and treats a wide range of common medical problems, and assists the physician in the management of complex chronic illnesses. Many PAs make hospital and nursing home rounds and assist in surgery. A very important part of the PA’s role is to educate the patient and the community about illness, family planning, social services, health hazards, baby and child care, and other aspects of health promotion and disease prevention.

Pre-Radiation Science Technology

Radiation science technology comprises several disciplines that utilize radiation for diagnosis or treatment, including but not limited to radiography, nuclear medicine, diagnostic medical sonography, or radiation therapy technology. Students should explore options in radiation science to see which field best fits their skills and interests. The career options available to students interested in radiation sciences continually expands as technology develops.

Medical imaging is the specialty of the radiologic technologist (or radiographer at the advanced level training). As part of the radiology team, the technologist uses radiation and other modalities to produce images of the tissues, organs, bones and vessels of the human body. The radiographer positions the patient and applies the exact quantity and the precise quality of radiation necessary to produce the image. Physicians trained in radiology interpret the images and diagnose the conditions shown.

The field of nuclear medicine technology uses radioactivity to help find diseases or other conditions in people, to treat some diseases, and to investigate better methods of diagnosis. Disorders in any part of the body may be studied—for example, a blood clot in the lungs or brain, altered rhythm of the heart, or infections in the bone or tissues. The nuclear medicine technologist has many responsibilities: caring for the patient, assuring that equipment is operating properly, preparing radioactive drugs, and performing the actual procedures.

Pre-Veterinary Science

Veterinarians are best known for healing animals, but veterinary medical research has been helpful for humans too. For instance, more and more links are being found between human and animal diseases, such as SARS, mad cow disease, West Nile virus, and avian flu, among others. Thus, a degree in veterinary medicine can prepare students for careers in public health and research. Veterinary science is a degree program in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources and students wishing to pursue veterinary medicine can complete the requirements for colleges of veterinary medicine while completing their degree in CASNR.

ADMISSION

High School Preparation

Students planning to pursue advanced work in any of the Pre-Health programs should begin with a strong college preparatory course program in high school. In addition to meeting the University entrance requirements, it is recommended that pre-health students finish four years of the same foreign language in high school. Pre-health students are also encouraged to take as many years of mathematics and science as possible while paying close attention to the use of pre-university earned credit options such as Advanced Placement, International Baccalaureate, and Dual Enrollment/Dual Credit options. Some health professional schools will not accept or will limit acceptance and applicability of prerequisite credit earned by examination or prior to high school graduation. Students should consult with an academic adviser in the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center or their high school guidance counselor when choosing to earn credit prior to graduating from high school.

Admission to Professional Programs

The admission requirements for health professional programs vary and may change from year to year. Admission to the professional programs is competitive. Therefore, students need to be aware of not only specific course requirements but also entrance exams, admission deadlines, research and volunteer opportunities, and other activities that enhance the application. In order to receive the timeliest information on requirements and preparation, students should visit or contact the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center, 33 Canfield, 402-472-3605, explorecenter@unl.edu. Information is also available on the website http://explorecenter.unl.edu/.

Pre-Law

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Pre-Law (Non-degree seeking)

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking only

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: David Aiken

DESCRIPTION

Law schools prefer students with broad academic backgrounds. Accordingly, there is no “prelaw” designation. Study toward a bachelor of science degree is excellent prelaw curriculum. There are no particular degree programs or courses students are advised to take to enhance their chances of admission to law school. Students should choose programs and courses that interest them. However, students should take many courses that require writing and complex readings. Students, especially those uncertain about law school, may want to take some courses that focus on law and the courts. While these courses will not enhance chances of admission, they will provide information about the legal system and the legal profession.

Prospective applicants are advised to take the Law School Admission Test (LSAT) during the summer before their last year or the fall of their last year. Information and application materials are available from the Career Services. The Official Guide to US Law Schools, available from the LSAT organization, contains material about the legal profession, the law school experience, the application process, and the individualized information on all American law schools approved by the American Bar Association.

CASNR students contemplating application to law school may contact Professor David Aiken, adviser in the Department of Agricultural Economics, 103 Filley Hall.

Pre-Law (EC)

COLLEGE: Exploratory & Pre-Professional Advising Center

MAJOR: Pre-Law (Explore Center)

DESCRIPTION

Law is the system we use to ensure order and justice for individuals and communities within our society. The broad nature of the legal field allows people to work with the law in a number of ways. Litigation (trial practice), representative practice, legal planning, education, and adjudication (becoming a judge) are traditional ways in which people work directly with the law. However, a legal education is useful and may be applied to a variety of other fields such as business, insurance, government, writing, resource management, or publishing.

The pre-law area of study is not a major at UNL but rather an advising category. Students interested in pursuing legal careers but have not yet decided on a major start their program of studies in the College of Arts and Sciences. Some students declare an academic major and earn a degree from UNL before entering professional school using their undergraduate academic program to develop the desired skill set for entry into law school and the legal profession. Students pursuing the Pre-Law category while earning degrees from any undergraduate college at UNL can receive guidance and advice from the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center by declaring their pre-law category with their college advising office.

High School Preparation

Students planning to pursue advanced work in the Pre-Law program should begin with a strong college preparatory course program in high school. In addition to meeting the University entrance requirements, it is recommended that pre-law students finish four years of the same foreign language in high school.

Admission to Professional Programs

The admission requirements for law professional programs vary and may change from year to year. Admission to the professional programs is competitive. Therefore, students need to be aware of academic recommendations, entrance exams, admission deadlines, research and volunteer opportunities, and other activities that enhance the application. In order to receive the timeliest information on requirements and preparation, students should visit or contact the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center, 33 Canfield, 402-472-3605, explorecenter@unl.edu. Information is also available on the website http://explorecenter.unl.edu/.

ADMISSION TO PRE-LAW

Pre-law is not a major at UNL but rather an advising category. Students may follow a pre-law area of study while pursing any degree/major at UNL. Students who are unsure of which college/major they would like to pursue, may initially apply to the College of Arts and Sciences as a Pre-Law student. Please review the entrance requirements for the College of Arts and Sciences in the college’s section of the bulletin at http://bulletin.unl.edu/undergraduate/college/Arts+%26+Sciences.

ADVISING FOR PRE-LAW

Students are advised in the pre-law area of study by professional academic advisers in the Explore Center. Advisers are available on an appointment and/or walk-in basis Monday through Friday in 33 Canfield Administration Building and can be reached at 402-472-3605 or explorecenter@unl.edu.

COLLEGE REQUIREMENTS FOR PRE-LAW

Students should check the section of the bulletin outlining the requirements for their specific college of admittance. Those students undecided on a major who were admitted as Pre-Law students to the College of Arts and Sciences should review the college requirements outlined in the college’s section of the bulletin at http://bulletin.unl.edu/undergraduate/major/Pre-Health%2C+Pre-Law+and+Combined+Degree+Programs.

Pre-Veterinary Medicine

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Pre-Veterinary Medicine (Non-degree seeking)

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking only

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Laura Hardin

DESCRIPTION

Director: Professor David Hardin, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, 120C Vet Basic Sciences

Head: Professor Larry Berger, Department of Animal Science, C203 Animal Sciences

Individuals wishing to enter the four-year professional curriculum leading to the degree, doctor of veterinary medicine (DVM), must first complete two or more years of pre-veterinary general education. Courses taken during pre-professional education must satisfy the entrance prerequisites for the college of veterinary medicine of the person’s choice. At the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, it usually requires a minimum of three years to complete the pre-professional requirements, but students must declare an acceptable degree program at the conclusion of their sophomore year. Certain options in the veterinary science and veterinary technology degree programs meet the pre-veterinary requirements of colleges of veterinary medicine. 8 The student should discuss special variations and other colleges of interest with their academic adviser at the earliest possible date.

The Pre-Veterinary Program IS NOT a degree-granting program. Completion of the pre-professional program alone in fulfilling the prerequisites for admission to a college or school of veterinary medicine does not result in the awarding of a degree from the University of Nebraska. Students are to select an appropriate field within which to work toward a college degree while concurrently working toward completion of pre-professional requirements. Students are encouraged to consider courses of study with a degree-granting program in veterinary science (biomedical science, microbiology options, or veterinary medicine options), veterinary technology, animal science, food science and technology, biochemistry or other fields compatible with the pre-professional program that leads to a bachelor of science degree. Students can also complete pre-veterinary prerequisites with a degree program in wildlife or environmental studies, leading to a bachelor of science degree. It is also possible to pursue these pre-veterinary requirements in degree-granting programs outside the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, such as the College of Arts and Sciences.

Students are expected to designate an acceptable degree program by the end of their sophomore year and to work with an adviser in that field. Additional advisory support relating to pre-professional requirements and admission policies is provided by advisers within the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

The program utilizes an “Advising Plus” model which involves faculty from the School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences (Laura Hardin, Rodney Moxley, and Michael Carlson) and the Department of Animal Science (Dennis Brink and Thomas Burkey). Team advising will be utilized to expose students to all the opportunities in animal health and assist them in identifying the appropriate degree program.

Students interested in veterinary medicine are encouraged to participate in the Pre-veterinary Club to learn about the exciting advancement and developments within the profession.

It is not recommended that pre-veterinary students take any courses on a Pass/No Pass basis (unless this is the only grading option for a given course, e.g. VBMS 101) because courses taken Pass/No Pass may not be accepted for pre-professional prerequisites. Letter grades are required to evaluate credentials of applicants for veterinary college admission.

See individual degree programs for specializations in those areas.

Psychology

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Psychology

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Celeste Spier

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Rick Bevins, 238 Burnett Hall

Vice Chairs: David DiLillo and Eve Brank, 238 Burnett Hall

Professors: Belli, Bevins, Bornstein, Crockett, DiLillo, Garbin, Hansen, Hope, Leger, Molfese, Pope-Edwards, Spaulding, Tomkins, Wiener, Wilcox

Associate Professors: Brank, Hoffman, Li, McChargue, Scalora, Schutte, Willis-Esqueda

Assistant Professors: Dodd, Gervais, Nelson, Stevens, Stoltenberg, Templin

The undergraduate degree program in psychology is designed to provide students with educational experiences that are conducive to entering diverse careers ranging from academic psychology to such applied fields as counseling, business, and human services. Careful selection of courses from within the required groups and of supplementary courses in psychology and related fields will help students pursue their chosen career. Students who plan to major in psychology should meet with a departmental adviser as early as possible to plan a program of courses consistent with their interests and goals.

Graduate Work. Graduate programs leading to the doctor of philosophy degree are offered in the department. A detailed description of these courses appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

1. PSYC 181

2. PSYC 100

3. Two courses from each of the following groups:

Group 1 (natural science): PSYC 233, PSYC 263, PSYC 265, PSYC 268, PSYC 270, PSYC 360, PSYC 373

Group 2 (social science): PSYC 287, PSYC 288, PSYC 289, PSYC 380

4. PSYC 350

5. One course from each of the following groups:

Group 1 (natural science): PSYC 456, PSYC 458, PSYC 460, PSYC 461, PSYC 463, PSYC 464, PSYC 465, PSYC 466, or BIOS 462

Group 2 (social science): PSYC 462, PSYC 483, PSYC 485, PSYC 486, PSYC 489

6. Any two additional 400-level courses, excluding 496, 497, 499.

7. Total credit hours required: 33

Appropriate credit toward the psychology major requirements will be granted for psychology courses that are cross-listed in other departments but taken in another department. Credit toward the major will be granted even if the course is applied to another major or minor.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, selected majors will be required:

1. To submit copies of work produced in 200-, 300-, and 400-level courses to an assessment committee.

2. In their last semester, to complete a written exit survey.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass credit may be taken in major requirements. Majors may take up to 6 hours Pass/No Pass in their minor(s), subject to the approval of the department(s) granting the minor(s). Students minoring in this department may take up to 6 hours Pass/No Pass.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A (1 minor):

1. PSYC 181

2. 14 credit hours at the 200 level or above, 9 of which must be at the 300 level or above.

Minimum: 18 credit hours

Plan B (2 minors):

1. PSYC 181

2. Plus three other courses at the 200 level or above.

Minimum: 12 credit hours.

No more than 3 hours from the following courses can count toward the minor: PSYC 296, PSYC 297, PSYC 299, PSYC 396, PSYC 496, PSYC 497, or PSYC 499.

Public Policy Analysis & Program Evaluation Certification

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Public Policy Analysis & Program Evaluation Certification

DEGREES OFFERED: Certification Program Only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINOR AVAILABLE: Certification Program Only

CHIEF ADVISER: Kevin Smith

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator and Chief Adviser: Kevin Smith (political science), 529 Oldfather Hall

Core Faculty: Blake, Krone, Michaels, Smith

The program trains students to analyze systematically and coherently public policies, negotiate multiple and competing interests, and develop in-depth knowledge and application in substantive policy issues.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Principles and Requirements for the Public Policy Analysis Certificate

1. First Level

Covers the theories, processes, models, and methods of policy analysis. (6 cr) (both courses required)

POLS 235 Public Policy: Concepts & Processes (3 cr)

POLS 236 Public Policy Analysis: Methods & Models (3 cr)

2. Second Level

Examines the interpersonal, interagency and inter-group negotiation processes within which policy making occurs. (3 cr) (select one)

COMM 211 Intercultural Communication (ETHN 211) (3 cr)

COMM 371 Communication in Negotiation & Conflict Resolution (3 cr)

COMM 375 Theories of Persuasion (3 cr)

POLS 261 Conflict & Conflict Resolution (ANTH 261/PSYC 261/SOCI 261) (3 cr)

3. Third Level

Applies models, methods, and the understanding of the policy process in substantive policy arenas. Students consult with the policy certificate coordinator to create a specialized plan of study for this level. (6 cr)

4. Fourth Level

Internship (3 cr) (capstone experience) Students intern in a governmental or nonprofit agency relating to their area of interest or expertise. The internship generally occurs after completing or during the last semester of course work for the certificate. The political science undergraduate adviser as well as the policy certificate coordinator will help students find an appropriate policy-relevant internship. Academic requirements for the internship will be set by the certificate coordinator; however, the student can register for internship credit through political science or their major department.

TOTAL: 18 cr

Supply Chain Management

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Supply Chain Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (33 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

CHIEF ADVISER: David Olson

DESCRIPTION

Director: David L. Olson

Professor: Schniederjans

Associate Professors: Swenseth, Trimi

Assistant Professors: Batur, Thornton

The College of Business Administration at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln has established an undergraduate supply chain management major to educate students to become supply chain management professionals. Supply chain management (SCM) includes all the activities that must take place to get the right products and services into the right customer’s hands in the right quantity at the right time—from raw material extraction to consumer purchase.

The topics that SCM covers are diverse and include: procurement, order fulfillment, inventory management, supplier relationship management, product development and commercialization, returns management, physical distribution and shipping, warehousing, and outsourcing. With the depth and breadth of issues that it encompasses, industries that use SCM tools and approaches include: transportation, hospitals, government organizations, construction, processing, social services, electronics, facility design, manufacturing, and warehousing.

The course work for the supply chain management major (bachelor of science in business administration) consists of 120 credit hours, 33 of which are specific to the major. A focus of the course work is developing the three foundational areas of supply chain management: procurement, logistics, and operations. The program offers integration among these critical, value-adding components to enhance global competitiveness. Twenty-one hours of required course work is intended to provide students with an understanding of supply chain and logistic activities, development of strong quantitative and analytic skills, and introduction to tools to explore and improve a system. Students will complete an additional 12 hours of course work from directed electives in supporting fields such as accounting, finance, management information systems, leadership and/or marketing.

ADMISSION

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 33 hours of course work for the major.

All students, regardless of their major or interests in the College will take SCMS 331/MNGT 331 and SCMS 350/MNGT 350 as part of the Business Core Foundation requirements.

NONE of these courses may be used to count toward the major.

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

All course work for the major must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).

The requirements for the major in addition to the general College requirements, consists of 21 hours of required major courses as listed:

SCMS 335 Supply Chain Decision Making Models

MRKT 346/SCMS 346 Distribution Channels Management

MNGT 431/SCMS 431 Enterprise Management Systems

SCMS 432 Supply Chain Planning & Control Systems

MRKT 444/SCMS 444 Supply Chain Logistics

SCMS 439 Global Sourcing & Distribution

SCMS 474 Strategic Supply Chain Management

As well as 12 hours from the following directed electives:

ACCT 308 Managerial Accounting

MNGT 311 Leadership, Communications, & Teams

MRKT 345 Marketing Research

FINA 375 Financial Statement Analysis

MRKT 425 Retail Management

MNGT 437/SCMS 437 Supply Chain Risk Management

MRKT 450 Strategic Database Marketing

MNGT 454/SCMS 454 Information Systems Analysis & Design

MNGT 458/SCMS 458 Electronic Business

MNGT 459/SCMS 459 Global Information Technology & IS

SCMS 434 Lean Supply Chain Operations

SCMS 436 Project Management

SCMS 447 Supply Chain Technology

SCMS 452/MNGT 452 Database Organization & Management

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College Grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

OTHER

Supply Chain Management Major

All course work for the major must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass). Course work applied to the SCMS major cannot be used towards the completion of any other major or minor in the college.

Theatre–Directing & Management Emphasis

COLLEGE: Fine & Performing Arts

MAJOR: Theatre–Directing & Management emphasis

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Harris Smith

DESCRIPTION

Director: Paul Steger, 215 Temple Building

Professors: Grange, V. Smith, Steger

Associate Professors: Brown, Endacott, H. Smith, E. Stauffer, J. Stauffer, Teo-Gooding

Assistant Professors: Borden, Kolbe, Shoemaker, Veneziano

Assistant Professor of Practice: Patterson

This program provides comprehensive training and practical experience in directing, stage management and theatre management. It shares a common core with our performance program, offering fundamental training in acting, movement and voice for the first three semesters. Specialized classes follow in stage management, theatre management, and beginning and advanced directing. The culmination of the emphasis is four mentored projects in the student’s area of specialty or a combination of projects in several areas.

Degree at a Glance

Hours

ACE Requirements 30

Languages: Classical and Modern 0-6

Select from the list of “Approved Courses” found under “College Degree Requirements.”

Library 110 1

Theatre Core Requirements 39

Directing and Management Emphasis Requirements 22

Electives 22-28

Total Hours Required for Graduation 120

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Students must apply for admission to the directing and management emphasis by completing an application form, supplying references, a resume, and examples of creative work. The acceptance process for both new and transfer students includes an interview and analysis of the overall academic and artistic record, and determination of the potential for success throughout the course of study.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

Hours

BA Core Requirements 39

THEA 112G Introduction to Theatre 3

THEA 114 Basic Acting Techniques I 3

THEA 115 Basic Acting Techniques II 3

THEA 201 Technical Theatre Practice 3

THEA 202 Play Direction I 3

THEA 204 Stage Makeup 3

THEA 223 Intermediate Acting I 3

THEA 234 Scripts in Performance 3

THEA 253 Voice Production for the Stage 3

THEA 255 Stage Movement I 3

THEA 335 History of Theatre I 3

THEA 336 History of Theatre II 3

THEA 472 Theatre Perspectives 3

Emphasis Requirements

Hours

Directing and Management Emphasis Requirements 22

THEA 300 Stage Management 3

THEA 301 Theatre Management 3

THEA 303 Stage Directing II 3

THEA 491 Advanced Projects in Directing, Stage Management &/or
Theatre Management 4

Select three courses from: 9

THEA 120 Principles of Design for Theatre & Film (3 cr)

THEA 331 Introduction to Playwriting (3 cr)

THEA 410 Stage Lighting I (3 cr)

THEA 411 Stage Lighting II (3 cr)

THEA 412 Scene Design I (3 cr)

THEA 413 Scene Design II (3 cr)

THEA 418 Costume Design I (3 cr)

THEA 419 Costume Design II (3 cr)

THEA 450 Sound Design I (3 cr)

THEA 451 Sound Design II (3 cr)

Minor Requirements

Minors are allowed, but not required, with the theatre–directing and management emphasis.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Advancement in Major

An interview/evaluation will be scheduled with directing and management students after their third semester to determine whether they may continue in the program.
Students in the Theatre-Directing and Management emphasis are expected to maintain a 2.5 cumulative GPA throughout their career. Transcripts will be reviewed periodically to ensure satisfactory progress. Failure to maintain a 2.5 GPA may result in dismissal from the program.

Grade Rules

All courses taken for major requirements must be for letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.
Minimum grade for all major requirements is C.

Undeclared

COLLEGE: Exploratory & Pre-Professional Advising Center

MAJOR: Undeclared

DESCRIPTION

The Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center (Explore Center) provides an academic home for students who are still deciding upon a major or who are transitioning between majors. The Center does not award degrees and students will transfer to one of the eight undergraduate colleges when they have chosen an academic major and degree program.

Professional academic advisers in the Explore Center engage undecided students in major exploration, degree planning, and academic course work selection processes. By working closely with all of the UNL colleges, Explore Center advisers can help students design a general academic plan for one or more semesters that will allow them to progress toward a degree, while also exploring the variety of opportunities offered by the University. Students are encouraged to enroll in exploratory courses to help identify majors of interest. Additionally, all UNL students are required to complete the Achievement-Centered Education (ACE) requirements (for more information see http://ace.unl.edu).

Undeclared students are encouraged to meet with a professional academic adviser in the Explore Center early in their first semester at UNL to discuss interest areas and to develop a plan for major exploration. Additional information concerning major exploration can be found on the Explore Center (http://explorecenter.unl.edu) and Career Services (www.unl.edu/careers/explore) websites.

ADMISSION

Program Admission

Students who have met the overall University admission requirements established by the Board of Regents are eligible for admission to the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center. The University admission requirements are outlined in detail on the Admissions site at http://admissions.unl.edu/.

Some UNL colleges have admission requirements in addition to the overall University admission requirements, and undecided students will be advised accordingly as they choose the majors they would like to pursue in their chosen colleges.

To be considered for admission a transfer student, Nebraska resident or nonresident, must meet the overall University admission requirements established by the Board of Regents. The University admission requirements are outlined in detail on the Admissions site at http://admissions.unl.edu/.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Because admission requirements establish the level of knowledge and skills which are needed for a student to succeed at UNL, students who are admitted with core course deficiencies in foreign language and geometry are expected to quickly remove them. Deficiencies must be removed before a student is eligible for graduation.

ADVISING

Students are assigned to a professional academic adviser in the Explore Center but may see any adviser in the center. Professional advisers in the Explore Center are available on an appointment and/or walk-in basis Monday through Friday in 33 Canfield Administration Building and can be reached at 402-472-3605 or explorecenter@unl.edu.

ACADEMIC POLICIES

Academic Load

Undeclared students may enroll in a maximum of 18 credits in the fall and spring semesters. Students should refer to the Summer Schedule of Classes to determine the number of credits they may enroll in for each of the summer sessions.

Grade Rules

The Pass/No Pass grading option was designed to enable students to take courses in areas of interest where they may feel they have had minimal preparation without adversely affecting their grade point average. Grades of P (pass) are interpreted as a grade of C or better. Neither grade P or N (no pass) contributes to the grade point average.

Undecided students should always seek assistance from their adviser in determining whether they should take a course on the Pass/No Pass option. Students may or may not be able to take courses Pass/No Pass depending on their intended majors.

Student Recognition

Students who complete at least 12 graded semester hours with a 3.60 GPA are eligible for the Undecided Students Honor Roll.

Transfer Credit Rules

Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center does not offer a degree. Thus advisers do not make transfer evaluation decisions. The determination of which transfer courses will meet graduation requirements in a specific college cannot be made until the student declares a specific major within one of the eight undergraduate degree-granting colleges.

Water Science

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Water Science

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Water Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Steven Thomas

DESCRIPTION

Water Science Curriculum Committee: Thomas, Chair (natural resources), Eisenhauer (biological systems engineering), Gates (geosciences), Lenters (natural resources), Lubben (agricultural economics), Thomas (natural resources)

Adviser: Steven Thomas, 403 Hardin Hall, 402-472-4030, sthomas5@unl.edu

Website: http://snr.unl.edu/undergrad/programs/water.asp

Facebook: UNL Water Science Major

The degree program in water science is designed to educate students in basic and applied sciences related to water resources. The goal is to educate individuals to gather and synthesize information from several disciplines, to formulate rational and broadly informed solutions to complex water related problems, and to effectively implement various water-based programs.

The curriculum is designed to meet the needs of students who intend to pursue careers in public and private organizations that conduct scientific water research or manage water resources, in private consulting companies that offer water research or management services, in agencies that form or implement water related policy, and in a broad range of nonprofit institutions that are interested in water resources. The program also provides students the opportunity to prepare for graduate study in water/hydrological sciences and water resources.

A minimum of 120 credit hours is required for the bachelor of science degree. Of these requirements, 43-48 credits are in an integrated water science curriculum designed to provide both breadth and depth in water resources. The water science degree program also requires 21 credit hours of science and mathematics. In addition, the student must select an option area consisting of approximately 18-26 credit hours. The option allows students to develop an individualized area of study. To complete the degree the student must take 24 credit hours of communication, humanities and social science courses.

Option areas include:

Aquatic Ecology

Hydrology

Watershed Management

Water Law and Policy

Water Quality

Application for UNL freshman scholarships automatically makes you eligible for SNR scholarships. Many scholarships are available, including the Viessman Scholarship, specifically for students in water science. For more information, visit http://snr.unl.edu.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

Hours

Natural Resources Core 3

NRES 103/AGRI 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems 3

Natural Sciences 13

CASNR Approved Life Sciences (ACE 4) 4

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab (4 cr)

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I (ACE 4) 4

Select one from the following: 5

MSYM 109 & MSYM 109L Physical Principles in Agriculture & Life Sciences & Lab (5 cr)

PHYS 141 Elementary General Physics I (5 cr)

PHYS 151 & PHYS 153 Elements of Physics & Lab (5 cr)

PHYS 211 & PHYS 221 General Physics I & Lab (5 cr)

Mathematics and Statistics (ACE 3) 8

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I or MATH 106B Calculus I for Biology & Medicine 5

STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics 3

Communication 9

Written Communication (ACE 1) 3

Select from: ENGL 150, ENGL 151, ENGL 254; JGEN 120, JGEN 200, JGEN 300

Oral Communication (ACE 2) 3

Select from: COMM 109, COMM 209, COMM 286

Communication and Interpersonal Skills Electives 3

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I or JGEN 300 Technical Communication II or NRES 260 Environmental Communications Skills

Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences 15

ECON 211 or ECON 212 or AECN 141 (ACE 6) 3

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

Specific Major Requirements

Hours

Water Science Core Courses 30-34

CIVE 353 Hydrology 3

Select from: 3-4

GEOL 100 Introduction to Geology (3 cr)

GEOL 101 Physical Geology (4 cr)

GEOL 106 Environmental Geology (3 cr)

NRES 108 Earth’s Natural Resource Systems Lab (3 cr)

Select from: 3-4

METR 200 Weather & Climate (4 cr)

NRES 208 Applied Climate Sciences (3 cr)

NRES 408 Microclimate: The Biological Environment (3 cr)

NRES 220 & NRES 222 Principles of Ecology & Lab 4

NRES 312 Introduction to Geospatial Information Sciences or NRES 412 Introduction to Geographic Information Systems 3-4

NRES 484 Water Resources Seminar 1

SOIL 153 Soil Resources 4

WATS 281 Introduction to Water Science 3

WATS 354 Soil Conservation & Watershed Management 3

ENVR 499A Environmental Studies Senior Thesis I (1 cr) & ENVR 499B Environmental Studies Senior Thesis II (2 cr) or ENVR 499H Honors: Environmental Studies Senior Thesis I & II (3 cr) or WATS 498A & WATS 498B Senior Project I & II (2 cr ea) 3-4

NOTE: The Senior Project fulfills the capstone requirement for water science students. The project is usually provided by private industry, government agencies, or nonprofit organizations. The senior thesis consists of research designed by the student along with the aid of faculty.

Law, Policy and Management 6

Select two of the following:

AECN 357 Natural Resource & Environmental Law (3 cr)

CRPL 470 Environmental Planning & Policy (3 cr)

NRES 323 Natural Resources Policy (3 cr)

NRES 423 Integrated Resources Management (3 cr)

WATS 465 Resource & Environmental Economics II (3 cr)

WATS 475 Water Quality Strategy (3 cr)

Science and Technology 6-8

Select two of the following:

NRES 463 Fisheries Science (4 cr)

NRES 488 Groundwater Geology (3 cr)

WATS 361 Soils, Environment & Water Quality (3 cr)

WATS 418 Chemistry of Natural Waters (3 cr)

WATS 452 Irrigation Systems Management (3 cr)

WATS 459 Limnology (4 cr) or WATS 468 Wetlands (4 cr) (or students may substitute NRES 498 River & Stream Ecology)

NOTE: Courses taken in the Water Science Core do not count toward the Water Science Options.

Major Requirements 42-48

Core Requirements 48

Core and Major Requirements Subtotal 90-96

Option Requirements and Electives 18-26

Free Electives 0-12

Total Credit Hours for Graduation 120

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Students must consult with an adviser to select an option prior to the beginning of their junior year.

NOTE: Courses taken in the Water Science Options do not count toward the Water Science Core.

Aquatic Ecology Option

This option is designed for students interested in lake, river, stream, or wetland ecology. Students are prepared for careers as research scientists or technicians with public agencies, private consulting firms, universities, and nonprofit organizations. Completion of this program provides excellent preparation for graduate study.

Hours

Option Requirements 15-16

BIOS 109 General Botany or BIOS 112 & BIOS 112L Introduction to Zoology & Lab 4

BIOS 457 Ecosystem Ecology (4 cr) or GEOL 424 Biogeochemical Cycles (3 cr) 3-4

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II 4

WATS 459 Limnology (or students may substitute NRES 498 River & Stream Ecology) 4

Electives 3-4

Select one of the following electives:

BIOS 473 Freshwater Algae (4 cr)

NRES 402 Aquatic Insects & NRES 402L Identification of Aquatic Insects (3 cr)

NRES 470 Lake & Reservoir Restoration (3 cr)

NRES 468 Wetlands (4 cr)

NRES 489 Ichthyology (4 cr)

Aquatic Ecology Option Requirements 18-20

Free Electives 4-12

Hydrology Option

This option trains students in the quantitative aspects of hydrologic sciences and is designed for students considering careers as a professional hydrologist, research scientist, or consultant (among others). Completion of this program provides excellent preparation for graduate study.

Hours

Option Requirements 15

NRES 488 Groundwater Geology 3

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 4

PHYS 212 & PHYS 222 General Physics II & Lab 5

WATS 461 Soil Physics 3

Electives 3-4

Select one of the following electives:

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II (4 cr)

CIVE 456 Surface Water Hydrology (3 cr)

GEOL 472 Water in Geosciences (3 cr)

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III (4 cr)

MATH 221 Differential Equations (3 cr)

WATS 479 Hydroclimatology (3 cr)

Hydrology Option Requirements 18-19

Free Electives 5-12

Water Law and Policy Option

Under this option, a student gains expertise in water issues pertaining to water quality, quantity, allocation, and planning. Careers in this rapidly emerging field of water include lobbyists, community planners, public and tribal liaisons, and policy makers to name some. This option also prepares students for continued education in water law.

NOTE: Students in the Water Law and Policy Option should select AECN 357 under the Law Policy, and Management cluster of the Water Science core.

Hours

Option Requirements 21

AECN 265 Resource & Environmental Economics I 3

AECN 456 Environmental Law 3

AECN 457 Water Law 3

CRPL 470 Environmental Planning & Policy 3

ECON 211 Principles of Macroeconomics 3

POLS 235 Public Policy: Concepts & Processes 3

SOCI 446 Environmental Sociology 3

Water Law and Policy Option Requirements 21

Free Electives 3-9

Water Quality Option

This option trains students with a desire to pursue a career examining water chemistry or quality within lakes, streams, rivers, and groundwater. This option is designed for students considering careers as water quality specialists, research scientists, laboratory and field technicians, water or environmental chemists, and many more.

Hours

Option Requirements 16-17

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II 4

CHEM 251 Organic Chemistry I (3 cr) or CHEM 221 Elementary Quantitative Analysis (4 cr) 3-4

GEOL 418 Chemistry of Natural Waters 3

NRES 475 Water Quality Strategy 3

SOIL 361 Soils, Environment, & Water Quality 3

Electives 6-9

Select two of the following electives:

BIOS 312 Microbiology (3 cr)

CIVE 456 Surface Water Hydrology (3 cr)

GEOL 424 Biogeochemical Cycles (3 cr)

GEOL 472 Water in Geosciences (3 cr)

NRES 470 Lake & Reservoir Restoration (3 cr)

NRES 488 Groundwater Geology (3 cr)

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II (4 cr)

PHYS 212 General Physics II (4 cr)

STAT 318 Introduction to Statistics II (3 cr)

WATS 459 Limnology (or students may substitute NRES 498 River & Stream Ecology) (4 cr)

Water Quality Option Requirements 22-26

Free Electives 0-8

Watershed Management Option

Watershed management is the management of the water, land, and biological resources to achieve a desired outcome of the water quality and water quantity. This option is designed for students considering careers as water resource managers working for local, state, and federal agencies and private consultants.

Hours

Option Requirements 20

AECN 357 Natural Resource & Environmental Law 3

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II 4

NRES 488 Groundwater Geology 3

WATS 361 Soils, Environment & Water Quality 3

WATS 452 Irrigation Systems Management 3

WATS 459 Limnology (or students may substitute NRES 498 River & Stream Ecology) 4

Watershed Management Option Requirements 20

Free Electives 4-10

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Hours

Required Courses 6

WATS 281 Introduction to Water Science 3

WATS 354 Soil Conservation & Watershed Management 3

Advanced Courses 9-11

Law, Policy and Management 3

Select at least one of the following:

AECN 357 Natural Resource & Environmental Law (3 cr)

CRPL 470 Environmental Planning & Policy (3 cr)

NRES 423 Integrated Resources Management (3 cr)

WATS 465 Resource & Environmental Economics II (3 cr)

WATS 475 Water Quality Strategy (3 cr)

Science and Technology 6-8

Select at least two of the following:

CIVE 353 Hydrology (3 cr)

NRES 463 Fisheries Science (4 cr)

NRES 488 Groundwater Geology (3 cr)

WATS 361 Soils, Environment & Water Quality (3 cr)

WATS 408 Microclimate: The Biological Environment (3 cr)

WATS 418 Chemistry of Natural Waters (3 cr)

WATS 452 Irrigation Systems Management (3 cr)

WATS 459 Limnology (4 cr) or WATS 468 Wetlands (4 cr) (or students may substitute NRES 498 River & Stream Ecology)